<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="GEN" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the earth was waste and void; and darkness was upon the face of the deep: and the Spirit of God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was brooding upon</char></char></note>moved upon the face of the waters. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And God said, Let there be light: and there was light. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And God saw the light, that it was good: and God divided the light from the darkness. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And God called the light Day, and the darkness he called Night. And there was evening and there was morning, one day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And God said, Let there be a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">expanse</char>.</char></note>firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it divide the waters from the waters. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And God made the firmament, and divided the waters which were under the firmament from the waters which were above the firmament: and it was so. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And God called the firmament Heaven. And there was evening and there was morning, a second day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And God said, Let the waters under the heavens be gathered together unto one place, and let the dry land appear: and it was so. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And God called the dry land Earth; and the gathering together of the waters called he Seas: and God saw that it was good. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And God said, Let the earth put forth grass, herbs yielding seed, <char style="add">and</char> fruit-trees bearing fruit after their kind, wherein is the seed thereof, upon the earth: and it was so. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And the earth brought forth grass, herbs yielding seed after their kind, and trees bearing fruit, wherein is the seed thereof, after their kind: and God saw that it was good. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And there was evening and there was morning, a third day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And God said, Let there be lights in the firmament of heaven to divide the day from the night; and let them be for signs, and for seasons, and for days and years: <verse number="15" style="v"/>and let them be for lights in the firmament of heaven to give light upon the earth: and it was so. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And God made the two great lights; the greater light to rule the day, and the lesser light to rule the night: <char style="add">he made</char> the stars also. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And God set them in the firmament of heaven to give light upon the earth, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and to rule over the day and over the night, and to divide the light from the darkness: and God saw that it was good. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And there was evening and there was morning, a fourth day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And God said, Let the waters swarm with swarms of living creatures, and let birds fly above the earth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">on the face of the expanse of the heavens</char>.</char></note>in the open firmament of heaven. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And God created the great sea-monsters, and every living creature that moveth, wherewith the waters swarmed, after their kind, and every winged bird after its kind: and God saw that it was good. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And God blessed them, saying, Be fruitful, and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and let birds multiply on the earth. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And there was evening and there was morning, a fifth day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>And God said, Let the earth bring forth living creatures after their kind, cattle, and creeping things, and beasts of the earth after their kind: and it was so. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And God made the beasts of the earth after their kind, and the cattle after their kind, and everything that creepeth upon the ground after its kind: and God saw that it was good. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the birds of the heavens, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him; male and female created he them. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And God blessed them: and God said unto them, Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth, and subdue it; and have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the birds of the heavens, and over every living thing that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">creepeth</char></char></note>moveth upon the earth. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And God said, Behold, I have given you every herb yielding seed, which is upon the face of all the earth, and every tree, in which is the fruit of a tree yielding seed; to you it shall be for food: <verse number="30" style="v"/>and to every beast of the earth, and to every bird of the heavens, and to everything that creepeth upon the earth, wherein there is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">a living soul</char>.</char></note>life, <char style="add">I have given</char> every green herb for food: and it was so. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And God saw everything that he had made, and, behold, it was very good. And there was evening and there was morning, the sixth day.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the heavens and the earth were finished, and all the host of them. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And on the seventh day God finished his work which he had made; and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And God blessed the seventh day, and hallowed it; because that in it he rested from all his work which God had created and made.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>These are the generations of the heavens and of the earth when they were created, in the day that Jehovah God made earth and heaven. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And no plant of the field was yet in the earth, and no herb of the field had yet sprung up; for Jehovah God had not caused it to rain upon the earth: and there was not a man to till the ground; <verse number="6" style="v"/>but there went up a mist from the earth, and watered the whole face of the ground. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Jehovah God formed man of the dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living soul. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Jehovah God planted a garden eastward, in Eden; and there he put the man whom he had formed. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And out of the ground made Jehovah God to grow every tree that is pleasant to the sight, and good for food; the tree of life also in the midst of the garden, and the tree of the knowledge of good and evil. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And a river went out of Eden to water the garden; and from thence it was parted, and became four heads. <verse number="11" style="v"/>The name of the first is Pishon: that is it which compasseth the whole land of Havilah, where there is gold; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and the gold of that land is good: there is bdellium and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">beryl</char></char></note>onyx stone. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And the name of the second river is Gihon: the same is it that compasseth the whole land of Cush. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the name of the third river is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Tigris</char>.</char></note>Hiddekel: that is it which goeth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">toward the east of</char></char></note>in front of Assyria. And the fourth river is the Euphrates. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Jehovah God took the man, and put him into the garden of Eden to dress it and to keep it. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Jehovah God commanded the man, saying, Of every tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat: <verse number="17" style="v"/>but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, thou shalt not eat of it: for in the day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely die.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Jehovah God said, It is not good that the man should be alone; I will make him a help <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">answering to</char></char></note>meet for him. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And out of the ground Jehovah God formed every beast of the field, and every bird of the heavens; and brought them unto the man to see what he would call them: and whatsoever the man called every living creature, that was the name thereof. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the man gave names to all cattle, and to the birds of the heavens, and to every beast of the field; but for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Adam</char></char></note>man there was not found a help meet for him. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Jehovah God caused a deep sleep to fall upon the man, and he slept; and he took one of his ribs, and closed up the flesh instead thereof: <verse number="22" style="v"/>and the rib, which Jehovah God had taken from the man, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">builded he into</char>.</char></note>made he a woman, and brought her unto the man. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And the man said, This is now bone of my bones, and flesh of my flesh: she shall be called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Isshah</char>.</char></note>Woman, because she was taken out of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Ish</char>.</char></note>Man. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother, and shall cleave unto his wife: and they shall be one flesh. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And they were both naked, the man and his wife, and were not ashamed.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now the serpent was more subtle than any beast of the field which Jehovah God had made. And he said unto the woman, Yea, hath God said, Ye shall not eat of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">all the trees</char></char></note>any tree of the garden? <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the woman said unto the serpent, Of the fruit of the trees of the garden we may eat: <verse number="3" style="v"/>but of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, Ye shall not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the serpent said unto the woman, Ye shall not surely die: <verse number="5" style="v"/>for God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes shall be opened, and ye shall be as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gods</char></char></note>God, knowing good and evil. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And when the woman saw that the tree was good for food, and that it was a delight to the eyes, and that the tree was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">desirable to look upon</char></char></note>to be desired to make one wise, she took of the fruit thereof, and did eat; and she gave also unto her husband with her, and he did eat. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked; and they sewed fig-leaves together, and made themselves <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">girdles</char></char></note>aprons. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And they heard the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sound</char></char></note>voice of Jehovah God walking in the garden in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">wind</char>.</char></note>cool of the day: and the man and his wife hid themselves from the presence of Jehovah God amongst the trees of the garden.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And Jehovah God called unto the man, and said unto him, Where art thou? <verse number="10" style="v"/>And he said, I heard thy voice in the garden, and I was afraid, because I was naked; and I hid myself. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And he said, Who told thee that thou wast naked? Hast thou eaten of the tree, whereof I commanded thee that thou shouldest not eat? <verse number="12" style="v"/>And the man said, The woman whom thou gavest to be with me, she gave me of the tree, and I did eat. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Jehovah God said unto the woman, What is this thou hast done? And the woman said, The serpent beguiled me, and I did eat. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Jehovah God said unto the serpent, Because thou hast done this, cursed art thou <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">from among</char></char></note>above all cattle, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">from among</char></char></note>above every beast of the field; upon thy belly shalt thou go, and dust shalt thou eat all the days of thy life: <verse number="15" style="v"/>and I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy seed and her seed: he shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lie in wait for</char></char></note>bruise thy head, and thou shalt <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lie in wait for</char></char></note>bruise his heel. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Unto the woman he said, I will greatly multiply thy pain and thy conception; in pain thou shalt bring forth children; and thy desire shall be to thy husband, and he shall rule over thee. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And unto Adam he said, Because thou hast hearkened unto the voice of thy wife, and hast eaten of the tree, of which I commanded thee, saying, Thou shalt not eat of it: cursed is the ground for thy sake; in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sorrow</char></char></note>toil shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life; <verse number="18" style="v"/>thorns also and thistles shall it bring forth to thee; and thou shalt eat the herb of the field; <verse number="19" style="v"/>in the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground; for out of it wast thou taken: for dust thou art, and unto dust shalt thou return. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the man called his wife&#8217;s name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Havvah</char>, that is, <char style="it">Living</char>, or <char style="it">Life</char>.</char></note>Eve; because she was the mother of all living. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Jehovah God made for Adam and for his wife coats of skins, and clothed them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And Jehovah God said, Behold, the man is become as one of us, to know good and evil; and now, lest he put forth his hand, and take also of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever&#8212;<verse number="23" style="v"/>therefore Jehovah God sent him forth from the garden of Eden, to till the ground from whence he was taken. <verse number="24" style="v"/>So he drove out the man; and he placed at the east of the garden of Eden the Cherubim, and the flame of a sword which turned every way, to keep the way of the tree of life.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the man knew Eve his wife; and she conceived, and bare Cain, and said, I have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">kanah</char>, to get.</char></note>gotten a man with <char style="add">the help of</char> Jehovah. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And again she bare his brother Abel. And Abel was a keeper of sheep, but Cain was a tiller of the ground. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And in process of time it came to pass, that Cain brought of the fruit of the ground an offering unto Jehovah. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Abel, he also brought of the firstlings of his flock and of the fat thereof. And Jehovah had respect unto Abel and to his offering: <verse number="5" style="v"/>but unto Cain and to his offering he had not respect. And Cain was very wroth, and his countenance fell. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Jehovah said unto Cain, Why art thou wroth? and why is thy countenance fallen? <verse number="7" style="v"/>If thou doest well, shall it not be lifted up? and if thou doest not well, sin coucheth at the door; and unto thee shall be its desire; but do thou rule over it. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Cain <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">said unto</char>.</char></note>told Abel his brother. And it came to pass, when they were in the field, that Cain rose up against Abel his brother, and slew him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And Jehovah said unto Cain, Where is Abel thy brother? And he said, I know not: am I my brother&#8217;s keeper? <verse number="10" style="v"/>And he said, What hast thou done? the voice of thy brother&#8217;s blood crieth unto me from the ground. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And now cursed art thou from the ground, which hath opened its mouth to receive thy brother&#8217;s blood from thy hand; <verse number="12" style="v"/>when thou tillest the ground, it shall not henceforth yield unto thee its strength; a fugitive and a wanderer shalt thou be in the earth. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Cain said unto Jehovah, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Mine iniquity</char></char></note>My punishment is greater <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">than can be forgiven</char></char></note>than I can bear. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Behold, thou hast driven me out this day from the face of the ground; and from thy face shall I be hid; and I shall be a fugitive and a wanderer in the earth; and it will come to pass, that whosoever findeth me will slay me. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Jehovah said unto him, Therefore whosoever slayeth Cain, vengeance shall be taken on him sevenfold. And Jehovah appointed a sign for Cain, lest any finding him should smite him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And Cain went out from the presence of Jehovah, and dwelt in the land of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Wandering</char>.</char></note>Nod, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in front of</char></char></note>on the east of Eden. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Cain knew his wife; and she conceived, and bare Enoch: and he builded a city, and called the name of the city, after the name of his son, Enoch. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And unto Enoch was born Irad: and Irad begat Mehujael; and Mehujael begat Methushael; and Methushael begat Lamech. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Lamech took unto him two wives: the name of the one was Adah, and the name of the other Zillah. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Adah bare Jabal: he was the father of such as dwell in tents and <char style="add">have</char> cattle. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And his brother&#8217;s name was Jubal: he was the father of all such as handle the harp and pipe. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Zillah, she also bare Tubal-cain, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">an instructor of every artificer</char></char></note>the forger of every cutting instrument of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">copper</char> (and so elsewhere)</char></note>brass and iron: and the sister of Tubal-cain was Naamah. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Lamech said unto his wives:</para>
	<para style="q1">Adah and Zillah, hear my voice;</para>
	<para style="q1">Ye wives of Lamech, hearken unto my speech:</para>
	<para style="q1">For <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">I will slay</char></char></note>I have slain a man <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to my wounding, And a young man to my hurt</char></char></note>for wounding me,</para>
	<para style="q1">And a young man for bruising me:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="24" style="v"/>If Cain shall be avenged sevenfold,</para>
	<para style="q1">Truly Lamech seventy and sevenfold.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And Adam knew his wife again; and she bare a son, and called his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Sheth</char>.</char></note>Seth: For, <char style="add">said she</char>, God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">shath</char>.</char></note>hath appointed me another seed instead of Abel; for Cain slew him. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And to Seth, to him also there was born a son; and he called his name Enosh. Then began men to call upon the name of Jehovah.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>This is the book of the generations of Adam. In the day that God created man, in the likeness of God made he him; <verse number="2" style="v"/>male and female created he them, and blessed them, and called their name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Man</char></char></note>Adam, in the day when they were created. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Adam lived a hundred and thirty years, and begat <char style="add">a son</char> in his own likeness, after his image; and called his name Seth: <verse number="4" style="v"/>and the days of Adam after he begat Seth were eight hundred years: and he begat sons and daughters. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And all the days that Adam lived were nine hundred and thirty years: and he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And Seth lived a hundred and five years, and begat Enosh: <verse number="7" style="v"/>and Seth lived after he begat Enosh eight hundred and seven years, and begat sons and daughters: <verse number="8" style="v"/>and all the days of Seth were nine hundred and twelve years: and he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And Enosh lived ninety years, and begat Kenan: <verse number="10" style="v"/>and Enosh lived after he begat Kenan eight hundred and fifteen years, and begat sons and daughters: <verse number="11" style="v"/>and all the days of Enosh were nine hundred and five years: and he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And Kenan lived seventy years, and begat Mahalalel: <verse number="13" style="v"/>and Kenan lived after he begat Mahalalel eight hundred and forty years, and begat sons and daughters: <verse number="14" style="v"/>and all the days of Kenan were nine hundred and ten years: and he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And Mahalalel lived sixty and five years, and begat Jared: <verse number="16" style="v"/>and Mahalalel lived after he begat Jared eight hundred and thirty years, and begat sons and daughters: <verse number="17" style="v"/>and all the days of Mahalalel were eight hundred ninety and five years: and he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Jared lived a hundred sixty and two years, and begat Enoch: <verse number="19" style="v"/>and Jared lived after he begat Enoch eight hundred years, and begat sons and daughters: <verse number="20" style="v"/>and all the days of Jared were nine hundred sixty and two years: and he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>And Enoch lived sixty and five years, and begat Methuselah: <verse number="22" style="v"/>and Enoch walked with God after he begat Methuselah three hundred years, and begat sons and daughters: <verse number="23" style="v"/>and all the days of Enoch were three hundred sixty and five years: <verse number="24" style="v"/>and Enoch walked with God: and he was not; for God took him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And Methuselah lived a hundred eighty and seven years, and begat Lamech: <verse number="26" style="v"/>and Methuselah lived after he begat Lamech seven hundred eighty and two years, and begat sons and daughters: <verse number="27" style="v"/>and all the days of Methuselah were nine hundred sixty and nine years: and he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And Lamech lived a hundred eighty and two years, and begat a son: <verse number="29" style="v"/>and he called his name Noah, saying, This same shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">nahem</char>, to comfort.</char></note>comfort us in our work and in the toil of our hands, <char style="add">which cometh</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">from</char>.</char></note>because of the ground which Jehovah hath cursed. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And Lamech lived after he begat Noah five hundred ninety and five years, and begat sons and daughters: <verse number="31" style="v"/>And all the days of Lamech were seven hundred seventy and seven years: and he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v"/>And Noah was five hundred years old: and Noah begat Shem, Ham, and Japheth.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when men began to multiply on the face of the ground, and daughters were born unto them, <verse number="2" style="v"/>that the sons of God saw the daughters of men that they were fair; and they took them wives of all that they chose. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Jehovah said, My Spirit shall not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">rule in</char>. According to Septuagint, Vulgate, and Syriac, <char style="it">abide in</char></char></note>strive with man for ever, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in their going astray they are flesh</char></char></note>for that he also is flesh: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">therefore</char></char></note>yet shall his days be a hundred and twenty years. <verse number="4" style="v"/>The <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">giants</char>. See <ref loc="NUM 13:33">Num. 13:33</ref>.</char></note>Nephilim were in the earth in those days, and also after that, when the sons of God came in unto the daughters of men, and they bare children to them: the same were the mighty men that were of old, the men of renown.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>And Jehovah saw that the wickedness of man was great in the earth, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And it repented Jehovah that he had made man on the earth, and it grieved him at his heart. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Jehovah said, I will <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">blot out</char>.</char></note>destroy man whom I have created from the face of the ground; both man, and beast, and creeping things, and birds of the heavens; for it repenteth me that I have made them. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But Noah found favor in the eyes of Jehovah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>These are the generations of Noah. Noah was a righteous man, <char style="add">and</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">blameless</char></char></note>perfect in his generations: Noah walked with God. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Noah begat three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the earth was corrupt before God, and the earth was filled with violence. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And God saw the earth, and, behold, it was corrupt; for all flesh had corrupted their way upon the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And God said unto Noah, The end of all flesh is come before me; for the earth is filled with violence through them; and, behold, I will destroy them with the earth. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Make thee an ark of gopher wood; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">nests</char>.</char></note>rooms shalt thou make in the ark, and shalt pitch it within and without with pitch. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And this is how thou shalt make it: the length of the ark three hundred cubits, the breadth of it fifty cubits, and the height of it thirty cubits. <verse number="16" style="v"/>A <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">roof</char></char></note>light shalt thou make to the ark, and to a cubit shalt thou finish it <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">from above</char></char></note>upward; and the door of the ark shalt thou set in the side thereof; with lower, second, and third stories shalt thou make it. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And I, behold, I do bring the flood of waters upon the earth, to destroy all flesh, wherein is the breath of life, from under heaven; everything that is in the earth shall die. <verse number="18" style="v"/>But I will establish my covenant with thee; and thou shalt come into the ark, thou, and thy sons, and thy wife, and thy sons&#8217; wives with thee. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And of every living thing of all flesh, two of every sort shalt thou bring into the ark, to keep them alive with thee; they shall be male and female. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Of the birds after their kind, and of the cattle after their kind, of every creeping thing of the ground after its kind, two of every sort shall come unto thee, to keep them alive. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And take thou unto thee of all food that is eaten, and gather it to thee; and it shall be for food for thee, and for them. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Thus did Noah; according to all that God commanded him, so did he.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Jehovah said unto Noah, Come thou and all thy house into the ark; for thee have I seen righteous before me in this generation. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Of every clean beast thou shalt take to thee seven and seven, the male and his female; and of the beasts that are not clean two, the male and his female: <verse number="3" style="v"/>of the birds also of the heavens, seven and seven, male and female, to keep seed alive upon the face of all the earth. <verse number="4" style="v"/>For yet seven days, and I will cause it to rain upon the earth forty days and forty nights; and every living thing that I have made will I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">blot out</char>.</char></note>destroy from off the face of the ground. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Noah did according unto all that Jehovah commanded him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And Noah was six hundred years old when the flood of waters was upon the earth. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Noah went in, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons&#8217; wives with him, into the ark, because of the waters of the flood. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Of clean beasts, and of beasts that are not clean, and of birds, and of everything that creepeth upon the ground, <verse number="9" style="v"/>there went in two and two unto Noah into the ark, male and female, as God commanded Noah. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And it came to pass after the seven days, that the waters of the flood were upon the earth. <verse number="11" style="v"/>In the six hundredth year of Noah&#8217;s life, in the second month, on the seventeenth day of the month, on the same day were all the fountains of the great deep broken up, and the windows of heaven were opened. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And the rain was upon the earth forty days and forty nights.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>In the selfsame day entered Noah, and Shem, and Ham, and Japheth, the sons of Noah, and Noah&#8217;s wife, and the three wives of his sons with them, into the ark; <verse number="14" style="v"/>they, and every beast after its kind, and all the cattle after their kind, and every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth after its kind, and every bird after its kind, every bird of every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">wing</char>.</char></note>sort. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And they went in unto Noah into the ark, two and two of all flesh wherein is the breath of life. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And they that went in, went in male and female of all flesh, as God commanded him: and Jehovah shut him in. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the flood was forty days upon the earth; and the waters increased, and bare up the ark, and it was lifted up above the earth. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the waters prevailed, and increased greatly upon the earth; and the ark went upon the face of the waters. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the waters prevailed exceedingly upon the earth; and all the high mountains that were under the whole heaven were covered. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Fifteen cubits upward did the waters prevail; and the mountains were covered. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And all flesh died that moved upon the earth, both birds, and cattle, and beasts, and every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">swarming thing that swarmeth</char></char></note>creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth, and every man: <verse number="22" style="v"/>all in whose nostrils was the breath of the spirit of life, of all that was on the dry land, died. <verse number="23" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">And he destroyed every living thing</char></char></note>And every living thing was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">blotted out</char>.</char></note>destroyed that was upon the face of the ground, both man, and cattle, and creeping things, and birds of the heavens; and they were destroyed from the earth: and Noah only was left, and they that were with him in the ark. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And the waters prevailed upon the earth a hundred and fifty days.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And God remembered Noah, and all the beasts, and all the cattle that were with him in the ark: and God made a wind to pass over the earth, and the waters assuaged; <verse number="2" style="v"/>the fountains also of the deep and the windows of heaven were stopped, and the rain from heaven was restrained; <verse number="3" style="v"/>and the waters returned from off the earth continually: and after the end of a hundred and fifty days the waters decreased. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the ark rested in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, upon the mountains of Ararat. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the waters decreased continually until the tenth month: in the tenth month, on the first day of the month, were the tops of the mountains seen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And it came to pass at the end of forty days, that Noah opened the window of the ark which he had made: <verse number="7" style="v"/>and he sent forth a raven, and it went forth to and fro, until the waters were dried up from off the earth. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he sent forth a dove from him, to see if the waters were abated from off the face of the ground; <verse number="9" style="v"/>but the dove found no rest for the sole of her foot, and she returned unto him to the ark; for the waters were on the face of the whole earth: and he put forth his hand, and took her, and brought her in unto him into the ark. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And he stayed yet other seven days; and again he sent forth the dove out of the ark; <verse number="11" style="v"/>and the dove came in to him at eventide; and, lo, in her mouth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a fresh olive-leaf</char></char></note>an olive-leaf plucked off: so Noah knew that the waters were abated from off the earth. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he stayed yet other seven days, and sent forth the dove; and she returned not again unto him any more.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And it came to pass in the six hundred and first year, in the first month, the first day of the month, the waters were dried up from off the earth: and Noah removed the covering of the ark, and looked, and, behold, the face of the ground was dried. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And in the second month, on the seven and twentieth day of the month, was the earth dry. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And God spake unto Noah, saying, <verse number="16" style="v"/>Go forth from the ark, thou, and thy wife, and thy sons, and thy sons&#8217; wives with thee. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Bring forth with thee every living thing that is with thee of all flesh, both birds, and cattle, and every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth; that they may breed abundantly in the earth, and be fruitful, and multiply upon the earth. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Noah went forth, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons&#8217; wives with him: <verse number="19" style="v"/>every beast, every creeping thing, and every bird, whatsoever moveth upon the earth, after their families, went forth out of the ark.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And Noah builded an altar unto Jehovah, and took of every clean beast, and of every clean bird, and offered burnt-offerings on the altar. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Jehovah smelled the sweet savor; and Jehovah said in his heart, I will not again curse the ground any more for man&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sake: for the</char></char></note>sake, for that the imagination of man&#8217;s heart is evil from his youth; neither will I again smite any more everything living, as I have done. <verse number="22" style="v"/>While the earth remaineth, seedtime and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night shall not cease.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And God blessed Noah and his sons, and said unto them, Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the fear of you and the dread of you shall be upon every beast of the earth, and upon every bird of the heavens; with all wherewith the ground <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">creepeth</char></char></note>teemeth, and all the fishes of the sea, into your hand are they delivered. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Every moving thing that liveth shall be food for you; as the green herb have I given you all. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But flesh with the life thereof, <char style="add">which is</char> the blood thereof, shall ye not eat. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And surely your blood, <char style="add">the blood</char> of your lives, will I require; at the hand of every beast will I require it: and at the hand of man, even at the hand of every man&#8217;s brother, will I require the life of man. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Whoso sheddeth man&#8217;s blood, by man shall his blood be shed: for in the image of God made he man. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And you, be ye fruitful, and multiply; bring forth abundantly in the earth, and multiply therein.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And God spake unto Noah, and to his sons with him, saying, <verse number="9" style="v"/>And I, behold, I establish my covenant with you, and with your seed after you; <verse number="10" style="v"/>and with every living creature that is with you, the birds, the cattle, and every beast of the earth with you; of all that go out of the ark, even every beast of the earth. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And I will establish my covenant with you; neither shall all flesh be cut off any more by the waters of the flood; neither shall there any more be a flood to destroy the earth. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And God said, This is the token of the covenant which I make between me and you and every living creature that is with you, for perpetual generations: <verse number="13" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">I have set</char></char></note>I do set my bow in the cloud, and it shall be for a token of a covenant between me and the earth. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And it shall come to pass, when I bring a cloud over the earth, that the bow shall be seen in the cloud, <verse number="15" style="v"/>and I will remember my covenant, which is between me and you and every living creature of all flesh; and the waters shall no more become a flood to destroy all flesh. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the bow shall be in the cloud; and I will look upon it, that I may remember the everlasting covenant between God and every living creature of all flesh that is upon the earth. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And God said unto Noah, This is the token of the covenant which I have established between me and all flesh that is upon the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And the sons of Noah, that went forth from the ark, were Shem, and Ham, and Japheth: and Ham is the father of Canaan. <verse number="19" style="v"/>These three were the sons of Noah: and of these was the whole earth overspread.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And Noah began to be a husbandman, and planted a vineyard: <verse number="21" style="v"/>and he drank of the wine, and was drunken; and he was uncovered within his tent. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Ham, the father of Canaan, saw the nakedness of his father, and told his two brethren without. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Shem and Japheth took a garment, and laid it upon both their shoulders, and went backward, and covered the nakedness of their father; and their faces were backward, and they saw not their father&#8217;s nakedness. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Noah awoke from his wine, and knew what his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">younger</char></char></note>youngest son had done unto him. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And he said,</para>
	<para style="q1">Cursed be Canaan;</para>
	<para style="q1">A servant of servants shall he be unto his brethren.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>And he said,</para>
	<para style="q1">Blessed be Jehovah, the God of Shem;</para>
	<para style="q1">And let Canaan be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">their</char></char></note>his servant.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="27" style="v"/>God enlarge Japheth,</para>
	<para style="q1">And <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">he shall</char></char></note>let him dwell in the tents of Shem;</para>
	<para style="q1">And let Canaan be his servant.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And Noah lived after the flood three hundred and fifty years. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And all the days of Noah were nine hundred and fifty years: and he died.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now these are the generations of the sons of Noah, <char style="add">namely</char>, of Shem, Ham, and Japheth: and unto them were sons born after the flood.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>The sons of Japheth: Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And the sons of Gomer: Ashkenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the sons of Javan: Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Of these were the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">coastlands</char></char></note>isles of the nations divided in their lands, every one after his tongue, after their families, in their nations.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And the sons of Ham: Cush, and Mizraim, and Put, and Canaan. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the sons of Cush: Seba, and Havilah, and Sabtah, and Raamah, and Sabteca; and the sons of Raamah: Sheba, and Dedan. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Cush begat Nimrod: he began to be a mighty one in the earth. <verse number="9" style="v"/>He was a mighty hunter before Jehovah: wherefore it is said, Like Nimrod a mighty hunter before Jehovah. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And the beginning of his kingdom was Babel, and Erech, and Accad, and Calneh, in the land of Shinar. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Out of that land <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">went forth Asshur</char></char></note>he went forth into Assyria, and builded Nineveh, and Rehoboth-Ir, and Calah, <verse number="12" style="v"/>and Resen between Nineveh and Calah (the same is the great city). <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Mizraim begat Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim, <verse number="14" style="v"/>and Pathrusim, and Casluhim (whence went forth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Pelishtim</char>.</char></note>the Philistines), and Caphtorim.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And Canaan begat Sidon his first-born, and Heth, <verse number="16" style="v"/>and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, and the Girgashite, <verse number="17" style="v"/>and the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite: and afterward were the families of the Canaanite spread abroad. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the border of the Canaanite was from Sidon, as thou goest toward Gerar, unto Gaza; as thou goest toward Sodom and Gomorrah and Admah and Zeboiim, unto Lasha. <verse number="20" style="v"/>These are the sons of Ham, after their families, after their tongues, in their lands, in their nations.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>And unto Shem, the father of all the children of Eber, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the brother of Japheth the elder</char></char></note>the elder brother of Japheth, to him also were children born. <verse number="22" style="v"/>The sons of Shem: Elam, and Asshur, and Arpachshad, and Lud, and Aram. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And the sons of Aram: Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Mash. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Arpachshad begat Shelah; and Shelah begat Eber. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And unto Eber were born two sons: the name of the one was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Division</char>.</char></note>Peleg; for in his days was the earth divided; and his brother&#8217;s name was Joktan. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Joktan begat Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah, <verse number="27" style="v"/>and Hadoram, and Uzal, and Diklah, <verse number="28" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:22">1 Chr. 1:22</ref>, <char style="it">Ebal</char>.</char></note>Obal, and Abimael, and Sheba, <verse number="29" style="v"/>and Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab: all these were the sons of Joktan. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And their dwelling was from Mesha, as thou goest toward Sephar, the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hill country</char></char></note>mountain of the east. <verse number="31" style="v"/>These are the sons of Shem, after their families, after their tongues, in their lands, after their nations.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v"/>These are the families of the sons of Noah, after their generations, in their nations: and of these were the nations divided in the earth after the flood.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the whole earth was of one <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">lip</char>.</char></note>language and of one <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">words</char>.</char></note>speech. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as they journeyed <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in the east</char></char></note>east, that they found a plain in the land of Shinar; and they dwelt there. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And they said one to another, Come, let us make brick, and burn them thoroughly. And they had brick for stone, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">bitumen</char>.</char></note>slime had they for mortar. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And they said, Come, let us build us a city, and a tower, whose top <char style="add">may reach</char> unto heaven, and let us make us a name; lest we be scattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Jehovah came down to see the city and the tower, which the children of men builded. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Jehovah said, Behold, they are one people, and they have all one language; and this is what they begin to do: and now nothing will be withholden from them, which they purpose to do. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Come, let us go down, and there confound their language, that they may not understand one another&#8217;s speech. <verse number="8" style="v"/>So Jehovah scattered them abroad from thence upon the face of all the earth: and they left off building the city. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Therefore was the name of it called Babel; because Jehovah did there <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">balal</char>, to confound.</char></note>confound the language of all the earth: and from thence did Jehovah scatter them abroad upon the face of all the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>These are the generations of Shem. Shem was a hundred years old, and begat Arpachshad two years after the flood: <verse number="11" style="v"/>and Shem lived after he begat Arpachshad five hundred years, and begat sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And Arpachshad lived five and thirty years, and begat Shelah: <verse number="13" style="v"/>and Arpachshad lived after he begat Shelah four hundred and three years, and begat sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And Shelah lived thirty years, and begat Eber: <verse number="15" style="v"/>and Shelah lived after he begat Eber four hundred and three years, and begat sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And Eber lived four and thirty years, and begat Peleg: <verse number="17" style="v"/>and Eber lived after he begat Peleg four hundred and thirty years, and begat sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Peleg lived thirty years, and begat Reu: <verse number="19" style="v"/>and Peleg lived after he begat Reu two hundred and nine years, and begat sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And Reu lived two and thirty years, and begat Serug: <verse number="21" style="v"/>and Reu lived after he begat Serug two hundred and seven years, and begat sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And Serug lived thirty years, and begat Nahor: <verse number="23" style="v"/>and Serug lived after he begat Nahor two hundred years, and begat sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>And Nahor lived nine and twenty years, and begat Terah: <verse number="25" style="v"/>and Nahor lived after he begat Terah a hundred and nineteen years, and begat sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>And Terah lived seventy years, and begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v"/>Now these are the generations of Terah. Terah begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran; and Haran begat Lot. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And Haran died before his father Terah in the land of his nativity, in Ur of the Chaldees. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Abram and Nahor took them wives: the name of Abram&#8217;s wife was Sarai; and the name of Nahor&#8217;s wife, Milcah, the daughter of Haran, the father of Milcah, and the father of Iscah. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And Sarai was barren; she had no child. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And Terah took Abram his son, and Lot the son of Haran, his son&#8217;s son, and Sarai his daughter-in-law, his son Abram&#8217;s wife; and they went forth with them from Ur of the Chaldees, to go into the land of Canaan; and they came unto Haran, and dwelt there. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And the days of Terah were two hundred and five years: and Terah died in Haran.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now Jehovah said unto Abram, Get thee out of thy country, and from thy kindred, and from thy father&#8217;s house, unto the land that I will show thee: <verse number="2" style="v"/>and I will make of thee a great nation, and I will bless thee, and make thy name great; and be thou a blessing: <verse number="3" style="v"/>and I will bless them that bless thee, and him that curseth thee will I curse: and in thee shall all the families of the earth be blessed. <verse number="4" style="v"/>So Abram went, as Jehovah had spoken unto him; and Lot went with him: and Abram was seventy and five years old when he departed out of Haran. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Abram took Sarai his wife, and Lot his brother&#8217;s son, and all their substance that they had gathered, and the souls that they had gotten in Haran; and they went forth to go into the land of Canaan; and into the land of Canaan they came. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Abram passed through the land unto the place of Shechem, unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">terebinth</char></char></note>oak of Moreh. And the Canaanite was then in the land. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Jehovah appeared unto Abram, and said, Unto thy seed will I give this land: and there builded he an altar unto Jehovah, who appeared unto him. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he removed from thence unto the mountain on the east of Beth-el, and pitched his tent, having Beth-el on the west, and Ai on the east: and there he builded an altar unto Jehovah, and called upon the name of Jehovah. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Abram journeyed, going on still toward the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Negeb</char>, the southern tract of Judah.</char></note>South.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And there was a famine in the land: and Abram went down into Egypt to sojourn there; for the famine was sore in the land. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when he was come near to enter into Egypt, that he said unto Sarai his wife, Behold now, I know that thou art a fair woman to look upon: <verse number="12" style="v"/>and it will come to pass, when the Egyptians shall see thee, that they will say, This is his wife: and they will kill me, but they will save thee alive. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Say, I pray thee, thou art my sister; that it may be well with me for thy sake, and that my soul may live because of thee. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that, when Abram was come into Egypt, the Egyptians beheld the woman that she was very fair. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the princes of Pharaoh saw her, and praised her to Pharaoh: and the woman was taken into Pharaoh&#8217;s house. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he dealt well with Abram for her sake: and he had sheep, and oxen, and he-asses, and men-servants, and maid-servants, and she-asses, and camels. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Jehovah plagued Pharaoh and his house with great plagues because of Sarai, Abram&#8217;s wife. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Pharaoh called Abram, and said, What is this that thou hast done unto me? why didst thou not tell me that she was thy wife? <verse number="19" style="v"/>why saidst thou, She is my sister, so that I took her to be my wife? now therefore behold thy wife, take her, and go thy way. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Pharaoh gave men charge concerning him: and they brought him on the way, and his wife, and all that he had.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Abram went up out of Egypt, he, and his wife, and all that he had, and Lot with him, into the South. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Abram was very rich in cattle, in silver, and in gold. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he went on his journeys from the South even to Beth-el, unto the place where his tent had been at the beginning, between Beth-el and Ai, <verse number="4" style="v"/>unto the place of the altar, which he had made there at the first: and there Abram called on the name of Jehovah. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Lot also, who went with Abram, had flocks, and herds, and tents. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And the land was not able to bear them, that they might dwell together: for their substance was great, so that they could not dwell together. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And there was a strife between the herdsmen of Abram&#8217;s cattle and the herdsmen of Lot&#8217;s cattle: and the Canaanite and the Perizzite dwelt then in the land. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Abram said unto Lot, Let there be no strife, I pray thee, between me and thee, and between my herdsmen and thy herdsmen; for we are brethren. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Is not the whole land before thee? separate thyself, I pray thee, from me: if <char style="add">thou wilt take</char> the left hand, then I will go to the right; or if <char style="add">thou take</char> the right hand, then I will go to the left. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Lot lifted up his eyes, and beheld all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Circle</char></char></note>Plain of the Jordan, that it was well watered every where, before Jehovah destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah, like the garden of Jehovah, like the land of Egypt, as thou goest unto Zoar. <verse number="11" style="v"/>So Lot chose him all the Plain of the Jordan; and Lot journeyed east: and they separated themselves the one from the other. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Abram dwelt in the land of Canaan, and Lot dwelt in the cities of the Plain, and moved his tent as far as Sodom. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Now the men of Sodom were wicked and sinners against Jehovah exceedingly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And Jehovah said unto Abram, after that Lot was separated from him, Lift up now thine eyes, and look from the place where thou art, northward and southward and eastward and westward: <verse number="15" style="v"/>for all the land which thou seest, to thee will I give it, and to thy seed for ever. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And I will make thy seed as the dust of the earth: so that if a man can number the dust of the earth, then may thy seed also be numbered. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Arise, walk through the land in the length of it and in the breadth of it; for unto thee will I give it. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Abram moved his tent, and came and dwelt by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">terebinths</char></char></note>oaks of Mamre, which are in Hebron, and built there an altar unto Jehovah.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass in the days of Amraphel king of Shinar, Arioch king of Ellasar, Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">nations</char></char></note>Goiim, <verse number="2" style="v"/>that they made war with Bera king of Sodom, and with Birsha king of Gomorrah, Shinab king of Admah, and Shemeber king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (the same is Zoar). <verse number="3" style="v"/>All these <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">joined themselves together against</char></char></note>joined together in the vale of Siddim (the same is the Salt Sea). <verse number="4" style="v"/>Twelve years they served Chedorlaomer, and in the thirteenth year they rebelled. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And in the fourteenth year came Chedorlaomer, and the kings that were with him, and smote the Rephaim in Ashteroth-karnaim, and the Zuzim in Ham, and the Emim in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the plain of Kiriathaim</char></char></note>Shaveh-kiriathaim, <verse number="6" style="v"/>and the Horites in their mount Seir, unto El-paran, which is by the wilderness. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And they returned, and came to En-mishpat (the same is Kadesh), and smote all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">field</char>.</char></note>country of the Amalekites, and also the Amorites, that dwelt in Hazazon-tamar. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And there went out the king of Sodom, and the king of Gomorrah, and the king of Admah, and the king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (the same is Zoar); and they set the battle in array against them in the vale of Siddim; <verse number="9" style="v"/>against Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of Goiim, and Amraphel king of Shinar, and Arioch king of Ellasar; four kings against the five. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Now the vale of Siddim was full of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">bitumen pits</char>.</char></note>slime pits; and the kings of Sodom and Gomorrah fled, and they fell there, and they that remained fled to the mountain. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And they took all the goods of Sodom and Gomorrah, and all their victuals, and went their way. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And they took Lot, Abram&#8217;s brother&#8217;s son, who dwelt in Sodom, and his goods, and departed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And there came one that had escaped, and told Abram the Hebrew: now he dwelt by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">terebinths</char></char></note>oaks of Mamre, the Amorite, brother of Eshcol, and brother of Aner; and these were confederate with Abram. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And when Abram heard that his brother was taken captive, he led forth his trained men, born in his house, three hundred and eighteen, and pursued as far as Dan. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And he divided himself against them by night, he and his servants, and smote them, and pursued them unto Hobah, which is on the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">north</char></char></note>left hand of Damascus. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he brought back all the goods, and also brought back his brother Lot, and his goods, and the women also, and the people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And the king of Sodom went out to meet him, after his return from the slaughter of Chedorlaomer and the kings that were with him, at the vale of Shaveh (the same is the King&#8217;s Vale). <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Melchizedek king of Salem brought forth bread and wine: and he was priest of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El Elyon</char>.</char></note>God Most High. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And he blessed him, and said, Blessed be Abram of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El Elyon</char>.</char></note>God Most High, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">maker</char></char></note>possessor of heaven and earth: <verse number="20" style="v"/>and blessed be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El Elyon</char>.</char></note>God Most High, who hath delivered thine enemies into thy hand. And he gave him a tenth of all. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And the king of Sodom said unto Abram, Give me the persons, and take the goods to thyself. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Abram said to the king of Sodom, I have lifted up my hand unto Jehovah, God Most High, possessor of heaven and earth, <verse number="23" style="v"/>that I will not take a thread nor a shoe-latchet nor aught that is thine, lest thou shouldest say, I have made Abram rich: <verse number="24" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, let there be <char style="it">nothing for me; only that etc.</char></char></note>save only that which the young men have eaten, and the portion of the men that went with me, Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre; let them take their portion.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After these things the word of Jehovah came unto Abram in a vision, saying, Fear not, Abram: I am thy shield, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">thy reward shall be exceeding great</char></char></note><char style="add">and</char> thy exceeding great reward. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Abram said, O Lord Jehovah, what wilt thou give me, seeing I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">go hence</char></char></note>go childless, and he that shall be possessor of my house is Eliezer of Damascus? <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Abram said, Behold, to me thou hast given no seed: and, lo, one born in my house is mine heir. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And, behold, the word of Jehovah came unto him, saying, This man shall not be thine heir; but he that shall come forth out of thine own bowels shall be thine heir. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And he brought him forth abroad, and said, Look now toward heaven, and number the stars, if thou be able to number them: and he said unto him, So shall thy seed be. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he believed in Jehovah; and he reckoned it to him for righteousness. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he said unto him, I am Jehovah that brought thee out of Ur of the Chaldees, to give thee this land to inherit it. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he said, O Lord Jehovah, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it? <verse number="9" style="v"/>And he said unto him, Take me a heifer three years old, and a she-goat three years old, and a ram three years old, and a turtle-dove, and a young pigeon. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And he took him all these, and divided them in the midst, and laid each half over against the other: but the birds divided he not. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the birds of prey came down upon the carcasses, and Abram drove them away.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And when the sun was going down, a deep sleep fell upon Abram; and, lo, a horror of great darkness fell upon him. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And he said unto Abram, Know of a surety that thy seed shall be sojourners in a land that is not theirs, and shall serve them; and they shall afflict them four hundred years; <verse number="14" style="v"/>and also that nation, whom they shall serve, will I judge: and afterward shall they come out with great substance. <verse number="15" style="v"/>But thou shalt go to thy fathers in peace; thou shalt be buried in a good old age. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And in the fourth generation they shall come hither again: for the iniquity of the Amorite is not yet full. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that, when the sun went down, and it was dark, behold, a smoking furnace, and a flaming torch that passed between these pieces. <verse number="18" style="v"/>In that day Jehovah made a covenant with Abram, saying, Unto thy seed have I given this land, from the river of Egypt unto the great river, the river Euphrates: <verse number="19" style="v"/>the Kenite, and the Kenizzite, and the Kadmonite, <verse number="20" style="v"/>and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Rephaim, <verse number="21" style="v"/>and the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Girgashite, and the Jebusite.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now Sarai, Abram&#8217;s wife, bare him no children: and she had a handmaid, an Egyptian, whose name was Hagar. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Sarai said unto Abram, Behold now, Jehovah hath restrained me from bearing; go in, I pray thee, unto my handmaid; it may be that I shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">be builded by her</char>.</char></note>obtain children by her. And Abram hearkened to the voice of Sarai. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Sarai, Abram&#8217;s wife, took Hagar the Egyptian, her handmaid, after Abram had dwelt ten years in the land of Canaan, and gave her to Abram her husband to be his wife. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And he went in unto Hagar, and she conceived: and when she saw that she had conceived, her mistress was despised in her eyes. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Sarai said unto Abram, My wrong be upon thee: I gave my handmaid into thy bosom; and when she saw that she had conceived, I was despised in her eyes: Jehovah judge between me and thee. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But Abram said unto Sarai, Behold, thy maid is in thy hand; do to her that which is good in thine eyes. And Sarai dealt hardly with her, and she fled from her face.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And the angel of Jehovah found her by a fountain of water in the wilderness, by the fountain in the way to Shur. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he said, Hagar, Sarai&#8217;s handmaid, whence camest thou? and whither goest thou? And she said, I am fleeing from the face of my mistress Sarai. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the angel of Jehovah said unto her, Return to thy mistress, and submit thyself under her hands. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And the angel of Jehovah said unto her, I will greatly multiply thy seed, that it shall not be numbered for multitude. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the angel of Jehovah said unto her, Behold, thou art with child, and shalt bear a son; and thou shalt call his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">God heareth</char>.</char></note>Ishmael, because Jehovah hath heard thy affliction. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he shall be <char style="add">as</char> a wild ass among men; his hand <char style="add">shall be</char> against every man, and every man&#8217;s hand against him; and he shall dwell <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to the east of</char></char></note>over against all his brethren. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And she called the name of Jehovah that spake unto her, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Thou God seest me</char></char></note>Thou art <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El roi</char>, that is, <char style="it">God of seeing</char>.</char></note>a God that seeth: for she said, Have I even here looked after him that seeth me? <verse number="14" style="v"/>Wherefore the well was called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The well of the living one who seeth me</char>.</char></note>Beer-lahai-roi; behold, it is between Kadesh and Bered.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And Hagar bare Abram a son: and Abram called the name of his son, whom Hagar bare, Ishmael. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Abram was fourscore and six years old, when Hagar bare Ishmael to Abram.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And when Abram was ninety years old and nine, Jehovah appeared to Abram, and said unto him, I am <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El Shaddai</char>.</char></note>God Almighty; walk before me, and be thou perfect. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And I will make my covenant between me and thee, and will multiply thee exceedingly. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Abram fell on his face: and God talked with him, saying, <verse number="4" style="v"/>As for me, behold, my covenant is with thee, and thou shalt be the father of a multitude of nations. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Neither shall thy name any more be called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">exalted father</char>.</char></note>Abram, but thy name shall be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">father of a multitude</char>.</char></note>Abraham; for the father of a multitude of nations have I made thee. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And I will make thee exceeding fruitful, and I will make nations of thee, and kings shall come out of thee. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And I will establish my covenant between me and thee and thy seed after thee throughout their generations for an everlasting covenant, to be a God unto thee and to thy seed after thee. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And I will give unto thee, and to thy seed after thee, the land of thy sojournings, all the land of Canaan, for an everlasting possession; and I will be their God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And God said unto Abraham, And as for thee, thou shalt keep my covenant, thou, and thy seed after thee throughout their generations. <verse number="10" style="v"/>This is my covenant, which ye shall keep, between me and you and thy seed after thee: every male among you shall be circumcised. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And ye shall be circumcised in the flesh of your foreskin; and it shall be a token of a covenant betwixt me and you. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he that is eight days old shall be circumcised among you, every male throughout your generations, he that is born in the house, or bought with money of any foreigner that is not of thy seed. <verse number="13" style="v"/>He that is born in thy house, and he that is bought with thy money, must needs be circumcised: and my covenant shall be in your flesh for an everlasting covenant. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the uncircumcised male who is not circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin, that soul shall be cut off from his people; he hath broken my covenant.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And God said unto Abraham, As for Sarai thy wife, thou shalt not call her name Sarai, but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Princess</char>.</char></note>Sarah shall her name be. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And I will bless her, and moreover I will give thee a son of her: yea, I will bless her, and she shall be <char style="add">a mother of</char> nations; kings of peoples shall be of her. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Then Abraham fell upon his face, and laughed, and said in his heart, Shall a child be born unto him that is a hundred years old? and shall Sarah, that is ninety years old, bear? <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Abraham said unto God, Oh that Ishmael might live before thee! <verse number="19" style="v"/>And God said, Nay, but Sarah thy wife shall bear thee a son; and thou shalt call his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">From the Hebrew word meaning <char style="it">to laugh</char>.</char></note>Isaac: and I will establish my covenant with him for an everlasting covenant for his seed after him. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And as for Ishmael, I have heard thee: behold, I have blessed him, and will make him fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly; twelve princes shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation. <verse number="21" style="v"/>But my covenant will I establish with Isaac, whom Sarah shall bear unto thee at this set time in the next year.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And he left off talking with him, and God went up from Abraham. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Abraham took Ishmael his son, and all that were born in his house, and all that were bought with his money, every male among the men of Abraham&#8217;s house, and circumcised the flesh of their foreskin in the selfsame day, as God had said unto him. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Abraham was ninety years old and nine, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And Ishmael his son was thirteen years old, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin. <verse number="26" style="v"/>In the selfsame day was Abraham circumcised, and Ishmael his son. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And all the men of his house, those born in the house, and those bought with money of a foreigner, were circumcised with him.</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Jehovah appeared unto him by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">terebinths</char></char></note>oaks of Mamre, as he sat in the tent door in the heat of the day; <verse number="2" style="v"/>and he lifted up his eyes and looked, and, lo, three men stood over against him: and when he saw them, he ran to meet them from the tent door, and bowed himself to the earth, <verse number="3" style="v"/>and said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">O Lord</char></char></note>My lord, if now I have found favor in thy sight, pass not away, I pray thee, from thy servant: <verse number="4" style="v"/>let now a little water be fetched, and wash your feet, and rest yourselves under the tree: <verse number="5" style="v"/>and I will fetch a morsel of bread, and strengthen ye your heart; after that ye shall pass on: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for therefore</char></char></note>forasmuch as ye are come to your servant. And they said, So do, as thou hast said. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Abraham hastened into the tent unto Sarah, and said, Make ready quickly three measures of fine meal, knead it, and make cakes. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Abraham ran unto the herd, and fetched a calf tender and good, and gave it unto the servant; and he hasted to dress it. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he took butter, and milk, and the calf which he had dressed, and set it before them; and he stood by them under the tree, and they did eat.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And they said unto him, Where is Sarah thy wife? And he said, Behold, in the tent. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And he said, I will certainly return unto thee when the season <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">liveth</char>, or, <char style="it">reviveth</char>.</char></note>cometh round; and, lo, Sarah thy wife shall have a son. And Sarah heard in the tent door, which was behind him. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Now Abraham and Sarah were old, <char style="add">and</char> well stricken in age; it had ceased to be with Sarah after the manner of women. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Sarah laughed within herself, saying, After I am waxed old shall I have pleasure, my lord being old also? <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Jehovah said unto Abraham, Wherefore did Sarah laugh, saying, Shall I of a surety bear a child, who am old? <verse number="14" style="v"/>Is anything too <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wonderful</char></char></note>hard for Jehovah? At the set time I will return unto thee, when the season cometh round, and Sarah shall have a son. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Then Sarah denied, saying, I laughed not; for she was afraid. And he said, Nay; but thou didst laugh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And the men rose up from thence, and looked toward Sodom: and Abraham went with them to bring them on the way. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Jehovah said, Shall I hide from Abraham that which I do; <verse number="18" style="v"/>seeing that Abraham shall surely become a great and mighty nation, and all the nations of the earth shall be blessed in him? <verse number="19" style="v"/>For I have known him, to the end that he may command his children and his household after him, that they may keep the way of Jehovah, to do righteousness and justice; to the end that Jehovah may bring upon Abraham that which he hath spoken of him. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Jehovah said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Verily</char></char></note>Because the cry of Sodom and Gomorrah is great, and because their sin is very grievous; <verse number="21" style="v"/>I will go down now, and see whether they have done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come unto me; and if not, I will know.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And the men turned from thence, and went toward Sodom: but Abraham stood yet before Jehovah. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Abraham drew near, and said, Wilt thou consume the righteous with the wicked? <verse number="24" style="v"/>Peradventure there are fifty righteous within the city: wilt thou consume and not spare the place for the fifty righteous that are therein? <verse number="25" style="v"/>That be far from thee to do after this manner, to slay the righteous with the wicked, that so the righteous should be as the wicked; that be far from thee: shall not the Judge of all the earth do right? <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Jehovah said, If I find in Sodom fifty righteous within the city, then I will spare all the place for their sake. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Abraham answered and said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord, who am but dust and ashes: <verse number="28" style="v"/>peradventure there shall lack five of the fifty righteous: wilt thou destroy all the city for lack of five? And he said, I will not destroy it, if I find there forty and five. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And he spake unto him yet again, and said, Peradventure there shall be forty found there. And he said, I will not do it for the forty&#8217;s sake. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And he said, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak: peradventure there shall thirty be found there. And he said, I will not do it, if I find thirty there. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And he said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord: peradventure there shall be twenty found there. And he said, I will not destroy it for the twenty&#8217;s sake. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And he said, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak yet but this once: peradventure ten shall be found there. And he said, I will not destroy it for the ten&#8217;s sake. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And Jehovah went his way, as soon as he had left off communing with Abraham: and Abraham returned unto his place.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the two angels came to Sodom at even; and Lot sat in the gate of Sodom: and Lot saw them, and rose up to meet them; and he bowed himself with his face to the earth; <verse number="2" style="v"/>and he said, Behold now, my lords, turn aside, I pray you, into your servant&#8217;s house, and tarry all night, and wash your feet, and ye shall rise up early, and go on your way. And they said, Nay; but we will abide in the street all night. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he urged them greatly; and they turned in unto him, and entered into his house; and he made them a feast, and did bake unleavened bread, and they did eat. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But before they lay down, the men of the city, <char style="add">even</char> the men of Sodom, compassed the house round, both young and old, all the people from every quarter; <verse number="5" style="v"/>and they called unto Lot, and said unto him, Where are the men that came in to thee this night? bring them out unto us, that we may know them. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Lot went out unto them to the door, and shut the door after him. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he said, I pray you, my brethren, do not so wickedly. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Behold now, I have two daughters that have not known man; let me, I pray you, bring them out unto you, and do ye to them as is good in your eyes: only unto these men do nothing, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for therefore</char></char></note>forasmuch as they are come under the shadow of my roof. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And they said, Stand back. And they said, This one fellow came in to sojourn, and he will needs be a judge: now will we deal worse with thee, than with them. And they pressed sore upon the man, even Lot, and drew near to break the door. <verse number="10" style="v"/>But the men put forth their hand, and brought Lot into the house to them, and shut to the door. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And they smote the men that were at the door of the house with blindness, both small and great, so that they wearied themselves to find the door.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And the men said unto Lot, Hast thou here any besides? son-in-law, and thy sons, and thy daughters, and whomsoever thou hast in the city, bring them out of the place: <verse number="13" style="v"/>for we will destroy this place, because the cry of them is waxed great before Jehovah; and Jehovah hath sent us to destroy it. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Lot went out, and spake unto his sons-in-law, who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">were to marry</char></char></note>married his daughters, and said, Up, get you out of this place; for Jehovah will destroy the city. But he seemed unto his sons-in-law as one that mocked. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And when the morning arose, then the angels hastened Lot, saying, Arise, take thy wife, and thy two daughters that are here, lest thou be consumed in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">punishment</char></char></note>iniquity of the city. <verse number="16" style="v"/>But he lingered; and the men laid hold upon his hand, and upon the hand of his wife, and upon the hand of his two daughters, Jehovah being merciful unto him: and they brought him forth, and set him without the city. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when they had brought them forth abroad, that he said, Escape for thy life; look not behind thee, neither stay thou in all the Plain; escape to the mountain, lest thou be consumed. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Lot said unto them, Oh, not so, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">O Lord</char></char></note>my lord: <verse number="19" style="v"/>behold now, thy servant hath found favor in thy sight, and thou hast magnified thy lovingkindness, which thou hast showed unto me in saving my life; and I cannot escape to the mountain, lest <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the evil</char></char></note>evil overtake me, and I die: <verse number="20" style="v"/>behold now, this city is near to flee unto, and it is a little one. Oh let me escape thither (is it not a little one?), and my soul shall live. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And he said unto him, See, I have accepted thee concerning this thing also, that I will not overthrow the city of which thou hast spoken. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Haste thee, escape thither; for I cannot do anything till thou be come thither. Therefore the name of the city was called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Little</char>. See <ref loc="GEN 19:20">verse 20</ref>; <ref loc="GEN 14:8">14:8</ref>.</char></note>Zoar.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>The sun was risen upon the earth when Lot came unto Zoar. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Then Jehovah rained upon Sodom and upon Gomorrah brimstone and fire from Jehovah out of heaven; <verse number="25" style="v"/>and he overthrew those cities, and all the Plain, and all the inhabitants of the cities, and that which grew upon the ground. <verse number="26" style="v"/>But his wife looked back from behind him, and she became a pillar of salt. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Abraham gat up early in the morning to the place where he had stood before Jehovah: <verse number="28" style="v"/>and he looked toward Sodom and Gomorrah, and toward all the land of the Plain, and beheld, and, lo, the smoke of the land went up as the smoke of a furnace.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when God destroyed the cities of the Plain, that God remembered Abraham, and sent Lot out of the midst of the overthrow, when he overthrew the cities in which Lot dwelt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>And Lot went up out of Zoar, and dwelt in the mountain, and his two daughters with him; for he feared to dwell in Zoar: and he dwelt in a cave, he and his two daughters. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And the first-born said unto the younger, Our father is old, and there is not a man in the earth to come in unto us after the manner of all the earth: <verse number="32" style="v"/>come, let us make our father drink wine, and we will lie with him, that we may preserve seed of our father. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And they made their father drink wine that night: and the first-born went in, and lay with her father; and he knew not when she lay down, nor when she arose. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And it came to pass on the morrow, that the first-born said unto the younger, Behold, I lay yesternight with my father: let us make him drink wine this night also; and go thou in, and lie with him, that we may preserve seed of our father. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And they made their father drink wine that night also: and the younger arose, and lay with him; and he knew not when she lay down, nor when she arose. <verse number="36" style="v"/>Thus were both the daughters of Lot with child by their father. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And the first-born bare a son, and called his name Moab: the same is the father of the Moabites unto this day. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And the younger, she also bare a son, and called his name Ben-ammi: the same is the father of the children of Ammon unto this day.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Abraham journeyed from thence toward the land of the South, and dwelt between Kadesh and Shur; and he sojourned in Gerar. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Abraham said of Sarah his wife, She is my sister: and Abimelech king of Gerar sent, and took Sarah. <verse number="3" style="v"/>But God came to Abimelech in a dream of the night, and said to him, Behold, thou art but a dead man, because of the woman whom thou hast taken; for she is a man&#8217;s wife. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Now Abimelech had not come near her: and he said, Lord, wilt thou slay even a righteous nation? <verse number="5" style="v"/>Said he not himself unto me, She is my sister? and she, even she herself said, He is my brother: in the integrity of my heart and the innocency of my hands have I done this. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And God said unto him in the dream, Yea, I know that in the integrity of thy heart thou hast done this, and I also withheld thee from sinning against me: therefore suffered I thee not to touch her. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Now therefore restore the man&#8217;s wife; for he is a prophet, and he shall pray for thee, and thou shalt live: and if thou restore her not, know thou that thou shalt surely die, thou, and all that are thine.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And Abimelech rose early in the morning, and called all his servants, and told all these things in their ears: and the men were sore afraid. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Then Abimelech called Abraham, and said unto him, What hast thou done unto us? and wherein have I sinned against thee, that thou hast brought on me and on my kingdom a great sin? thou hast done deeds unto me that ought not to be done. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What sawest thou, that thou hast done this thing? <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Abraham said, Because I thought, Surely the fear of God is not in this place; and they will slay me for my wife&#8217;s sake. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And moreover she is indeed my sister, the daughter of my father, but not the daughter of my mother; and she became my wife: <verse number="13" style="v"/>and it came to pass, when God caused me to wander from my father&#8217;s house, that I said unto her, This is thy kindness which thou shalt show unto me: at every place whither we shall come, say of me, He is my brother. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Abimelech took sheep and oxen, and men-servants and women-servants, and gave them unto Abraham, and restored him Sarah his wife. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Abimelech said, Behold, my land is before thee: dwell where it pleaseth thee. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And unto Sarah he said, Behold, I have given thy brother a thousand pieces of silver: behold, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">he</char></char></note>it is for thee a covering of the eyes to all that are with thee; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">before all</char> men</char></note>in respect of all thou art righted. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Abraham prayed unto God: and God healed Abimelech, and his wife, and his maid-servants; and they bare children. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For Jehovah had fast closed up all the wombs of the house of Abimelech, because of Sarah, Abraham&#8217;s wife.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Jehovah visited Sarah as he had said, and Jehovah did unto Sarah as he had spoken. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Sarah conceived, and bare Abraham a son in his old age, at the set time of which God had spoken to him. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Abraham called the name of his son that was born unto him, whom Sarah bare to him, Isaac. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Abraham circumcised his son Isaac when he was eight days old, as God had commanded him. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Abraham was a hundred years old, when his son Isaac was born unto him. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Sarah said, God hath <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">prepared laughter for me</char></char></note>made me to laugh; every one that heareth will laugh with me. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And she said, Who would have said unto Abraham, that Sarah should give children suck? for I have borne him a son in his old age.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And the child grew, and was weaned: and Abraham made a great feast on the day that Isaac was weaned. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Sarah saw the son of Hagar the Egyptian, whom she had borne unto Abraham, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">playing</char></char></note>mocking. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Wherefore she said unto Abraham, Cast out this handmaid and her son: for the son of this handmaid shall not be heir with my son, even with Isaac. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the thing was very grievous in Abraham&#8217;s sight on account of his son. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And God said unto Abraham, Let it not be grievous in thy sight because of the lad, and because of thy handmaid; in all that Sarah saith unto thee, hearken unto her voice; for in Isaac shall thy seed be called. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And also of the son of the handmaid will I make a nation, because he is thy seed. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Abraham rose up early in the morning, and took bread and a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">skin</char></char></note>bottle of water, and gave it unto Hagar, putting it on her shoulder, and <char style="add">gave her</char> the child, and sent her away: and she departed, and wandered in the wilderness of Beer-sheba. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the water in the bottle was spent, and she cast the child under one of the shrubs. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And she went, and sat her down over against him a good way off, as it were a bowshot: for she said, Let me not look upon the death of the child. And she sat over against him, and lifted up her voice, and wept. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And God heard the voice of the lad; and the angel of God called to Hagar out of heaven, and said unto her, What aileth thee, Hagar? fear not; for God hath heard the voice of the lad where he is. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Arise, lift up the lad, and hold him in thy hand; for I will make him a great nation. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And God opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water; and she went, and filled the bottle with water, and gave the lad drink. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And God was with the lad, and he grew; and he dwelt in the wilderness, and became, as he grew up, an archer. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And he dwelt in the wilderness of Paran: and his mother took him a wife out of the land of Egypt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And it came to pass at that time, that Abimelech and Phicol the captain of his host spake unto Abraham, saying, God is with thee in all that thou doest: <verse number="23" style="v"/>now therefore swear unto me here by God that thou wilt not deal falsely with me, nor with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">my offspring, nor with my posterity</char></char></note>my son, nor with my son&#8217;s son: but according to the kindness that I have done unto thee, thou shalt do unto me, and to the land wherein thou hast sojourned. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Abraham said, I will swear. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And Abraham reproved Abimelech because of the well of water, which Abimelech&#8217;s servants had violently taken away. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Abimelech said, I know not who hath done this thing: neither didst thou tell me, neither yet heard I of it, but to-day. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Abraham took sheep and oxen, and gave them unto Abimelech; and they two made a covenant. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And Abraham set seven ewe lambs of the flock by themselves. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What mean these seven ewe lambs which thou hast set by themselves? <verse number="30" style="v"/>And he said, These seven ewe lambs shalt thou take of my hand, that it may be a witness unto me, that I have digged this well. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Wherefore he called that place Beer-sheba; because there they sware both of them. <verse number="32" style="v"/>So they made a covenant at Beer-sheba: and Abimelech rose up, and Phicol the captain of his host, and they returned into the land of the Philistines. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And <char style="add">Abraham</char> planted a tamarisk tree in Beer-sheba, and called there on the name of Jehovah, the Everlasting God. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And Abraham sojourned in the land of the Philistines many days.</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass after these things, that God did prove Abraham, and said unto him, Abraham; and he said, Here am I. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he said, Take now thy son, thine only son, whom thou lovest, even Isaac, and get thee into the land of Moriah; and offer him there for a burnt-offering upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Abraham rose early in the morning, and saddled his ass, and took two of his young men with him, and Isaac his son; and he clave the wood for the burnt-offering, and rose up, and went unto the place of which God had told him. <verse number="4" style="v"/>On the third day Abraham lifted up his eyes, and saw the place afar off. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Abraham said unto his young men, Abide ye here with the ass, and I and the lad will go yonder; and we will worship, and come again to you. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Abraham took the wood of the burnt-offering, and laid it upon Isaac his son; and he took in his hand the fire and the knife; and they went both of them together. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Isaac spake unto Abraham his father, and said, My father: and he said, Here am I, my son. And he said, Behold, the fire and the wood: but where is the lamb for a burnt-offering? <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Abraham said, God will <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">see for himself</char>.</char></note>provide himself the lamb for a burnt-offering, my son: so they went both of them together.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And they came to the place which God had told him of; and Abraham built the altar there, and laid the wood in order, and bound Isaac his son, and laid him on the altar, upon the wood. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Abraham stretched forth his hand, and took the knife to slay his son. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the angel of Jehovah called unto him out of heaven, and said, Abraham, Abraham: and he said, Here am I. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he said, Lay not thy hand upon the lad, neither do thou anything unto him; for now I know that thou fearest God, seeing thou hast not withheld thy son, thine only son, from me. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Abraham lifted up his eyes, and looked, and, behold, behind <char style="add">him</char> a ram caught in the thicket by his horns: and Abraham went and took the ram, and offered him up for a burnt-offering in the stead of his son. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Abraham called the name of that place <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Jehovah will see</char>, or <char style="it">provide</char>.</char></note>Jehovah-jireh: as it is said to this day, In the mount of Jehovah <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">he shall be seen</char></char></note>it shall be provided. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the angel of Jehovah called unto Abraham a second time out of heaven, <verse number="16" style="v"/>and said, By myself have I sworn, saith Jehovah, because thou hast done this thing, and hast not withheld thy son, thine only son, <verse number="17" style="v"/>that in blessing I will bless thee, and in multiplying I will multiply thy seed as the stars of the heavens, and as the sand which is upon the sea-shore; and thy seed shall possess the gate of his enemies; <verse number="18" style="v"/>and in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">bless themselves</char></char></note>be blessed; because thou hast obeyed my voice. <verse number="19" style="v"/>So Abraham returned unto his young men, and they rose up and went together to Beer-sheba; and Abraham dwelt at Beer-sheba.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And it came to pass after these things, that it was told Abraham, saying, Behold, Milcah, she also hath borne children unto thy brother Nahor: <verse number="21" style="v"/>Uz his first-born, and Buz his brother, and Kemuel the father of Aram, <verse number="22" style="v"/>and Chesed, and Hazo, and Pildash, and Jidlaph, and Bethuel. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Bethuel begat Rebekah: these eight did Milcah bear to Nahor, Abraham&#8217;s brother. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And his concubine, whose name was Reumah, she also bare Tebah, and Gaham, and Tahash, and Maacah.</para>
	<chapter number="23" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the life of Sarah was a hundred and seven and twenty years: these were the years of the life of Sarah. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Sarah died in Kiriath-arba (the same is Hebron), in the land of Canaan: and Abraham came to mourn for Sarah, and to weep for her. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Abraham rose up from before his dead, and spake unto the children of Heth, saying, <verse number="4" style="v"/>I am a stranger and a sojourner with you: give me a possession of a burying-place with you, that I may bury my dead out of my sight. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the children of Heth answered Abraham, saying unto him, <verse number="6" style="v"/>Hear us, my lord; thou art a prince of God among us: in the choice of our sepulchres bury thy dead; none of us shall withhold from thee his sepulchre, but that thou mayest bury thy dead. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Abraham rose up, and bowed himself to the people of the land, even to the children of Heth. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he communed with them, saying, If it be your mind that I should bury my dead out of my sight, hear me, and entreat for me to Ephron the son of Zohar, <verse number="9" style="v"/>that he may give me the cave of Machpelah, which he hath, which is in the end of his field; for the full price let him give it to me in the midst of you for a possession of a burying-place. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Now Ephron was sitting in the midst of the children of Heth: and Ephron the Hittite answered Abraham in the audience of the children of Heth, even of all that went in at the gate of his city, saying, <verse number="11" style="v"/>Nay, my lord, hear me: the field give I thee, and the cave that is therein, I give it thee; in the presence of the children of my people give I it thee: bury thy dead. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Abraham bowed himself down before the people of the land. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And he spake unto Ephron in the audience of the people of the land, saying, But if thou wilt, I pray thee, hear me: I will give the price of the field; take it of me, and I will bury my dead there. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Ephron answered Abraham, saying unto him, <verse number="15" style="v"/>My lord, hearken unto me: a piece of land worth four hundred shekels of silver, what is that betwixt me and thee? bury therefore thy dead. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Abraham hearkened unto Ephron; and Abraham weighed to Ephron the silver which he had named in the audience of the children of Heth, four hundred shekels of silver, current <char style="add">money</char> with the merchant.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>So the field of Ephron, which was in Machpelah, which was before Mamre, the field, and the cave which was therein, and all the trees that were in the field, that were in all the border thereof round about, were made sure <verse number="18" style="v"/>unto Abraham for a possession in the presence of the children of Heth, before all that went in at the gate of his city. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And after this, Abraham buried Sarah his wife in the cave of the field of Machpelah before Mamre (the same is Hebron), in the land of Canaan. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the field, and the cave that is therein, were made sure unto Abraham for a possession of a burying-place by the children of Heth.</para>
	<chapter number="24" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Abraham was old, <char style="add">and</char> well stricken in age: and Jehovah had blessed Abraham in all things. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Abraham said unto his servant, the elder of his house, that ruled over all that he had, Put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh: <verse number="3" style="v"/>and I will make thee swear by Jehovah, the God of heaven and the God of the earth, that thou wilt not take a wife for my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, among whom I dwell: <verse number="4" style="v"/>but thou shalt go unto my country, and to my kindred, and take a wife for my son Isaac. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the servant said unto him, Peradventure the woman will not be willing to follow me unto this land: must I needs bring thy son again unto the land from whence thou camest? <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Abraham said unto him, Beware thou that thou bring not my son thither again. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Jehovah, the God of heaven, who took me from my father&#8217;s house, and from the land of my nativity, and who spake unto me, and who sware unto me, saying, Unto thy seed will I give this land; he will send his angel before thee, and thou shalt take a wife for my son from thence. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And if the woman be not willing to follow thee, then thou shalt be clear from this my oath; only thou shalt not bring my son thither again. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the servant put his hand under the thigh of Abraham his master, and sware to him concerning this matter.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And the servant took ten camels, of the camels of his master, and departed, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for all the goods of his master were in his hand</char></char></note>having all goodly things of his master&#8217;s in his hand: and he arose, and went to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Aram-naharaim</char>, that is, <char style="it">Aram of the two rivers</char>.</char></note>Mesopotamia, unto the city of Nahor. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And he made the camels to kneel down without the city by the well of water at the time of evening, the time that women go out to draw water. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he said, O Jehovah, the God of my master Abraham, send me, I pray thee, good speed this day, and show kindness unto my master Abraham. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Behold, I am standing by the fountain of water; and the daughters of the men of the city are coming out to draw water: <verse number="14" style="v"/>and let it come to pass, that the damsel to whom I shall say, Let down thy pitcher, I pray thee, that I may drink; and she shall say, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also: let the same be she that thou hast appointed for thy servant Isaac; and thereby shall I know that thou hast showed kindness unto my master. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And it came to pass, before he had done speaking, that, behold, Rebekah came out, who was born to Bethuel the son of Milcah, the wife of Nahor, Abraham&#8217;s brother, with her pitcher upon her shoulder. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the damsel was very fair to look upon, a virgin, neither had any man known her: and she went down to the fountain, and filled her pitcher, and came up. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the servant ran to meet her, and said, Give me to drink, I pray thee, a little water from thy pitcher. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And she said, Drink, my lord: and she hasted, and let down her pitcher upon her hand, and gave him drink. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And when she had done giving him drink, she said, I will draw for thy camels also, until they have done drinking. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And she hasted, and emptied her pitcher into the trough, and ran again unto the well to draw, and drew for all his camels. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And the man looked stedfastly on her, holding his peace, to know whether Jehovah had made his journey prosperous or not. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as the camels had done drinking, that the man took a golden ring of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">a beka</char>. See <ref loc="EXO 38:26">Ex. 38:26</ref>.</char></note>half a shekel weight, and two bracelets for her hands of ten shekels weight of gold, <verse number="23" style="v"/>and said, Whose daughter art thou? tell me, I pray thee. Is there room in thy father&#8217;s house for us to lodge in? <verse number="24" style="v"/>And she said unto him, I am the daughter of Bethuel the son of Milcah, whom she bare unto Nahor. <verse number="25" style="v"/>She said moreover unto him, We have both straw and provender enough, and room to lodge in. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And the man bowed his head, and worshipped Jehovah. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And he said, Blessed be Jehovah, the God of my master Abraham, who hath not forsaken his lovingkindness and his truth toward my master: as for me, Jehovah hath led me in the way to the house of my master&#8217;s brethren.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And the damsel ran, and told her mother&#8217;s house according to these words. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Rebekah had a brother, and his name was Laban: and Laban ran out unto the man, unto the fountain. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when he saw the ring, and the bracelets upon his sister&#8217;s hands, and when he heard the words of Rebekah his sister, saying, Thus spake the man unto me; that he came unto the man; and, behold, he was standing by the camels at the fountain. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And he said, Come in, thou blessed of Jehovah; wherefore standest thou without? for I have prepared the house, and room for the camels. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And the man came into the house, and he ungirded the camels; and he gave straw and provender for the camels, and water to wash his feet and the feet of the men that were with him. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And there was set food before him to eat: but he said, I will not eat, until I have told mine errand. And he said, Speak on. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And he said, I am Abraham&#8217;s servant. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And Jehovah hath blessed my master greatly; and he is become great: and he hath given him flocks and herds, and silver and gold, and men-servants and maid-servants, and camels and asses. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And Sarah my master&#8217;s wife bare a son to my master when she was old: and unto him hath he given all that he hath. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And my master made me swear, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife for my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, in whose land I dwell: <verse number="38" style="v"/>but thou shalt go unto my father&#8217;s house, and to my kindred, and take a wife for my son. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And I said unto my master, Peradventure the woman will not follow me. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And he said unto me, Jehovah, before whom I walk, will send his angel with thee, and prosper thy way; and thou shalt take a wife for my son of my kindred, and of my father&#8217;s house: <verse number="41" style="v"/>then shalt thou be clear from my oath, when thou comest to my kindred; and if they give her not to thee, thou shalt be clear from my oath. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And I came this day unto the fountain, and said, O Jehovah, the God of my master Abraham, if now thou do prosper my way which I go: <verse number="43" style="v"/>behold, I am standing by the fountain of water; and let it come to pass, that the maiden that cometh forth to draw, to whom I shall say, Give me, I pray thee, a little water from thy pitcher to drink; <verse number="44" style="v"/>and she shall say to me, Both drink thou, and I will also draw for thy camels: let the same be the woman whom Jehovah hath appointed for my master&#8217;s son. <verse number="45" style="v"/>And before I had done speaking in my heart, behold, Rebekah came forth with her pitcher on her shoulder; and she went down unto the fountain, and drew: and I said unto her, Let me drink, I pray thee. <verse number="46" style="v"/>And she made haste, and let down her pitcher from her shoulder, and said, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also: so I drank, and she made the camels drink also. <verse number="47" style="v"/>And I asked her, and said, Whose daughter art thou? And she said, The daughter of Bethuel, Nahor&#8217;s son, whom Milcah bare unto him: and I put the ring upon her nose, and the bracelets upon her hands. <verse number="48" style="v"/>And I bowed my head, and worshipped Jehovah, and blessed Jehovah, the God of my master Abraham, who had led me in the right way to take my master&#8217;s brother&#8217;s daughter for his son. <verse number="49" style="v"/>And now if ye will deal kindly and truly with my master, tell me: and if not, tell me; that I may turn to the right hand, or to the left.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v"/>Then Laban and Bethuel answered and said, The thing proceedeth from Jehovah: we cannot speak unto thee bad or good. <verse number="51" style="v"/>Behold, Rebekah is before thee, take her, and go, and let her be thy master&#8217;s son&#8217;s wife, as Jehovah hath spoken. <verse number="52" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that, when Abraham&#8217;s servant heard their words, he bowed himself down to the earth unto Jehovah. <verse number="53" style="v"/>And the servant brought forth jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment, and gave them to Rebekah: he gave also to her brother and to her mother precious things. <verse number="54" style="v"/>And they did eat and drink, he and the men that were with him, and tarried all night; and they rose up in the morning, and he said, Send me away unto my master. <verse number="55" style="v"/>And her brother and her mother said, Let the damsel abide with us <char style="add">a few</char> days, at the least ten; after that she shall go. <verse number="56" style="v"/>And he said unto them, Hinder me not, seeing Jehovah hath prospered my way; send me away that I may go to my master. <verse number="57" style="v"/>And they said, We will call the damsel, and inquire at her mouth. <verse number="58" style="v"/>And they called Rebekah, and said unto her, Wilt thou go with this man? And she said, I will go. <verse number="59" style="v"/>And they sent away Rebekah their sister, and her nurse, and Abraham&#8217;s servant, and his men. <verse number="60" style="v"/>And they blessed Rebekah, and said unto her, Our sister, be thou <char style="add">the mother</char> of thousands of ten thousands, and let thy seed possess the gate of those that hate them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="61" style="v"/>And Rebekah arose, and her damsels, and they rode upon the camels, and followed the man: and the servant took Rebekah, and went his way. <verse number="62" style="v"/>And Isaac came from the way of Beer-lahai-roi; for he dwelt in the land of the South. <verse number="63" style="v"/>And Isaac went out to meditate in the field at the eventide: and he lifted up his eyes, and saw, and, behold, there were camels coming. <verse number="64" style="v"/>And Rebekah lifted up her eyes, and when she saw Isaac, she alighted from the camel. <verse number="65" style="v"/>And she said unto the servant, What man is this that walketh in the field to meet us? And the servant said, It is my master: and she took her veil, and covered herself. <verse number="66" style="v"/>And the servant told Isaac all the things that he had done. <verse number="67" style="v"/>And Isaac brought her into his mother Sarah&#8217;s tent, and took Rebekah, and she became his wife; and he loved her: and Isaac was comforted after his mother&#8217;s death.</para>
	<chapter number="25" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Abraham took another wife, and her name was Keturah. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And she bare him Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Jokshan begat Sheba, and Dedan. And the sons of Dedan were Asshurim, and Letushim, and Leummim. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the sons of Midian: Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abida, and Eldaah. All these were the children of Keturah. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Abraham gave all that he had unto Isaac. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But unto the sons of the concubines, that Abraham had, Abraham gave gifts; and he sent them away from Isaac his son, while he yet lived, eastward, unto the east country. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And these are the days of the years of Abraham&#8217;s life which he lived, a hundred threescore and fifteen years. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Abraham gave up the ghost, and died in a good old age, an old man, and full <char style="add">of years</char>, and was gathered to his people. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Isaac and Ishmael his sons buried him in the cave of Machpelah, in the field of Ephron the son of Zohar the Hittite, which is before Mamre; <verse number="10" style="v"/>the field which Abraham purchased of the children of Heth: there was Abraham buried, and Sarah his wife. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And it came to pass after the death of Abraham, that God blessed Isaac his son: and Isaac dwelt by Beer-lahai-roi.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Now these are the generations of Ishmael, Abraham&#8217;s son, whom Hagar the Egyptian, Sarah&#8217;s handmaid, bare unto Abraham: <verse number="13" style="v"/>and these are the names of the sons of Ishmael, by their names, according to their generations: the first-born of Ishmael, Nebaioth; and Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam, <verse number="14" style="v"/>and Mishma, and Dumah, and Massa, <verse number="15" style="v"/>Hadad, and Tema, Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah: <verse number="16" style="v"/>these are the sons of Ishmael, and these are their names, by their villages, and by their encampments; twelve princes according to their nations. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And these are the years of the life of Ishmael, a hundred and thirty and seven years: and he gave up the ghost and died, and was gathered unto his people. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And they dwelt from Havilah unto Shur that is before Egypt, as thou goest toward Assyria: he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">settled</char>. Hebrew <char style="it">fell</char></char></note>abode over against all his brethren.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>And these are the generations of Isaac, Abraham&#8217;s son: Abraham begat Isaac: <verse number="20" style="v"/>and Isaac was forty years old when he took Rebekah, the daughter of Bethuel the Syrian of Paddan-aram, the sister of Laban the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Aramean</char>.</char></note>Syrian, to be his wife. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Isaac entreated Jehovah for his wife, because she was barren: and Jehovah was entreated of him, and Rebekah his wife conceived. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the children struggled together within her; and she said, If it be so, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wherefore am I thus?</char></char></note>wherefore do I live? And she went to inquire of Jehovah. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Jehovah said unto her,</para>
	<para style="q1">Two nations are in thy womb,</para>
	<para style="q1">And two peoples shall be separated from thy bowels:</para>
	<para style="q1">And the one people shall be stronger than the other people;</para>
	<para style="q1">And the elder shall serve the younger.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>And when her days to be delivered were fulfilled, behold, there were twins in her womb. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And the first came forth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">ruddy</char></char></note>red, all over like a hairy garment; and they called his name Esau. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And after that came forth his brother, and his hand had hold on Esau&#8217;s heel; and his name was called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">One that takes by the heel</char> or <char style="it">supplants</char>.</char></note>Jacob: and Isaac was threescore years old when she bare them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v"/>And the boys grew: and Esau was a skilful hunter, a man of the field; and Jacob was a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">harmless</char>. Hebrew <char style="it">perfect</char>.</char></note>quiet man, dwelling in tents. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Now Isaac loved Esau, because he did eat of his venison: and Rebekah loved Jacob. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Jacob boiled pottage: and Esau came in from the field, and he was faint: <verse number="30" style="v"/>and Esau said to Jacob, Feed me, I pray thee, with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">the red</char> pottage, <char style="it">this red</char> pottage.</char></note>that same red <char style="add">pottage</char>; for I am faint: therefore was his name called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Red</char>.</char></note>Edom. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And Jacob said, Sell me <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">to-day</char>.</char></note>first thy birthright. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And Esau said, Behold, I am about to die: and what profit shall the birthright do to me? <verse number="33" style="v"/>And Jacob said, Swear to me first; and he sware unto him: and he sold his birthright unto Jacob. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And Jacob gave Esau bread and pottage of lentils; and he did eat and drink, and rose up, and went his way: so Esau despised his birthright.</para>
	<chapter number="26" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And there was a famine in the land, besides the first famine that was in the days of Abraham. And Isaac went unto Abimelech king of the Philistines, unto Gerar. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Jehovah appeared unto him, and said, Go not down into Egypt; dwell in the land which I shall tell thee of: <verse number="3" style="v"/>sojourn in this land, and I will be with thee, and will bless thee; for unto thee, and unto thy seed, I will give all these lands, and I will establish the oath which I sware unto Abraham thy father; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and I will multiply thy seed as the stars of heaven, and will give unto thy seed all these lands; and in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">bless themselves</char></char></note>be blessed; <verse number="5" style="v"/>because that Abraham obeyed my voice, and kept my charge, my commandments, my statutes, and my laws. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Isaac dwelt in Gerar: <verse number="7" style="v"/>and the men of the place asked him of his wife; and he said, She is my sister: for he feared to say, My wife; lest, <char style="add">said he</char>, the men of the place should kill me for Rebekah; because she was fair to look upon. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when he had been there a long time, that Abimelech king of the Philistines looked out at a window, and saw, and, behold, Isaac was sporting with Rebekah his wife. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Abimelech called Isaac, and said, Behold, of a surety she is thy wife: and how saidst thou, She is my sister? And Isaac said unto him, Because I said, Lest I die because of her. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Abimelech said, What is this thou hast done unto us? one of the people might easily have lain with thy wife, and thou wouldest have brought guiltiness upon us. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Abimelech charged all the people, saying, He that toucheth this man or his wife shall surely be put to death.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And Isaac sowed in that land, and found in the same year a hundredfold: and Jehovah blessed him. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And the man waxed great, and grew more and more until he became very great: <verse number="14" style="v"/>and he had possessions of flocks, and possessions of herds, and a great household: and the Philistines envied him. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Now all the wells which his father&#8217;s servants had digged in the days of Abraham his father, the Philistines had stopped, and filled with earth. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Abimelech said unto Isaac, Go from us; for thou art much mightier than we. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Isaac departed thence, and encamped in the valley of Gerar, and dwelt there.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Isaac digged again the wells of water, which they had digged in the days of Abraham his father; for the Philistines had stopped them after the death of Abraham: and he called their names after the names by which his father had called them. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Isaac&#8217;s servants digged in the valley, and found there a well of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">living</char>.</char></note>springing water. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the herdsmen of Gerar strove with Isaac&#8217;s herdsmen, saying, The water is ours: and he called the name of the well <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Contention</char>.</char></note>Esek, because they contended with him. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And they digged another well, and they strove for that also: and he called the name of it <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Enmity</char>.</char></note>Sitnah. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And he removed from thence, and digged another well; and for that they strove not: and he called the name of it <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Broad places</char>, or, <char style="it">Room</char>.</char></note>Rehoboth; and he said, For now Jehovah hath made room for us, and we shall be fruitful in the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>And he went up from thence to Beer-sheba. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Jehovah appeared unto him the same night, and said, I am the God of Abraham thy father: fear not, for I am with thee, and will bless thee, and multiply thy seed for my servant Abraham&#8217;s sake. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And he builded an altar there, and called upon the name of Jehovah, and pitched his tent there: and there Isaac&#8217;s servants digged a well.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>Then Abimelech went to him from Gerar, and Ahuzzath his friend, and Phicol the captain of his host. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Isaac said unto them, Wherefore are ye come unto me, seeing ye hate me, and have sent me away from you? <verse number="28" style="v"/>And they said, We saw plainly that Jehovah was with thee: and we said, Let there now be an oath betwixt us, even betwixt us and thee, and let us make a covenant with thee, <verse number="29" style="v"/>that thou wilt do us no hurt, as we have not touched thee, and as we have done unto thee nothing but good, and have sent thee away in peace: thou art now the blessed of Jehovah. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And he made them a feast, and they did eat and drink. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And they rose up betimes in the morning, and sware one to another: and Isaac sent them away, and they departed from him in peace. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And it came to pass the same day, that Isaac&#8217;s servants came, and told him concerning the well which they had digged, and said unto him, We have found water. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And he called it Shibah: therefore the name of the city is Beer-sheba unto this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v"/>And when Esau was forty years old he took to wife Judith the daughter of Beeri the Hittite, and Basemath the daughter of Elon the Hittite: <verse number="35" style="v"/>and they were <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">bitterness of spirit</char>.</char></note>a grief of mind unto Isaac and to Rebekah.</para>
	<chapter number="27" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that when Isaac was old, and his eyes were dim, so that he could not see, he called Esau his elder son, and said unto him, My son: and he said unto him, Here am I. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he said, Behold now, I am old, I know not the day of my death. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Now therefore take, I pray thee, thy weapons, thy quiver and thy bow, and go out to the field, and take me venison; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and make me savory food, such as I love, and bring it to me, that I may eat; that my soul may bless thee before I die.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>And Rebekah heard when Isaac spake to Esau his son. And Esau went to the field to hunt for venison, and to bring it. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Rebekah spake unto Jacob her son, saying, Behold, I heard thy father speak unto Esau thy brother, saying, <verse number="7" style="v"/>Bring me venison, and make me savory food, that I may eat, and bless thee before Jehovah before my death. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Now therefore, my son, obey my voice according to that which I command thee. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Go now to the flock, and fetch me from thence two good kids of the goats; and I will make them savory food for thy father, such as he loveth: <verse number="10" style="v"/>and thou shalt bring it to thy father, that he may eat, so that he may bless thee before his death. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Jacob said to Rebekah his mother, Behold, Esau my brother is a hairy man, and I am a smooth man. <verse number="12" style="v"/>My father peradventure will feel me, and I shall seem to him as a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">mocker</char></char></note>deceiver; and I shall bring a curse upon me, and not a blessing. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And his mother said unto him, Upon me be thy curse, my son; only obey my voice, and go fetch me them. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And he went, and fetched, and brought them to his mother: and his mother made savory food, such as his father loved. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Rebekah took the goodly garments of Esau her elder son, which were with her in the house, and put them upon Jacob her younger son; <verse number="16" style="v"/>and she put the skins of the kids of the goats upon his hands, and upon the smooth of his neck: <verse number="17" style="v"/>and she gave the savory food and the bread, which she had prepared, into the hand of her son Jacob.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And he came unto his father, and said, My father: and he said, Here am I; who art thou, my son? <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Jacob said unto his father, I am Esau thy first-born; I have done according as thou badest me: arise, I pray thee, sit and eat of my venison, that thy soul may bless me. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Isaac said unto his son, How is it that thou hast found it so quickly, my son? And he said, Because Jehovah thy God sent me good speed. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Isaac said unto Jacob, Come near, I pray thee, that I may feel thee, my son, whether thou be my very son Esau or not. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Jacob went near unto Isaac his father; and he felt him, and said, The voice is Jacob&#8217;s voice, but the hands are the hands of Esau. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he discerned him not, because his hands were hairy, as his brother Esau&#8217;s hands: so he blessed him. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And he said, Art thou my very son Esau? And he said, I am. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And he said, Bring it near to me, and I will eat of my son&#8217;s venison, that my soul may bless thee. And he brought it near to him, and he did eat: and he brought him wine, and he drank. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And his father Isaac said unto him, Come near now, and kiss me, my son. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And he came near, and kissed him: and he smelled the smell of his raiment, and blessed him, and said,</para>
	<para style="q1">See, the smell of my son</para>
	<para style="q1">Is as the smell of a field which Jehovah hath blessed:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And God give thee of the dew of heaven,</para>
	<para style="q1">And of the fatness of the earth,</para>
	<para style="q1">And plenty of grain and new wine:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="29" style="v"/>Let peoples serve thee,</para>
	<para style="q1">And nations bow down to thee:</para>
	<para style="q1">Be lord over thy brethren,</para>
	<para style="q1">And let thy mother&#8217;s sons bow down to thee:</para>
	<para style="q1">Cursed be every one that curseth thee,</para>
	<para style="q1">And blessed be every one that blesseth thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as soon as Isaac had made an end of blessing Jacob, and Jacob was yet scarce gone out from the presence of Isaac his father, that Esau his brother came in from his hunting. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And he also made savory food, and brought it unto his father; and he said unto his father, Let my father arise, and eat of his son&#8217;s venison, that thy soul may bless me. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And Isaac his father said unto him, Who art thou? And he said, I am thy son, thy first-born, Esau. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And Isaac trembled very exceedingly, and said, Who then is he that hath taken venison, and brought it me, and I have eaten of all before thou camest, and have blessed him? yea, <char style="add">and</char> he shall be blessed. <verse number="34" style="v"/>When Esau heard the words of his father, he cried with an exceeding great and bitter cry, and said unto his father, Bless me, even me also, O my father. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And he said, Thy brother came with guile, and hath taken away thy blessing. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And he said, Is not he rightly named Jacob? for he hath supplanted me these two times: he took away my birthright; and, behold, now he hath taken away my blessing. And he said, Hast thou not reserved a blessing for me? <verse number="37" style="v"/>And Isaac answered and said unto Esau, Behold, I have made him thy lord, and all his brethren have I given to him for servants; and with grain and new wine have I sustained him: and what then shall I do for thee, my son? <verse number="38" style="v"/>And Esau said unto his father, Hast thou but one blessing, my father? bless me, even me also, O my father. And Esau lifted up his voice, and wept. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And Isaac his father answered and said unto him,</para>
	<para style="q1">Behold, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">away from</char></char></note>of the fatness of the earth shall be thy dwelling,</para>
	<para style="q1">And of the dew of heaven from above;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="40" style="v"/>And by thy sword shalt thou live, and thou shalt serve thy brother;</para>
	<para style="q1">And it shall come to pass, when thou shalt break loose,</para>
	<para style="q1">That thou shalt shake his yoke from off thy neck.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v"/>And Esau hated Jacob because of the blessing wherewith his father blessed him: and Esau said in his heart, The days of mourning for my father are at hand; then will I slay my brother Jacob. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And the words of Esau her elder son were told to Rebekah; and she sent and called Jacob her younger son, and said unto him, Behold, thy brother Esau, as touching thee, doth comfort himself, <char style="add">purposing</char> to kill thee. <verse number="43" style="v"/>Now therefore, my son, obey my voice; and arise, flee thou to Laban my brother to Haran; <verse number="44" style="v"/>and tarry with him a few days, until thy brother&#8217;s fury turn away; <verse number="45" style="v"/>until thy brother&#8217;s anger turn away from thee, and he forget that which thou hast done to him: then I will send, and fetch thee from thence: why should I be bereaved of you both in one day?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v"/>And Rebekah said to Isaac, I am weary of my life because of the daughters of Heth: if Jacob take a wife of the daughters of Heth, such as these, of the daughters of the land, what good shall my life do me?</para>
	<chapter number="28" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Isaac called Jacob, and blessed him, and charged him, and said unto him, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Arise, go to Paddan-aram, to the house of Bethuel thy mother&#8217;s father; and take thee a wife from thence of the daughters of Laban thy mother&#8217;s brother. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El Shaddai</char>.</char></note>God Almighty bless thee, and make thee fruitful, and multiply thee, that thou mayest be a company of peoples; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and give thee the blessing of Abraham, to thee, and to thy seed with thee; that thou mayest inherit the land of thy sojournings, which God gave unto Abraham. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Isaac sent away Jacob: and he went to Paddan-aram unto Laban, son of Bethuel the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Aramean</char>.</char></note>Syrian, the brother of Rebekah, Jacob&#8217;s and Esau&#8217;s mother.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>Now Esau saw that Isaac had blessed Jacob and sent him away to Paddan-aram, to take him a wife from thence; and that as he blessed him he gave him a charge, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan; <verse number="7" style="v"/>and that Jacob obeyed his father and his mother, and was gone to Paddan-aram: <verse number="8" style="v"/>and Esau saw that the daughters of Canaan pleased not Isaac his father; <verse number="9" style="v"/>and Esau went unto Ishmael, and took, besides the wives that he had, Mahalath the daughter of Ishmael Abraham&#8217;s son, the sister of Nebaioth, to be his wife.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And Jacob went out from Beer-sheba, and went toward Haran. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And he lighted upon <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">the place</char>.</char></note>a certain place, and tarried there all night, because the sun was set; and he took one of the stones of the place, and put it under his head, and lay down in that place to sleep. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he dreamed; and, behold, a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reached to heaven; and, behold, the angels of God ascending and descending on it. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And, behold, Jehovah stood <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">beside him</char></char></note>above it, and said, I am Jehovah, the God of Abraham thy father, and the God of Isaac: the land whereon thou liest, to thee will I give it, and to thy seed; <verse number="14" style="v"/>and thy seed shall be as the dust of the earth, and thou shalt <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">break forth</char>.</char></note>spread abroad to the west, and to the east, and to the north, and to the south: and in thee and in thy seed shall all the families of the earth be blessed. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And, behold, I am with thee, and will keep thee whithersoever thou goest, and will bring thee again into this land; for I will not leave thee, until I have done that which I have spoken to thee of. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Jacob awaked out of his sleep, and he said, Surely Jehovah is in this place; and I knew it not. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And he was afraid, and said, How dreadful is this place! this is none other than the house of God, and this is the gate of heaven.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Jacob rose up early in the morning, and took the stone that he had put under his head, and set it up for a pillar, and poured oil upon the top of it. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And he called the name of that place <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The house of God</char>.</char></note>Beth-el: but the name of the city was Luz at the first. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Jacob vowed a vow, saying, If God will be with me, and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me bread to eat, and raiment to put on, <verse number="21" style="v"/>so that I come again to my father&#8217;s house in peace, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">then shall Jehovah be my God, and this stone etc.</char></char></note>and Jehovah will be my God, <verse number="22" style="v"/>then this stone, which I have set up for a pillar, shall be God&#8217;s house: and of all that thou shalt give me I will surely give the tenth unto thee.</para>
	<chapter number="29" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Then Jacob <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">lifted up his feet</char>.</char></note>went on his journey, and came to the land of the children of the east. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he looked, and, behold, a well in the field, and, lo, three flocks of sheep lying there by it; for out of that well they watered the flocks: and the stone upon the well&#8217;s mouth was great. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And thither were all the flocks gathered: and they rolled the stone from the well&#8217;s mouth, and watered the sheep, and put the stone again upon the well&#8217;s mouth in its place. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Jacob said unto them, My brethren, whence are ye? And they said, Of Haran are we. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And he said unto them, Know ye Laban the son of Nahor? And they said, We know him. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he said unto them, Is it well with him? And they said, It is well: and, behold, Rachel his daughter cometh with the sheep. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he said, Lo, it is yet high day, neither is it time that the cattle should be gathered together: water ye the sheep, and go and feed them. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And they said, We cannot, until all the flocks be gathered together, and they roll the stone from the well&#8217;s mouth; then we water the sheep. <verse number="9" style="v"/>While he was yet speaking with them, Rachel came with her father&#8217;s sheep; for she kept them. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when Jacob saw Rachel the daughter of Laban his mother&#8217;s brother, and the sheep of Laban his mother&#8217;s brother, that Jacob went near, and rolled the stone from the well&#8217;s mouth, and watered the flock of Laban his mother&#8217;s brother. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Jacob kissed Rachel, and lifted up his voice, and wept. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Jacob told Rachel that he was her father&#8217;s brother, and that he was Rebekah&#8217;s son: and she ran and told her father.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when Laban heard the tidings of Jacob his sister&#8217;s son, that he ran to meet him, and embraced him, and kissed him, and brought him to his house. And he told Laban all these things. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Laban said to him, Surely thou art my bone and my flesh. And he abode with him the space of a month. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Laban said unto Jacob, Because thou art my brother, shouldest thou therefore serve me for nought? tell me, what shall thy wages be? <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Laban had two daughters: the name of the elder was Leah, and the name of the younger was Rachel. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Leah&#8217;s eyes were tender; but Rachel was beautiful and well-favored. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Jacob loved Rachel; and he said, I will serve thee seven years for Rachel thy younger daughter. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Laban said, It is better that I give her to thee, than that I should give her to another man: abide with me. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Jacob served seven years for Rachel; and they seemed unto him but a few days, for the love he had to her.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>And Jacob said unto Laban, Give me my wife, for my days are fulfilled, that I may go in unto her. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Laban gathered together all the men of the place, and made a feast. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And it came to pass in the evening, that he took Leah his daughter, and brought her to him; and he went in unto her. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Laban gave Zilpah his handmaid unto his daughter Leah for a handmaid. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And it came to pass in the morning that, behold, it was Leah: and he said to Laban, What is this thou hast done unto me? did not I serve with thee for Rachel? wherefore then hast thou beguiled me? <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Laban said, It is not so done in our place, to give the younger before the first-born. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Fulfil the week of this one, and we will give thee the other also for the service which thou shalt serve with me yet seven other years. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And Jacob did so, and fulfilled her week: and he gave him Rachel his daughter to wife. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Laban gave to Rachel his daughter Bilhah his handmaid to be her handmaid. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And he went in also unto Rachel, and he loved also Rachel more than Leah, and served with him yet seven other years.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>And Jehovah saw that Leah was hated, and he opened her womb: but Rachel was barren. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And Leah conceived, and bare a son, and she called his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">See, a son</char>.</char></note>Reuben: for she said, Because Jehovah hath looked upon my affliction; for now my husband will love me. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And she conceived again, and bare a son: and said, Because Jehovah <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">shama</char>.</char></note>hath heard that I am hated, he hath therefore given me this <char style="add">son</char> also: and she called his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Shimeon</char>.</char></note>Simeon. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And she conceived again, and bare a son; and said, Now this time will my husband be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">From the root <char style="it">lavah</char>.</char></note>joined unto me, because I have borne him three sons: therefore was his name called Levi. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And she conceived again, and bare a son: and she said, This time will I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">From the Hebrew <char style="it">hodah</char>.</char></note>praise Jehovah: therefore she called his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Jehudah</char>.</char></note>Judah; and she left off bearing.</para>
	<chapter number="30" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And when Rachel saw that she bare Jacob no children, Rachel envied her sister; and she said unto Jacob, Give me children, or else I die. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Jacob&#8217;s anger was kindled against Rachel: and he said, Am I in God&#8217;s stead, who hath withheld from thee the fruit of the womb? <verse number="3" style="v"/>And she said, Behold, my maid Bilhah, go in unto her; that she may bear upon my knees, and I also may <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">be builded by her</char>.</char></note>obtain children by her. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And she gave him Bilhah her handmaid to wife: and Jacob went in unto her. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Bilhah conceived, and bare Jacob a son. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Rachel said, God hath <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">dan</char>, he judged.</char></note>judged me, and hath also heard my voice, and hath given me a son: therefore called she his name Dan. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Bilhah Rachel&#8217;s handmaid conceived again, and bare Jacob a second son. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Rachel said, With <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">wrestlings of God</char>.</char></note>mighty wrestlings have I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">niphtal</char>, he wrestled.</char></note>wrestled with my sister, and have prevailed: and she called his name Naphtali.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>When Leah saw that she had left off bearing, she took Zilpah her handmaid, and gave her to Jacob to wife. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Zilpah Leah&#8217;s handmaid bare Jacob a son. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Leah said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">With fortune!</char> Another reading is, <char style="it">Fortune is come</char>.</char></note>Fortunate! and she called his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Fortune</char>.</char></note>Gad. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Zilpah Leah&#8217;s handmaid bare Jacob a second son. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Leah said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">With my happiness!</char></char></note>Happy am I! for the daughters will call me happy: and she called his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Happy</char>.</char></note>Asher.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And Reuben went in the days of wheat harvest, and found <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">love apples</char></char></note>mandrakes in the field, and brought them unto his mother Leah. Then Rachel said to Leah, Give me, I pray thee, of thy son&#8217;s mandrakes. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And she said unto her, Is it a small matter that thou hast taken away my husband? and wouldest thou take away my son&#8217;s mandrakes also? And Rachel said, Therefore he shall lie with thee to-night for thy son&#8217;s mandrakes. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Jacob came from the field in the evening, and Leah went out to meet him, and said, Thou must come in unto me; for I have surely hired thee with my son&#8217;s mandrakes. And he lay with her that night. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And God hearkened unto Leah, and she conceived, and bare Jacob a fifth son. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Leah said, God hath given me my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">sachar</char>.</char></note>hire, because I gave my handmaid to my husband: and she called his name Issachar. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Leah conceived again, and bare a sixth son to Jacob. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Leah said, God hath endowed me with a good dowry; now will my husband <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">zabal</char>, he dwelt.</char></note>dwell with me, because I have borne him six sons: and she called his name Zebulun. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And afterwards she bare a daughter, and called her name Dinah. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And God remembered Rachel, and God hearkened to her, and opened her womb. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And she conceived, and bare a son: and said, God hath taken away my reproach: <verse number="24" style="v"/>and she called his name Joseph, saying, Jehovah <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">joseph</char>.</char></note>add to me another son.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when Rachel had borne Joseph, that Jacob said unto Laban, Send me away, that I may go unto mine own place, and to my country. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Give me my wives and my children for whom I have served thee, and let me go: for thou knowest my service wherewith I have served thee. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Laban said unto him, If now I have found favor in thine eyes, <char style="add">tarry</char>: <char style="add">for</char> I have divined that Jehovah hath blessed me for thy sake. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And he said, Appoint me thy wages, and I will give it. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And he said unto him, Thou knowest how I have served thee, and how thy cattle have fared with me. <verse number="30" style="v"/>For it was little which thou hadst before I came, and it hath <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">broken forth</char>.</char></note>increased unto a multitude; and Jehovah hath blessed thee <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">at my foot</char>.</char></note>whithersoever I turned: and now when shall I provide for mine own house also? <verse number="31" style="v"/>And he said, What shall I give thee? And Jacob said, Thou shalt not give me aught: if thou wilt do this thing for me, I will again feed thy flock and keep it. <verse number="32" style="v"/>I will pass through all thy flock to-day, removing from thence every speckled and spotted one, and every black one among the sheep, and the spotted and speckled among the goats: and <char style="add">of such</char> shall be my hire. <verse number="33" style="v"/>So shall my righteousness answer for me hereafter, when thou shalt come concerning my hire that is before thee: every one that is not speckled and spotted among the goats, and black among the sheep, that, <char style="add">if found</char> with me, shall be counted stolen. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And Laban said, Behold, I would it might be according to thy word. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And he removed that day the he-goats that were ringstreaked and spotted, and all the she-goats that were speckled and spotted, every one that had white in it, and all the black ones among the sheep, and gave them into the hand of his sons; <verse number="36" style="v"/>and he set three days&#8217; journey betwixt himself and Jacob: and Jacob fed the rest of Laban&#8217;s flocks.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v"/>And Jacob took him rods of fresh <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">storax-tree</char></char></note>poplar, and of the almond and of the plane-tree; and peeled white streaks in them, and made the white appear which was in the rods. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And he set the rods which he had peeled over against the flocks in the gutters in the watering-troughs where the flocks came to drink; and they conceived when they came to drink. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And the flocks conceived before the rods, and the flocks brought forth ringstreaked, speckled, and spotted. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And Jacob separated the lambs, and set the faces of the flocks toward the ringstreaked and all the black in the flock of Laban: and he put his own droves apart, and put them not unto Laban&#8217;s flock. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And it came to pass, whensoever the stronger of the flock did conceive, that Jacob laid the rods before the eyes of the flock in the gutters, that they might conceive among the rods; <verse number="42" style="v"/>but when the flock were feeble, he put them not in: so the feebler were Laban&#8217;s, and the stronger Jacob&#8217;s. <verse number="43" style="v"/>And the man increased exceedingly, and had large flocks, and maid-servants and men-servants, and camels and asses.</para>
	<chapter number="31" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And he heard the words of Laban&#8217;s sons, saying, Jacob hath taken away all that was our father&#8217;s; and of that which was our father&#8217;s hath he gotten all this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wealth</char></char></note>glory. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Jacob beheld the countenance of Laban, and, behold, it was not toward him as beforetime. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Jehovah said unto Jacob, Return unto the land of thy fathers, and to thy kindred; and I will be with thee. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Jacob sent and called Rachel and Leah to the field unto his flock, <verse number="5" style="v"/>and said unto them, I see your father&#8217;s countenance, that it is not toward me as beforetime; but the God of my father hath been with me. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And ye know that with all my power I have served your father. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And your father hath deceived me, and changed my wages ten times; but God suffered him not to hurt me. <verse number="8" style="v"/>If he said thus, The speckled shall be thy wages; then all the flock bare speckled: and if he said thus, The ringstreaked shall be thy wages; then bare all the flock ringstreaked. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Thus God hath taken away the cattle of your father, and given them to me. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And it came to pass at the time that the flock conceive, that I lifted up mine eyes, and saw in a dream, and, behold, the he-goats which leaped upon the flock were ringstreaked, speckled, and grizzled. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the angel of God said unto me in the dream, Jacob: and I said, Here am I. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he said, Lift up now thine eyes, and see: all the he-goats which leap upon the flock are ringstreaked, speckled, and grizzled: for I have seen all that Laban doeth unto thee. <verse number="13" style="v"/>I am the God of Beth-el, where thou anointedst a pillar, where thou vowedst a vow unto me: now arise, get thee out from this land, and return unto the land of thy nativity. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Rachel and Leah answered and said unto him, Is there yet any portion or inheritance for us in our father&#8217;s house? <verse number="15" style="v"/>Are we not accounted by him as foreigners? for he hath sold us, and hath also quite devoured <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the price paid for us</char></char></note>our money. <verse number="16" style="v"/>For all the riches which God hath taken away from our father, that is ours and our children&#8217;s: now then, whatsoever God hath said unto thee, do.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>Then Jacob rose up, and set his sons and his wives upon the camels; <verse number="18" style="v"/>and he carried away all his cattle, and all his substance which he had gathered, the cattle of his getting, which he had gathered in Paddan-aram, to go to Isaac his father unto the land of Canaan. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Now Laban was gone to shear his sheep: and Rachel stole the teraphim that were her father&#8217;s. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Jacob <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">stole the heart of Laban the Aramean</char>.</char></note>stole away unawares to Laban the Syrian, in that he told him not that he fled. <verse number="21" style="v"/>So he fled with all that he had; and he rose up, and passed over <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is the Euphrates.</char></note>the River, and set his face toward the mountain of Gilead.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And it was told Laban on the third day that Jacob was fled. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he took his brethren with him, and pursued after him seven days&#8217; journey; and he overtook him in the mountain of Gilead. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And God came to Laban the Syrian in a dream of the night, and said unto him, Take heed to thyself that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And Laban came up with Jacob. Now Jacob had pitched his tent in the mountain: and Laban with his brethren encamped in the mountain of Gilead. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Laban said to Jacob, What hast thou done, that thou hast stolen away unawares to me, and carried away my daughters as captives of the sword? <verse number="27" style="v"/>Wherefore didst thou flee secretly, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">didst steal me</char>.</char></note>steal away from me, and didst not tell me, that I might have sent thee away with mirth and with songs, with tabret and with harp; <verse number="28" style="v"/>and didst not suffer me to kiss my sons and my daughters? now hast thou done foolishly. <verse number="29" style="v"/>It is in the power of my hand to do you hurt: but the God of your father spake unto me yesternight, saying, Take heed to thyself that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And now, <char style="add">though</char> thou wouldest needs be gone, because thou sore longedst after thy father&#8217;s house, <char style="add">yet</char> wherefore hast thou stolen my gods? <verse number="31" style="v"/>And Jacob answered and said to Laban, Because I was afraid: for I said, Lest thou shouldest take thy daughters from me by force. <verse number="32" style="v"/>With whomsoever thou findest thy gods, he shall not live: before our brethren discern thou what is thine with me, and take it to thee. For Jacob knew not that Rachel had stolen them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v"/>And Laban went into Jacob&#8217;s tent, and into Leah&#8217;s tent, and into the tent of the two maid-servants; but he found them not. And he went out of Leah&#8217;s tent, and entered into Rachel&#8217;s tent. <verse number="34" style="v"/>Now Rachel had taken the teraphim, and put them in the camel&#8217;s saddle, and sat upon them. And Laban felt about all the tent, but found them not. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And she said to her father, Let not my lord be angry that I cannot rise up before thee; for the manner of women is upon me. And he searched, but found not the teraphim.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v"/>And Jacob was wroth, and chode with Laban: and Jacob answered and said to Laban, What is my trespass? what is my sin, that thou hast hotly pursued after me? <verse number="37" style="v"/>Whereas thou hast felt about all my stuff, what hast thou found of all thy household stuff? Set it here before my brethren and thy brethren, that they may judge betwixt us two. <verse number="38" style="v"/>These twenty years have I been with thee; thy ewes and thy she-goats have not cast their young, and the rams of thy flocks have I not eaten. <verse number="39" style="v"/>That which was torn of beasts I brought not unto thee; I bare the loss of it; of my hand didst thou require it, whether stolen by day or stolen by night. <verse number="40" style="v"/>Thus I was; in the day the drought consumed me, and the frost by night; and my sleep fled from mine eyes. <verse number="41" style="v"/>These twenty years have I been in thy house; I served thee fourteen years for thy two daughters, and six years for thy flock: and thou hast changed my wages ten times. <verse number="42" style="v"/>Except the God of my father, the God of Abraham, and the Fear of Isaac, had been with me, surely now hadst thou sent me away empty. God hath seen mine affliction and the labor of my hands, and rebuked thee yesternight.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v"/>And Laban answered and said unto Jacob, The daughters are my daughters, and the children are my children, and the flocks are my flocks, and all that thou seest is mine: and what can I do this day unto these my daughters, or unto their children whom they have borne? <verse number="44" style="v"/>And now come, let us make a covenant, I and thou; and let it be for a witness between me and thee. <verse number="45" style="v"/>And Jacob took a stone, and set it up for a pillar. <verse number="46" style="v"/>And Jacob said unto his brethren, Gather stones; and they took stones, and made a heap: and they did eat there by the heap. <verse number="47" style="v"/>And Laban called it <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The heap of witness</char>, in Aramaic.</char></note>Jegar-saha-dutha: but Jacob called it <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The heap of witness</char>, in Hebrew.</char></note>Galeed. <verse number="48" style="v"/>And Laban said, This heap is witness between me and thee this day. Therefore was the name of it called Galeed: <verse number="49" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The watch tower</char>.</char></note>Mizpah, for he said, Jehovah watch between me and thee, when we are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">hidden</char>.</char></note>absent one from another. <verse number="50" style="v"/>If thou shalt afflict my daughters, and if thou shalt take wives besides my daughters, no man is with us; see, God is witness betwixt me and thee. <verse number="51" style="v"/>And Laban said to Jacob, Behold this heap, and behold the pillar, which I have set betwixt me and thee. <verse number="52" style="v"/>This heap be witness, and the pillar be witness, that I will not pass over this heap to thee, and that thou shalt not pass over this heap and this pillar unto me, for harm. <verse number="53" style="v"/>The God of Abraham, and the God of Nahor, the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gods</char></char></note>God of their father, judge betwixt us. And Jacob sware by the Fear of his father Isaac. <verse number="54" style="v"/>And Jacob offered a sacrifice in the mountain, and called his brethren to eat bread: and they did eat bread, and tarried all night in the mountain. <verse number="55" style="v"/>And early in the morning Laban rose up, and kissed his sons and his daughters, and blessed them: and Laban departed, and returned unto his place.</para>
	<chapter number="32" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Jacob went on his way, and the angels of God met him. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Jacob said when he saw them, This is God&#8217;s host: and he called the name of that place <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Two hosts</char>, or, <char style="it">Companies</char>.</char></note>Mahanaim.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>And Jacob sent messengers before him to Esau his brother unto the land of Seir, the field of Edom. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And he commanded them, saying, Thus shall ye say unto my lord Esau: Thus saith thy servant Jacob, I have sojourned with Laban, and stayed until now: <verse number="5" style="v"/>and I have oxen, and asses, <char style="add">and</char> flocks, and men-servants, and maid-servants: and I have sent to tell my lord, that I may find favor in thy sight. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And the messengers returned to Jacob, saying, We came to thy brother Esau, and moreover he cometh to meet thee, and four hundred men with him. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Then Jacob was greatly afraid and was distressed: and he divided the people that were with him, and the flocks, and the herds, and the camels, into two companies; <verse number="8" style="v"/>and he said, If Esau come to the one company, and smite it, then the company which is left shall escape. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Jacob said, O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Isaac, O Jehovah, who saidst unto me, Return unto thy country, and to thy kindred, and I will do thee good: <verse number="10" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">I am less than all etc.</char></char></note>I am not worthy of the least of all the lovingkindnesses, and of all the truth, which thou hast showed unto thy servant; for with my staff I passed over this Jordan; and now I am become two companies. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Deliver me, I pray thee, from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau: for I fear him, lest he come and smite me, the mother with the children. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And thou saidst, I will surely do thee good, and make thy seed as the sand of the sea, which cannot be numbered for multitude.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And he lodged there that night, and took of that which he had with him a present for Esau his brother: <verse number="14" style="v"/>two hundred she-goats and twenty he-goats, two hundred ewes and twenty rams, <verse number="15" style="v"/>thirty milch camels and their colts, forty cows and ten bulls, twenty she-asses and ten foals. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he delivered them into the hand of his servants, every drove by itself, and said unto his servants, Pass over before me, and put a space betwixt drove and drove. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And he commanded the foremost, saying, When Esau my brother meeteth thee, and asketh thee, saying, Whose art thou? and whither goest thou? and whose are these before thee? <verse number="18" style="v"/>then thou shalt say, <char style="add">They are</char> thy servant Jacob&#8217;s; it is a present sent unto my lord Esau: and, behold, he also is behind us. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And he commanded also the second, and the third, and all that followed the droves, saying, On this manner shall ye speak unto Esau, when ye find him; <verse number="20" style="v"/>and ye shall say, Moreover, behold, thy servant Jacob is behind us. For he said, I will appease him with the present that goeth before me, and afterward I will see his face; peradventure he will accept me. <verse number="21" style="v"/>So the present passed over before him: and he himself lodged that night in the company.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And he rose up that night, and took his two wives, and his two handmaids, and his eleven children, and passed over the ford of the Jabbok. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he took them, and sent them over the stream, and sent over that which he had. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Jacob was left alone; and there wrestled a man with him until the breaking of the day. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And when he saw that he prevailed not against him, he touched the hollow of his thigh; and the hollow of Jacob&#8217;s thigh was strained, as he wrestled with him. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And he said, Let me go, for the day breaketh. And he said, I will not let thee go, except thou bless me. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And he said unto him, What is thy name? And he said, Jacob. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And he said, Thy name shall be called no more Jacob, but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">He who striveth with God</char>, or, <char style="it">God striveth</char>.</char></note>Israel: for thou hast <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">had power with</char></char></note>striven with God and with men, and hast prevailed. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Jacob asked him, and said, Tell me, I pray thee, thy name. And he said, Wherefore is it that thou dost ask after my name? And he blessed him there. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And Jacob called the name of the place <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The face of God</char>.</char></note>Peniel: for, <char style="add">said he</char>, I have seen God face to face, and my life is preserved. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And the sun rose upon him as he passed over Penuel, and he limped upon his thigh. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Therefore the children of Israel eat not the sinew of the hip which is upon the hollow of the thigh, unto this day: because he touched the hollow of Jacob&#8217;s thigh in the sinew of the hip.</para>
	<chapter number="33" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Jacob lifted up his eyes, and looked, and, behold, Esau was coming, and with him four hundred men. And he divided the children unto Leah, and unto Rachel, and unto the two handmaids. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he put the handmaids and their children foremost, and Leah and her children after, and Rachel and Joseph hindermost. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he himself passed over before them, and bowed himself to the ground seven times, until he came near to his brother. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Esau ran to meet him, and embraced him, and fell on his neck, and kissed him: and they wept. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And he lifted up his eyes, and saw the women and the children; and said, Who are these with thee? And he said, The children whom God hath graciously given thy servant. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Then the handmaids came near, they and their children, and they bowed themselves. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Leah also and her children came near, and bowed themselves: and after came Joseph near and Rachel, and they bowed themselves. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he said, What meanest thou by all this company which I met? And he said, To find favor in the sight of my lord. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Esau said, I have enough, my brother; let that which thou hast be thine. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Jacob said, Nay, I pray thee, if now I have found favor in thy sight, then receive my present at my hand; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for therefore have I seen</char></char></note>forasmuch as I have seen thy face, as one seeth the face of God, and thou wast pleased with me. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Take, I pray thee, my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">blessing</char>.</char></note>gift that is brought to thee; because God hath dealt graciously with me, and because I have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">all</char>.</char></note>enough. And he urged him, and he took it. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he said, Let us take our journey, and let us go, and I will go before thee. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And he said unto him, My lord knoweth that the children are tender, and that the flocks and herds with me have their young: and if they overdrive them one day, all the flocks will die. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Let my lord, I pray thee, pass over before his servant: and I will lead on gently, according to the pace of the cattle that are before me and according to the pace of the children, until I come unto my lord unto Seir. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Esau said, Let me now leave with thee some of the folk that are with me. And he said, What needeth it? let me find favor in the sight of my lord. <verse number="16" style="v"/>So Esau returned that day on his way unto Seir. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Jacob journeyed to Succoth, and built him a house, and made booths for his cattle: therefore the name of the place is called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Booths</char>.</char></note>Succoth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Jacob came <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to Shalem, a city</char></char></note>in peace to the city of Shechem, which is in the land of Canaan, when he came from Paddan-aram; and encamped before the city. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And he bought the parcel of ground, where he had spread his tent, at the hand of the children of Hamor, Shechem&#8217;s father, for a hundred <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">kesitah</char>.</char></note>pieces of money. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And he erected there an altar, and called it <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">God, the God of Israel</char>.</char></note>El-Elohe-Israel.</para>
	<chapter number="34" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Dinah the daughter of Leah, whom she bare unto Jacob, went out to see the daughters of the land. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Shechem the son of Hamor the Hivite, the prince of the land, saw her; and he took her, and lay with her, and humbled her. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And his soul clave unto Dinah the daughter of Jacob, and he loved the damsel, and spake <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">to the heart of the damsel</char>.</char></note>kindly unto the damsel. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Shechem spake unto his father Hamor, saying, Get me this damsel to wife. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Now Jacob heard that he had defiled Dinah his daughter; and his sons were with his cattle in the field: and Jacob held his peace until they came. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Hamor the father of Shechem went out unto Jacob to commune with him. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the sons of Jacob came in from the field when they heard it: and the men were grieved, and they were very wroth, because he had wrought folly in Israel in lying with Jacob&#8217;s daughter; which thing ought not to be done. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Hamor communed with them, saying, The soul of my son Shechem longeth for your daughter: I pray you, give her unto him to wife. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And make ye marriages with us; give your daughters unto us, and take our daughters unto you. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And ye shall dwell with us: and the land shall be before you; dwell and trade ye therein, and get you possessions therein. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Shechem said unto her father and unto her brethren, Let me find favor in your eyes, and what ye shall say unto me I will give. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Ask me never so much dowry and gift, and I will give according as ye shall say unto me: but give me the damsel to wife. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And the sons of Jacob answered Shechem and Hamor his father with guile, and spake, because he had defiled Dinah their sister, <verse number="14" style="v"/>and said unto them, We cannot do this thing, to give our sister to one that is uncircumcised; for that were a reproach unto us. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Only on this condition will we consent unto you: if ye will be as we are, that every male of you be circumcised; <verse number="16" style="v"/>then will we give our daughters unto you, and we will take your daughters to us, and we will dwell with you, and we will become one people. <verse number="17" style="v"/>But if ye will not hearken unto us, to be circumcised; then will we take our daughter, and we will be gone.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And their words pleased Hamor, and Shechem Hamor&#8217;s son. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the young man deferred not to do the thing, because he had delight in Jacob&#8217;s daughter: and he was honored above all the house of his father. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Hamor and Shechem his son came unto the gate of their city, and communed with the men of their city, saying, <verse number="21" style="v"/>These men are peaceable with us; therefore let them dwell in the land, and trade therein; for, behold, the land is large enough for them; let us take their daughters to us for wives, and let us give them our daughters. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Only on this condition will the men consent unto us to dwell with us, to become one people, if every male among us be circumcised, as they are circumcised. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Shall not their cattle and their substance and all their beasts be ours? only let us consent unto them, and they will dwell with us. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And unto Hamor and unto Shechem his son hearkened all that went out of the gate of his city; and every male was circumcised, all that went out of the gate of his city. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And it came to pass on the third day, when they were sore, that two of the sons of Jacob, Simeon and Levi, Dinah&#8217;s brethren, took each man his sword, and came upon the city <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">boldly</char></char></note>unawares, and slew all the males. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And they slew Hamor and Shechem his son with the edge of the sword, and took Dinah out of Shechem&#8217;s house, and went forth. <verse number="27" style="v"/>The sons of Jacob came upon the slain, and plundered the city, because they had defiled their sister. <verse number="28" style="v"/>They took their flocks and their herds and their asses, and that which was in the city, and that which was in the field; <verse number="29" style="v"/>and all their wealth, and all their little ones and their wives, took they captive and made a prey, even all that was in the house. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And Jacob said to Simeon and Levi, Ye have troubled me, to make me odious to the inhabitants of the land, among the Canaanites and the Perizzites: and, I being few in number, they will gather themselves together against me and smite me; and I shall be destroyed, I and my house. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And they said, Should he deal with our sister as with a harlot?</para>
	<chapter number="35" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And God said unto Jacob, Arise, go up to Beth-el, and dwell there: and make there an altar unto God, who appeared unto thee when thou fleddest from the face of Esau thy brother. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Then Jacob said unto his household, and to all that were with him, Put away the foreign gods that are among you, and purify yourselves, and change your garments: <verse number="3" style="v"/>and let us arise, and go up to Beth-el; and I will make there an altar unto God, who answered me in the day of my distress, and was with me in the way which I went. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And they gave unto Jacob all the foreign gods which were in their hand, and the rings which were in their ears; and Jacob hid them under the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">terebinth</char></char></note>oak which was by Shechem. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And they journeyed: and a terror of God was upon the cities that were round about them, and they did not pursue after the sons of Jacob. <verse number="6" style="v"/>So Jacob came to Luz, which is in the land of Canaan (the same is Beth-el), he and all the people that were with him. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he built there an altar, and called the place <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The God of Beth-el</char>.</char></note>El-beth-el; because there God was revealed unto him, when he fled from the face of his brother. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Deborah Rebekah&#8217;s nurse died, and she was buried below Beth-el under the oak: and the name of it was called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The oak of weeping</char>.</char></note>Allon-bacuth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And God appeared unto Jacob again, when he came from Paddan-aram, and blessed him. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And God said unto him, Thy name is Jacob: thy name shall not be called any more Jacob, but Israel shall be thy name: and he called his name Israel. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And God said unto him, I am <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El Shaddai</char>.</char></note>God Almighty: be fruitful and multiply; a nation and a company of nations shall be of thee, and kings shall come out of thy loins; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and the land which I gave unto Abraham and Isaac, to thee I will give it, and to thy seed after thee will I give the land. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And God went up from him in the place where he spake with him. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Jacob set up a pillar in the place where he spake with him, a pillar of stone: and he poured out a drink-offering thereon, and poured oil thereon. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Jacob called the name of the place where God spake with him, Beth-el.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And they journeyed from Beth-el; and there was still some distance to come to Ephrath: and Rachel travailed, and she had hard labor. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when she was in hard labor, that the midwife said unto her, Fear not; for now thou shalt have another son. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as her soul was departing (for she died), that she called his name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The son of my sorrow</char>.</char></note>Ben-oni: but his father called him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The son of the right hand</char>.</char></note>Benjamin. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Rachel died, and was buried in the way to Ephrath (the same is Beth-lehem). <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Jacob set up a pillar upon her grave: the same is the Pillar of Rachel&#8217;s grave unto this day. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Israel journeyed, and spread his tent beyond the tower of Eder. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And it came to pass, while Israel dwelt in that land, that Reuben went and lay with Bilhah his father&#8217;s concubine: and Israel heard of it.</para>
	<para style="p">Now the sons of Jacob were twelve: <verse number="23" style="v"/>the sons of Leah: Reuben, Jacob&#8217;s first-born, and Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Zebulun; <verse number="24" style="v"/>the sons of Rachel: Joseph and Benjamin; <verse number="25" style="v"/>and the sons of Bilhah, Rachel&#8217;s handmaid: Dan and Naphtali; <verse number="26" style="v"/>and the sons of Zilpah, Leah&#8217;s handmaid: Gad and Asher: these are the sons of Jacob, that were born to him in Paddan-aram. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Jacob came unto Isaac his father to Mamre, to Kiriath-arba (the same is Hebron), where Abraham and Isaac sojourned.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And the days of Isaac were a hundred and fourscore years. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Isaac gave up the ghost, and died, and was gathered unto his people, old and full of days: and Esau and Jacob his sons buried him.</para>
	<chapter number="36" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now these are the generations of Esau (the same is Edom). <verse number="2" style="v"/>Esau took his wives of the daughters of Canaan: Adah the daughter of Elon the Hittite, and Oholibamah the daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon the Hivite, <verse number="3" style="v"/>and Basemath Ishmael&#8217;s daughter, sister of Nebaioth. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Adah bare to Esau Eliphaz; and Basemath bare Reuel; <verse number="5" style="v"/>and Oholibamah bare Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah: these are the sons of Esau, that were born unto him in the land of Canaan. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Esau took his wives, and his sons, and his daughters, and all the souls of his house, and his cattle, and all his beasts, and all his possessions, which he had gathered in the land of Canaan; and went into a land away from his brother Jacob. <verse number="7" style="v"/>For their substance was too great for them to dwell together; and the land of their sojournings could not bear them because of their cattle. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Esau dwelt in mount Seir: Esau is Edom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And these are the generations of Esau the father of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Edom</char>.</char></note>the Edomites in mount Seir: <verse number="10" style="v"/>these are the names of Esau&#8217;s sons: Eliphaz the son of Adah the wife of Esau, Reuel the son of Basemath the wife of Esau. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the sons of Eliphaz were Teman, Omar, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:36">1 Chr. 1:36</ref>, <char style="it">Zephi</char>.</char></note>Zepho, and Gatam, and Kenaz. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Timna was concubine to Eliphaz Esau&#8217;s son; and she bare to Eliphaz Amalek: these are the sons of Adah, Esau&#8217;s wife. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And these are the sons of Reuel: Nahath, and Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah: these were the sons of Basemath, Esau&#8217;s wife. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And these were the sons of Oholibamah the daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon, Esau&#8217;s wife: and she bare to Esau Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>These are the chiefs of the sons of Esau: the sons of Eliphaz the first-born of Esau: chief Teman, chief Omar, chief Zepho, chief Kenaz, <verse number="16" style="v"/>chief Korah, chief Gatam, chief Amalek: these are the chiefs that came of Eliphaz in the land of Edom; these are the sons of Adah. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And these are the sons of Reuel, Esau&#8217;s son: chief Nahath, chief Zerah, chief Shammah, chief Mizzah: these are the chiefs that came of Reuel in the land of Edom; these are the sons of Basemath, Esau&#8217;s wife. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And these are the sons of Oholibamah, Esau&#8217;s wife: chief Jeush, chief Jalam, chief Korah: these are the chiefs that came of Oholibamah the daughter of Anah, Esau&#8217;s wife. <verse number="19" style="v"/>These are the sons of Esau, and these are their chiefs: the same is Edom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>These are the sons of Seir the Horite, the inhabitants of the land: Lotan and Shobal and Zibeon and Anah, <verse number="21" style="v"/>and Dishon and Ezer and Dishan: these are the chiefs that came of the Horites, the children of Seir in the land of Edom. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the children of Lotan were Hori and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:39">1 Chr. 1:39</ref>, <char style="it">Homam</char>.</char></note>Heman; and Lotan&#8217;s sister was Timna. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And these are the children of Shobal: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:40">1 Chr. 1:40</ref>, <char style="it">Alian</char>.</char></note>Alvan and Manahath and Ebal, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:40">1 Chr. 1:40</ref>, <char style="it">Shephi</char>.</char></note>Shepho and Onam. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And these are the children of Zibeon: Aiah and Anah; this is Anah who found the hot springs in the wilderness, as he fed the asses of Zibeon his father. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And these are the children of Anah: Dishon and Oholibamah the daughter of Anah. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And these are the children of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Dishan</char>.</char></note>Dishon: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:41">1 Chr. 1:41</ref>, <char style="it">Hamran</char>.</char></note>Hemdan and Eshban and Ithran and Cheran. <verse number="27" style="v"/>These are the children of Ezer: Bilhan and Zaavan and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:42">1 Chr. 1:42</ref>, <char style="it">Jaakan</char>.</char></note>Akan. <verse number="28" style="v"/>These are the children of Dishan: Uz and Aran. <verse number="29" style="v"/>These are the chiefs that came of the Horites: chief Lotan, chief Shobal, chief Zibeon, chief Anah, <verse number="30" style="v"/>chief Dishon, chief Ezer, chief Dishan: these are the chiefs that came of the Horites, according to their chiefs in the land of Seir.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>And these are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom, before there reigned any king over the children of Israel. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And Bela the son of Beor reigned in Edom; and the name of his city was Dinhabah. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And Bela died, and Jobab the son of Zerah of Bozrah reigned in his stead. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And Jobab died, and Husham of the land of the Temanites reigned in his stead. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And Husham died, and Hadad the son of Bedad, who smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Avith. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And Hadad died, and Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And Samlah died, and Shaul of Rehoboth by the River reigned in his stead. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And Shaul died, and Baal-hanan the son of Achbor reigned in his stead. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And Baal-hanan the son of Achbor died, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:50">1 Chr. 1:50</ref>, <char style="it">Hadad</char>.</char></note>Hadar reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:50">1 Chr. 1:50</ref>, <char style="it">Pai</char>.</char></note>Pau; and his wife&#8217;s name was Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Me-zahab.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v"/>And these are the names of the chiefs that came of Esau, according to their families, after their places, by their names: chief Timna, chief <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 1:51">1 Chr. 1:51</ref>, <char style="it">Aliah</char>.</char></note>Alvah, chief Jetheth, <verse number="41" style="v"/>chief Oholibamah, chief Elah, chief Pinon, <verse number="42" style="v"/>chief Kenaz, chief Teman, chief Mibzar, <verse number="43" style="v"/>chief Magdiel, chief Iram: these are the chiefs of Edom, according to their habitations in the land of their possession. This is Esau, the father of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Edom</char>.</char></note>the Edomites.</para>
	<chapter number="37" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Jacob dwelt in the land of his father&#8217;s sojournings, in the land of Canaan. <verse number="2" style="v"/>These are the generations of Jacob. Joseph, being seventeen years old, was feeding the flock with his brethren; and he was a lad with the sons of Bilhah, and with the sons of Zilpah, his father&#8217;s wives: and Joseph brought the evil report of them unto their father. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his children, because he was the son of his old age: and he made him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a long garment with sleeves</char></char></note>a coat of many colors. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And his brethren saw that their father loved him more than all his brethren; and they hated him, and could not speak peaceably unto him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>And Joseph dreamed a dream, and he told it to his brethren: and they hated him yet the more. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he said unto them, Hear, I pray you, this dream which I have dreamed: <verse number="7" style="v"/>for, behold, we were binding sheaves in the field, and, lo, my sheaf arose, and also stood upright; and, behold, your sheaves came round about, and made obeisance to my sheaf. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And his brethren said to him, Shalt thou indeed reign over us? or shalt thou indeed have dominion over us? And they hated him yet the more for his dreams, and for his words. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And he dreamed yet another dream, and told it to his brethren, and said, Behold, I have dreamed yet a dream; and, behold, the sun and the moon and eleven stars made obeisance to me. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And he told it to his father, and to his brethren; and his father rebuked him, and said unto him, What is this dream that thou hast dreamed? Shall I and thy mother and thy brethren indeed come to bow down ourselves to thee to the earth? <verse number="11" style="v"/>And his brethren envied him; but his father kept the saying in mind.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And his brethren went to feed their father&#8217;s flock in Shechem. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Israel said unto Joseph, Are not thy brethren feeding the flock in Shechem? come, and I will send thee unto them. And he said to him, Here am I. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And he said to him, Go now, see whether it is well with thy brethren, and well with the flock; and bring me word again. So he sent him out of the vale of Hebron, and he came to Shechem. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And a certain man found him, and, behold, he was wandering in the field: and the man asked him, saying, What seekest thou? <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he said, I am seeking my brethren: tell me, I pray thee, where they are feeding <char style="add">the flock</char>. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the man said, They are departed hence; for I heard them say, Let us go to Dothan. And Joseph went after his brethren, and found them in Dothan.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And they saw him afar off, and before he came near unto them, they conspired against him to slay him. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And they said one to another, Behold, this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">master of dreams</char>.</char></note>dreamer cometh. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Come now therefore, and let us slay him, and cast him into one of the pits, and we will say, An evil beast hath devoured him: and we shall see what will become of his dreams. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Reuben heard it, and delivered him out of their hand, and said, Let us not take his life. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Reuben said unto them, Shed no blood; cast him into this pit that is in the wilderness, but lay no hand upon him: that he might deliver him out of their hand, to restore him to his father. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when Joseph was come unto his brethren, that they stripped Joseph of his coat, the coat of many colors that was on him; <verse number="24" style="v"/>and they took him, and cast him into the pit: and the pit was empty, there was no water in it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And they sat down to eat bread: and they lifted up their eyes and looked, and, behold, a caravan of Ishmaelites was coming from Gilead, with their camels bearing <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gum tragacanth</char>. Or, <char style="it">storax</char></char></note>spicery and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">mastic</char></char></note>balm and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">ladanum</char></char></note>myrrh, going to carry it down to Egypt. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Judah said unto his brethren, What profit is it if we slay our brother and conceal his blood? <verse number="27" style="v"/>Come, and let us sell him to the Ishmaelites, and let not our hand be upon him; for he is our brother, our flesh. And his brethren hearkened unto him. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And there passed by Midianites, merchantmen; and they drew and lifted up Joseph out of the pit, and sold Joseph to the Ishmaelites for twenty pieces of silver. And they brought Joseph into Egypt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v"/>And Reuben returned unto the pit; and, behold, Joseph was not in the pit; and he rent his clothes. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And he returned unto his brethren, and said, The child is not; and I, whither shall I go? <verse number="31" style="v"/>And they took Joseph&#8217;s coat, and killed a he-goat, and dipped the coat in the blood; <verse number="32" style="v"/>and they sent the coat of many colors, and they brought it to their father, and said, This have we found: know now whether it is thy son&#8217;s coat or not. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And he knew it, and said, It is my son&#8217;s coat; an evil beast hath devoured him; Joseph is without doubt torn in pieces. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And Jacob rent his garments, and put sackcloth upon his loins, and mourned for his son many days. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And all his sons and all his daughters rose up to comfort him; but he refused to be comforted; and he said, For I will go down to Sheol to my son mourning. And his father wept for him. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Medanites</char>.</char></note>Midianites sold him into Egypt unto Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh&#8217;s, the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">chief of the executioners</char>.</char></note>captain of the guard.</para>
	<chapter number="38" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass at that time, that Judah went down from his brethren, and turned in to a certain Adullamite, whose name was Hirah. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Judah saw there a daughter of a certain Canaanite whose name was Shua; and he took her, and went in unto her. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And she conceived, and bare a son; and he called his name Er. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And she conceived again, and bare a son; and she called his name Onan. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And she yet again bare a son, and called his name Shelah: and he was at Chezib, when she bare him. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Judah took a wife for Er his first-born, and her name was Tamar. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Er, Judah&#8217;s first-born, was wicked in the sight of Jehovah; and Jehovah slew him. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Judah said unto Onan, Go in unto thy brother&#8217;s wife, and perform the duty of a husband&#8217;s brother unto her, and raise up seed to thy brother. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Onan knew that the seed would not be his; and it came to pass, when he went in unto his brother&#8217;s wife, that he spilled it on the ground, lest he should give seed to his brother. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And the thing which he did was evil in the sight of Jehovah: and he slew him also. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Then said Judah to Tamar his daughter-in-law, Remain a widow in thy father&#8217;s house, till Shelah my son be grown up; for he said, Lest he also die, like his brethren. And Tamar went and dwelt in her father&#8217;s house.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And in process of time Shua&#8217;s daughter, the wife of Judah, died; and Judah was comforted, and went up unto his sheep-shearers to Timnah, he and his friend Hirah the Adullamite. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And it was told Tamar, saying, Behold, thy father-in-law goeth up to Timnah to shear his sheep. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And she put off from her the garments of her widowhood, and covered herself with her veil, and wrapped herself, and sat in the gate of Enaim, which is by the way to Timnah; for she saw that Shelah was grown up, and she was not given unto him to wife. <verse number="15" style="v"/>When Judah saw her, he thought her to be a harlot; for she had covered her face. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he turned unto her by the way, and said, Come, I pray thee, let me come in unto thee: for he knew not that she was his daughter-in-law. And she said, What wilt thou give me, that thou mayest come in unto me? <verse number="17" style="v"/>And he said, I will send thee a kid of the goats from the flock. And she said, Wilt thou give me a pledge, till thou send it? <verse number="18" style="v"/>And he said, What pledge shall I give thee? And she said, Thy signet and thy cord, and thy staff that is in thy hand. And he gave them to her, and came in unto her, and she conceived by him. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And she arose, and went away, and put off her veil from her, and put on the garments of her widowhood. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Judah sent the kid of the goats by the hand of his friend the Adullamite, to receive the pledge from the woman&#8217;s hand: but he found her not. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Then he asked the men of her place, saying, Where is the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">kedeshah</char>, that is, a woman dedicated to impure heathen worship. See <ref loc="DEU 23:17">Dt. 23:17</ref>; <ref loc="HOS 4:14">Hos. 4:14</ref>.</char></note>prostitute, that was at Enaim by the wayside? And they said, There hath been no prostitute here. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And he returned to Judah, and said, I have not found her; and also the men of the place said, There hath been no prostitute here. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Judah said, Let her take it to her, lest we be put to shame: behold, I sent this kid, and thou hast not found her.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>And it came to pass about three months after, that it was told Judah, saying, Tamar thy daughter-in-law hath played the harlot; and moreover, behold, she is with child by whoredom. And Judah said, Bring her forth, and let her be burnt. <verse number="25" style="v"/>When she was brought forth, she sent to her father-in-law, saying, By the man, whose these are, am I with child: and she said, Discern, I pray thee, whose are these, the signet, and the cords, and the staff. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Judah acknowledged them, and said, She is more righteous than I, forasmuch as I gave her not to Shelah my son. And he knew her again no more. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And it came to pass in the time of her travail, that, behold, twins were in her womb. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when she travailed, that one put out a hand: and the midwife took and bound upon his hand a scarlet thread, saying, This came out first. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as he drew back his hand, that, behold, his brother came out: and she said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">How hast thou made a breach! a breach be upon thee!</char></char></note>Wherefore hast thou made a breach for thyself? therefore his name was called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">A breach</char>.</char></note>Perez. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And afterward came out his brother, that had the scarlet thread upon his hand: and his name was called Zerah.</para>
	<chapter number="39" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Joseph was brought down to Egypt; and Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh&#8217;s, the captain of the guard, an Egyptian, bought him of the hand of the Ishmaelites, that had brought him down thither. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Jehovah was with Joseph, and he was a prosperous man; and he was in the house of his master the Egyptian. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And his master saw that Jehovah was with him, and that Jehovah made all that he did to prosper in his hand. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Joseph found favor in his sight, and he ministered unto him: and he made him overseer over his house, and all that he had he put into his hand. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And it came to pass from the time that he made him overseer in his house, and over all that he had, that Jehovah blessed the Egyptian&#8217;s house for Joseph&#8217;s sake; and the blessing of Jehovah was upon all that he had, in the house and in the field. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he left all that he had in Joseph&#8217;s hand; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with him he knew not</char></char></note>he knew not aught <char style="add">that was</char> with him, save the bread which he did eat. And Joseph was comely, and well-favored. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And it came to pass after these things, that his master&#8217;s wife cast her eyes upon Joseph; and she said, Lie with me. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But he refused, and said unto his master&#8217;s wife, Behold, my master <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">knoweth not with me what is etc.</char></char></note>knoweth not what is with me in the house, and he hath put all that he hath into my hand: <verse number="9" style="v"/>he is not greater in this house than I; neither hath he kept back anything from me but thee, because thou art his wife: how then can I do this great wickedness, and sin against God? <verse number="10" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as she spake to Joseph day by day, that he hearkened not unto her, to lie by her, <char style="add">or</char> to be with her. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And it came to pass about this time, that he went into the house to do his work; and there was none of the men of the house there within. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And she caught him by his garment, saying, Lie with me: and he left his garment in her hand, and fled, and got him out. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when she saw that he had left his garment in her hand, and was fled forth, <verse number="14" style="v"/>that she called unto the men of her house, and spake unto them, saying, See, he hath brought in a Hebrew unto us to mock us: he came in unto me to lie with me, and I cried with a loud voice: <verse number="15" style="v"/>and it came to pass, when he heard that I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment by me, and fled, and got him out. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And she laid up his garment by her, until his master came home. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And she spake unto him according to these words, saying, The Hebrew servant, whom thou hast brought unto us, came in unto me to mock me: <verse number="18" style="v"/>and it came to pass, as I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment by me, and fled out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when his master heard the words of his wife, which she spake unto him, saying, After this manner did thy servant to me; that his wrath was kindled. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Joseph&#8217;s master took him, and put him into the prison, the place where the king&#8217;s prisoners were bound: and he was there in the prison. <verse number="21" style="v"/>But Jehovah was with Joseph, and showed kindness unto him, and gave him favor in the sight of the keeper of the prison. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the keeper of the prison committed to Joseph&#8217;s hand all the prisoners that were in the prison; and whatsoever they did there, he was the doer of it. <verse number="23" style="v"/>The keeper of the prison looked not to anything that was under his hand, because Jehovah was with him; and that which he did, Jehovah made it to prosper.</para>
	<chapter number="40" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass after these things, that the butler of the king of Egypt and his baker offended their lord the king of Egypt. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Pharaoh was wroth against his two officers, against the chief of the butlers, and against the chief of the bakers. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he put them in ward in the house of the captain of the guard, into the prison, the place where Joseph was bound. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the captain of the guard charged Joseph with them, and he ministered unto them: and they continued a season in ward. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And they dreamed a dream both of them, each man his dream, in one night, each man according to the interpretation of his dream, the butler and the baker of the king of Egypt, who were bound in the prison. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Joseph came in unto them in the morning, and saw them, and, behold, they were sad. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he asked Pharaoh&#8217;s officers that were with him in ward in his master&#8217;s house, saying, Wherefore look ye so sad to-day? <verse number="8" style="v"/>And they said unto him, We have dreamed a dream, and there is none that can interpret it. And Joseph said unto them, Do not interpretations belong to God? tell it me, I pray you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And the chief butler told his dream to Joseph, and said to him, In my dream, behold, a vine was before me; <verse number="10" style="v"/>and in the vine were three branches: and it was as though it budded, <char style="add">and</char> its blossoms shot forth; <char style="add">and</char> the clusters thereof brought forth ripe grapes: <verse number="11" style="v"/>and Pharaoh&#8217;s cup was in my hand; and I took the grapes, and pressed them into Pharaoh&#8217;s cup, and I gave the cup into Pharaoh&#8217;s hand. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto him, This is the interpretation of it: the three branches are three days; <verse number="13" style="v"/>within yet three days shall Pharaoh lift up thy head, and restore thee unto thine office: and thou shalt give Pharaoh&#8217;s cup into his hand, after the former manner when thou wast his butler. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But have me in thy remembrance when it shall be well with thee, and show kindness, I pray thee, unto me, and make mention of me unto Pharaoh, and bring me out of this house: <verse number="15" style="v"/>for indeed I was stolen away out of the land of the Hebrews: and here also have I done nothing that they should put me into the dungeon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>When the chief baker saw that the interpretation was good, he said unto Joseph, I also was in my dream, and, behold, three baskets of white bread were on my head: <verse number="17" style="v"/>and in the uppermost basket there was of all manner of baked food for Pharaoh; and the birds did eat them out of the basket upon my head. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Joseph answered and said, This is the interpretation thereof: the three baskets are three days; <verse number="19" style="v"/>within yet three days shall Pharaoh lift up thy head from off thee, and shall hang thee on a tree; and the birds shall eat thy flesh from off thee. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And it came to pass the third day, which was Pharaoh&#8217;s birthday, that he made a feast unto all his servants: and he lifted up the head of the chief butler and the head of the chief baker among his servants. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And he restored the chief butler unto his butlership again; and he gave the cup into Pharaoh&#8217;s hand: <verse number="22" style="v"/>but he hanged the chief baker: as Joseph had interpreted to them. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Yet did not the chief butler remember Joseph, but forgat him.</para>
	<chapter number="41" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass at the end of two full years, that Pharaoh dreamed: and, behold, he stood by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Yeor</char>, that is, the Nile.</char></note>river. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And, behold, there came up out of the river seven kine, well-favored and fat-fleshed; and they fed in the reed-grass. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And, behold, seven other kine came up after them out of the river, ill-favored and lean-fleshed, and stood by the other kine upon the brink of the river. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the ill-favored and lean-fleshed kine did eat up the seven well-favored and fat kine. So Pharaoh awoke. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And he slept and dreamed a second time: and, behold, seven ears of grain came up upon one stalk, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">fat</char>.</char></note>rank and good. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And, behold, seven ears, thin and blasted with the east wind, sprung up after them. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the thin ears swallowed up the seven rank and full ears. And Pharaoh awoke, and, behold, it was a dream. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And it came to pass in the morning that his spirit was troubled; and he sent and called for all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sacred scribes</char></char></note>magicians of Egypt, and all the wise men thereof: and Pharaoh told them his dream; but there was none that could interpret them unto Pharaoh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>Then spake the chief butler unto Pharaoh, saying, I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">will make mention of</char></char></note>do remember my faults this day: <verse number="10" style="v"/>Pharaoh was wroth with his servants, and put me in ward in the house of the captain of the guard, me and the chief baker: <verse number="11" style="v"/>and we dreamed a dream in one night, I and he; we dreamed each man according to the interpretation of his dream. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And there was with us there a young man, a Hebrew, servant to the captain of the guard; and we told him, and he interpreted to us our dreams; to each man according to his dream he did interpret. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as he interpreted to us, so it was; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">I was restored&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. and he was hanged</char></char></note>me he restored unto mine office, and him he hanged.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>Then Pharaoh sent and called Joseph, and they brought him hastily out of the dungeon: and he shaved himself, and changed his raiment, and came in unto Pharaoh. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I have dreamed a dream, and there is none that can interpret it: and I have heard say of thee, that when thou hearest a dream thou canst interpret it. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Joseph answered Pharaoh, saying, It is not in me: God will give Pharaoh an answer of peace. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Pharaoh spake unto Joseph, In my dream, behold, I stood upon the brink of the river: <verse number="18" style="v"/>and, behold, there came up out of the river seven kine, fat-fleshed and well-favored; and they fed in the reed-grass: <verse number="19" style="v"/>and, behold, seven other kine came up after them, poor and very ill-favored and lean-fleshed, such as I never saw in all the land of Egypt for badness: <verse number="20" style="v"/>and the lean and ill-favored kine did eat up the first seven fat kine: <verse number="21" style="v"/>and when they had eaten them up, it could not be known that they had eaten them; but they were still ill-favored, as at the beginning. So I awoke. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And I saw in my dream, and, behold, seven ears came up upon one stalk, full and good: <verse number="23" style="v"/>and, behold, seven ears, withered, thin, <char style="add">and</char> blasted with the east wind, sprung up after them: <verse number="24" style="v"/>and the thin ears swallowed up the seven good ears: and I told it unto the magicians; but there was none that could declare it to me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto Pharaoh, The dream of Pharaoh is one: what God is about to do he hath declared unto Pharaoh. <verse number="26" style="v"/>The seven good kine are seven years; and the seven good ears are seven years: the dream is one. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And the seven lean and ill-favored kine that came up after them are seven years, and also the seven empty ears blasted with the east wind; they shall be seven years of famine. <verse number="28" style="v"/>That is the thing which I spake unto Pharaoh: what God is about to do he hath showed unto Pharaoh. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Behold, there come seven years of great plenty throughout all the land of Egypt: <verse number="30" style="v"/>and there shall arise after them seven years of famine; and all the plenty shall be forgotten in the land of Egypt; and the famine shall consume the land; <verse number="31" style="v"/>and the plenty shall not be known in the land by reason of that famine which followeth; for it shall be very grievous. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And for that the dream was doubled unto Pharaoh, it is because the thing is established by God, and God will shortly bring it to pass. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Now therefore let Pharaoh look out a man discreet and wise, and set him over the land of Egypt. <verse number="34" style="v"/>Let Pharaoh do <char style="add">this</char>, and let him appoint overseers over the land, and take up the fifth part of the land of Egypt in the seven plenteous years. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And let them gather all the food of these good years that come, and lay up grain under the hand of Pharaoh for food in the cities, and let them keep it. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And the food shall be for a store to the land against the seven years of famine, which shall be in the land of Egypt; that the land perish not through the famine.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v"/>And the thing was good in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of all his servants. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said unto his servants, Can we find such a one as this, a man in whom the spirit of God is? <verse number="39" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Forasmuch as God hath showed thee all this, there is none so discreet and wise as thou: <verse number="40" style="v"/>thou shalt be over my house, and according unto thy word shall all my people <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">order themselves</char>. Or, <char style="it">do homage</char></char></note>be ruled: only in the throne will I be greater than thou. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, See, I have set thee over all the land of Egypt. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And Pharaoh took off his signet ring from his hand, and put it upon Joseph&#8217;s hand, and arrayed him in vestures of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cotton</char></char></note>fine linen, and put a gold chain about his neck; <verse number="43" style="v"/>and he made him to ride in the second chariot which he had; and they cried before him, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">Abrech</char>, probably an Egyptian word, similar in sound to the Hebrew word meaning <char style="it">to kneel</char>.</char></note>Bow the knee: and he set him over all the land of Egypt. <verse number="44" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I am Pharaoh, and without thee shall no man lift up his hand or his foot in all the land of Egypt. <verse number="45" style="v"/>And Pharaoh called Joseph&#8217;s name Zaphenath-paneah; and he gave him to wife Asenath, the daughter of Poti-phera priest of On. And Joseph went out over the land of Egypt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v"/>And Joseph was thirty years old when he stood before Pharaoh king of Egypt. And Joseph went out from the presence of Pharaoh, and went throughout all the land of Egypt. <verse number="47" style="v"/>And in the seven plenteous years the earth brought forth by handfuls. <verse number="48" style="v"/>And he gathered up all the food of the seven years which were in the land of Egypt, and laid up the food in the cities: the food of the field, which was round about every city, laid he up in the same. <verse number="49" style="v"/>And Joseph laid up grain as the sand of the sea, very much, until he left off numbering; for it was without number. <verse number="50" style="v"/>And unto Joseph were born two sons before the year of famine came, whom Asenath, the daughter of Poti-phera priest of On, bare unto him. <verse number="51" style="v"/>And Joseph called the name of the first-born <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Making to forget</char>.</char></note>Manasseh: For, <char style="add">said he</char>, God hath made me forget all my toil, and all my father&#8217;s house. <verse number="52" style="v"/>And the name of the second called he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">From a Hebrew word signifying <char style="it">to be fruitful</char>.</char></note>Ephraim: For God hath made me fruitful in the land of my affliction. <verse number="53" style="v"/>And the seven years of plenty, that was in the land of Egypt, came to an end. <verse number="54" style="v"/>And the seven years of famine began to come, according as Joseph had said: and there was famine in all lands; but in all the land of Egypt there was bread. <verse number="55" style="v"/>And when all the land of Egypt was famished, the people cried to Pharaoh for bread: and Pharaoh said unto all the Egyptians, Go unto Joseph; what he saith to you, do. <verse number="56" style="v"/>And the famine was over all the face of the earth: and Joseph opened all the store-houses, and sold unto the Egyptians; and the famine was sore in the land of Egypt. <verse number="57" style="v"/>And all countries came into Egypt to Joseph to buy grain, because the famine was sore in all the earth.</para>
	<chapter number="42" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now Jacob saw that there was grain in Egypt, and Jacob said unto his sons, Why do ye look one upon another? <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he said, Behold, I have heard that there is grain in Egypt: get you down thither, and buy for us from thence; that we may live, and not die. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Joseph&#8217;s ten brethren went down to buy grain from Egypt. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But Benjamin, Joseph&#8217;s brother, Jacob sent not with his brethren; for he said, Lest peradventure harm befall him. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the sons of Israel came to buy among those that came: for the famine was in the land of Canaan. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Joseph was the governor over the land; he it was that sold to all the people of the land. And Joseph&#8217;s brethren came, and bowed down themselves to him with their faces to the earth. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Joseph saw his brethren, and he knew them, but made himself strange unto them, and spake roughly with them; and he said unto them, Whence come ye? And they said, From the land of Canaan to buy food. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Joseph knew his brethren, but they knew not him. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Joseph remembered the dreams which he dreamed of them, and said unto them, Ye are spies; to see the nakedness of the land ye are come. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And they said unto him, Nay, my lord, but to buy food are thy servants come. <verse number="11" style="v"/>We are all one man&#8217;s sons; we are true men, thy servants are no spies. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he said unto them, Nay, but to see the nakedness of the land ye are come. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And they said, We thy servants are twelve brethren, the sons of one man in the land of Canaan; and, behold, the youngest is this day with our father, and one is not. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto them, That is it that I spake unto you, saying, Ye are spies: <verse number="15" style="v"/>hereby ye shall be proved: by the life of Pharaoh ye shall not go forth hence, except your youngest brother come hither. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Send one of you, and let him fetch your brother, and ye shall be bound, that your words may be proved, whether there be truth in you: or else by the life of Pharaoh surely ye are spies. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And he put them all together into ward three days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto them the third day, This do, and live; for I fear God: <verse number="19" style="v"/>if ye be true men, let one of your brethren be bound in your prison-house; but go ye, carry grain for the famine of your houses: <verse number="20" style="v"/>and bring your youngest brother unto me; so shall your words be verified, and ye shall not die. And they did so. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And they said one to another, We are verily guilty concerning our brother, in that we saw the distress of his soul, when he besought us, and we would not hear; therefore is this distress come upon us. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Reuben answered them, saying, Spake I not unto you, saying, Do not sin against the child; and ye would not hear? therefore also, behold, his blood is required. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And they knew not that Joseph understood them; for there was an interpreter between them. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And he turned himself about from them, and wept; and he returned to them, and spake to them, and took Simeon from among them, and bound him before their eyes. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Then Joseph commanded to fill their vessels with grain, and to restore every man&#8217;s money into his sack, and to give them provision for the way: and thus was it done unto them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>And they laded their asses with their grain, and departed thence. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And as one of them opened his sack to give his ass provender in the lodging-place, he espied his money; and, behold, it was in the mouth of his sack. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And he said unto his brethren, My money is restored; and, lo, it is even in my sack: and their heart failed them, and they turned trembling one to another, saying, What is this that God hath done unto us? <verse number="29" style="v"/>And they came unto Jacob their father unto the land of Canaan, and told him all that had befallen them, saying, <verse number="30" style="v"/>The man, the lord of the land, spake roughly with us, and took us for spies of the country. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And we said unto him, We are true men; we are no spies: <verse number="32" style="v"/>we are twelve brethren, sons of our father; one is not, and the youngest is this day with our father in the land of Canaan. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And the man, the lord of the land, said unto us, Hereby shall I know that ye are true men: leave one of your brethren with me, and take <char style="add">grain for</char> the famine of your houses, and go your way; <verse number="34" style="v"/>and bring your youngest brother unto me: then shall I know that ye are no spies, but that ye are true men: so will I deliver you your brother, and ye shall traffic in the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v"/>And it came to pass as they emptied their sacks, that, behold, every man&#8217;s bundle of money was in his sack: and when they and their father saw their bundles of money, they were afraid. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And Jacob their father said unto them, Me have ye bereaved of my children: Joseph is not, and Simeon is not, and ye will take Benjamin away: all these things are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">upon</char></char></note>against me. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And Reuben spake unto his father, saying, Slay my two sons, if I bring him not to thee: deliver him into my hand, and I will bring him to thee again. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And he said, My son shall not go down with you; for his brother is dead, and he only is left: if harm befall him by the way in which ye go, then will ye bring down my gray hairs with sorrow to Sheol.</para>
	<chapter number="43" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the famine was sore in the land. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when they had eaten up the grain which they had brought out of Egypt, their father said unto them, Go again, buy us a little food. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Judah spake unto him, saying, The man did solemnly protest unto us, saying, Ye shall not see my face, except your brother be with you. <verse number="4" style="v"/>If thou wilt send our brother with us, we will go down and buy thee food: <verse number="5" style="v"/>but if thou wilt not send him, we will not go down; for the man said unto us, Ye shall not see my face, except your brother be with you. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Israel said, Wherefore dealt ye so ill with me, as to tell the man whether ye had yet a brother? <verse number="7" style="v"/>And they said, The man asked straitly concerning ourselves, and concerning our kindred, saying, Is your father yet alive? have ye <char style="add">another</char> brother? and we told him according to the tenor of these words: could we in any wise know that he would say, Bring your brother down? <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Judah said unto Israel his father, Send the lad with me, and we will arise and go; that we may live, and not die, both we, and thou, and also our little ones. <verse number="9" style="v"/>I will be surety for him; of my hand shalt thou require him: if I bring him not unto thee, and set him before thee, then <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">I shall have sinned against thee for ever</char>.</char></note>let me bear the blame for ever: <verse number="10" style="v"/>for except we had lingered, surely we had now returned a second time. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And their father Israel said unto them, If it be so now, do this: take of the choice fruits of the land in your vessels, and carry down the man a present, a little balm, and a little honey, spicery and myrrh, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">pistachio nuts</char>.</char></note>nuts, and almonds; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and take double money in your hand; and the money that was returned in the mouth of your sacks carry again in your hand; peradventure it was an oversight: <verse number="13" style="v"/>take also your brother, and arise, go again unto the man: <verse number="14" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El Shaddai</char>.</char></note>God Almighty give you mercy before the man, that he may release unto you your other brother and Benjamin. And if I be bereaved of my children, I am bereaved. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the men took that present, and they took double money in their hand, and Benjamin; and rose up, and went down to Egypt, and stood before Joseph.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And when Joseph saw Benjamin with them, he said to the steward of his house, Bring the men into the house, and slay, and make ready; for the men shall dine with me at noon. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the man did as Joseph bade; and the man brought the men to Joseph&#8217;s house. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the men were afraid, because they were brought to Joseph&#8217;s house; and they said, Because of the money that was returned in our sacks at the first time are we brought in; that he may <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">roll himself upon us</char>.</char></note>seek occasion against us, and fall upon us, and take us for bondmen, and our asses. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And they came near to the steward of Joseph&#8217;s house, and they spake unto him at the door of the house, <verse number="20" style="v"/>and said, Oh, my lord, we came indeed down at the first time to buy food: <verse number="21" style="v"/>and it came to pass, when we came to the lodging-place, that we opened our sacks, and, behold, every man&#8217;s money was in the mouth of his sack, our money in full weight: and we have brought it again in our hand. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And other money have we brought down in our hand to buy food: we know not who put our money in our sacks. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he said, Peace be to you, fear not: your God, and the God of your father, hath given you treasure in your sacks: I had your money. And he brought Simeon out unto them. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And the man brought the men into Joseph&#8217;s house, and gave them water, and they washed their feet; and he gave their asses provender. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And they made ready the present against Joseph&#8217;s coming at noon: for they heard that they should eat bread there.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>And when Joseph came home, they brought him the present which was in their hand into the house, and bowed down themselves to him to the earth. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And he asked them of their welfare, and said, Is your father well, the old man of whom ye spake? Is he yet alive? <verse number="28" style="v"/>And they said, Thy servant our father is well, he is yet alive. And they bowed the head, and made obeisance. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And he lifted up his eyes, and saw Benjamin his brother, his mother&#8217;s son, and said, Is this your youngest brother, of whom ye spake unto me? And he said, God be gracious unto thee, my son. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And Joseph made haste; for his heart yearned over his brother: and he sought where to weep; and he entered into his chamber, and wept there. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And he washed his face, and came out; and he refrained himself, and said, Set on bread. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And they set on for him by himself, and for them by themselves, and for the Egyptians, that did eat with him, by themselves: because the Egyptians might not eat bread with the Hebrews; for that is an abomination unto the Egyptians. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And they sat before him, the first-born according to his birthright, and the youngest according to his youth: and the men marvelled one with another. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">messes were taken</char></char></note>he took <char style="add">and sent</char> messes unto them from before him: but Benjamin&#8217;s mess was five times so much as any of theirs. And they drank, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">drank largely</char>.</char></note>were merry with him.</para>
	<chapter number="44" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And he commanded the steward of his house, saying, Fill the men&#8217;s sacks with food, as much as they can carry, and put every man&#8217;s money in his sack&#8217;s mouth. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And put my cup, the silver cup, in the sack&#8217;s mouth of the youngest, and his grain money. And he did according to the word that Joseph had spoken. <verse number="3" style="v"/>As soon as the morning was light, the men were sent away, they and their asses. <verse number="4" style="v"/><char style="add">And</char> when they were gone out of the city, and were not yet far off, Joseph said unto his steward, Up, follow after the men; and when thou dost overtake them, say unto them, Wherefore have ye rewarded evil for good? <verse number="5" style="v"/>Is not this that in which my lord drinketh, and whereby he indeed divineth? ye have done evil in so doing. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he overtook them, and he spake unto them these words. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And they said unto him, Wherefore speaketh my lord such words as these? Far be it from thy servants that they should do such a thing. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Behold, the money, which we found in our sacks&#8217; mouths, we brought again unto thee out of the land of Canaan: how then should we steal out of thy lord&#8217;s house silver or gold? <verse number="9" style="v"/>With whomsoever of thy servants it be found, let him die, and we also will be my lord&#8217;s bondmen. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And he said, Now also let it be according unto your words: he with whom it is found shall be my bondman; and ye shall be blameless. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Then they hasted, and took down every man his sack to the ground, and opened every man his sack. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he searched, <char style="add">and</char> began at the eldest, and left off at the youngest: and the cup was found in Benjamin&#8217;s sack. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Then they rent their clothes, and laded every man his ass, and returned to the city.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And Judah and his brethren came to Joseph&#8217;s house; and he was yet there: and they fell before him on the ground. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto them, What deed is this that ye have done? know ye not that such a man as I can indeed divine? <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Judah said, What shall we say unto my lord? what shall we speak? or how shall we clear ourselves? God hath found out the iniquity of thy servants: behold, we are my lord&#8217;s bondmen, both we, and he also in whose hand the cup is found. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And he said, Far be it from me that I should do so: the man in whose hand the cup is found, he shall be my bondman; but as for you, get you up in peace unto your father.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>Then Judah came near unto him, and said, Oh, my lord, let thy servant, I pray thee, speak a word in my lord&#8217;s ears, and let not thine anger burn against thy servant; for thou art even as Pharaoh. <verse number="19" style="v"/>My lord asked his servants, saying, Have ye a father, or a brother? <verse number="20" style="v"/>And we said unto my lord, We have a father, an old man, and a child of his old age, a little one; and his brother is dead, and he alone is left of his mother; and his father loveth him. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And thou saidst unto thy servants, Bring him down unto me, that I may set mine eyes upon him. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And we said unto my lord, The lad cannot leave his father: for if he should leave his father, his father would die. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And thou saidst unto thy servants, Except your youngest brother come down with you, ye shall see my face no more. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And it came to pass when we came up unto thy servant my father, we told him the words of my lord. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And our father said, Go again, buy us a little food. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And we said, We cannot go down: if our youngest brother be with us, then will we go down; for we may not see the man&#8217;s face, except our youngest brother be with us. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And thy servant my father said unto us, Ye know that my wife bare me two sons: <verse number="28" style="v"/>and the one went out from me, and I said, Surely he is torn in pieces; and I have not seen him since: <verse number="29" style="v"/>and if ye take this one also from me, and harm befall him, ye will bring down my gray hairs with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">evil</char>.</char></note>sorrow to Sheol. <verse number="30" style="v"/>Now therefore when I come to thy servant my father, and the lad is not with us; seeing that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">his soul is knit with the lad&#8217;s soul</char>. See <ref loc="1SA 18:1">1 Sam. 18:1</ref>.</char></note>his life is bound up in the lad&#8217;s life; <verse number="31" style="v"/>it will come to pass, when he seeth that the lad is not <char style="add">with us</char>, that he will die: and thy servants will bring down the gray hairs of thy servant our father with sorrow to Sheol. <verse number="32" style="v"/>For thy servant became surety for the lad unto my father, saying, If I bring him not unto thee, then shall I bear the blame to my father for ever. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Now therefore, let thy servant, I pray thee, abide instead of the lad a bondman to my lord; and let the lad go up with his brethren. <verse number="34" style="v"/>For how shall I go up to my father, if the lad be not with me? lest I see the evil that shall come on my father.</para>
	<chapter number="45" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Then Joseph could not refrain himself before all them that stood by him; and he cried, Cause every man to go out from me. And there stood no man with him, while Joseph made himself known unto his brethren. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">gave forth his voice in weeping</char>.</char></note>wept aloud: and the Egyptians heard, and the house of Pharaoh heard. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto his brethren, I am Joseph; doth my father yet live? And his brethren could not answer him; for they were troubled at his presence. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto his brethren, Come near to me, I pray you. And they came near. And he said, I am Joseph your brother, whom ye sold into Egypt. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And now be not grieved, nor angry with yourselves, that ye sold me hither: for God did send me before you to preserve life. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For these two years hath the famine been in the land: and there are yet five years, in which there shall be neither plowing nor harvest. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And God sent me before you to preserve you a remnant in the earth, and to save you alive <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to be a great company that escape</char></char></note>by a great deliverance. <verse number="8" style="v"/>So now it was not you that sent me hither, but God: and he hath made me a father to Pharaoh, and lord of all his house, and ruler over all the land of Egypt. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Haste ye, and go up to my father, and say unto him, Thus saith thy son Joseph, God hath made me lord of all Egypt: come down unto me, tarry not; <verse number="10" style="v"/>and thou shalt dwell in the land of Goshen, and thou shalt be near unto me, thou, and thy children, and thy children&#8217;s children, and thy flocks, and thy herds, and all that thou hast: <verse number="11" style="v"/>and there will I nourish thee; for there are yet five years of famine; lest thou come to poverty, thou, and thy household, and all that thou hast. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And, behold, your eyes see, and the eyes of my brother Benjamin, that it is my mouth that speaketh unto you. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And ye shall tell my father of all my glory in Egypt, and of all that ye have seen: and ye shall haste and bring down my father hither. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And he fell upon his brother Benjamin&#8217;s neck, and wept; and Benjamin wept upon his neck. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And he kissed all his brethren, and wept upon them: and after that his brethren talked with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And the report thereof was heard in Pharaoh&#8217;s house, saying, Joseph&#8217;s brethren are come: and it pleased Pharaoh well, and his servants. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Say unto thy brethren, This do ye: lade your beasts, and go, get you unto the land of Canaan; <verse number="18" style="v"/>and take your father and your households, and come unto me: and I will give you the good of the land of Egypt, and ye shall eat the fat of the land. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Now thou art commanded, this do ye: take you wagons out of the land of Egypt for your little ones, and for your wives, and bring your father, and come. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Also regard not your stuff; for the good of all the land of Egypt is yours.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>And the sons of Israel did so: and Joseph gave them wagons, according to the commandment of Pharaoh, and gave them provision for the way. <verse number="22" style="v"/>To all of them he gave each man changes of raiment; but to Benjamin he gave three hundred pieces of silver, and five changes of raiment. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And to his father he sent after this manner: ten asses laden with the good things of Egypt, and ten she-asses laden with grain and bread and provision for his father by the way. <verse number="24" style="v"/>So he sent his brethren away, and they departed: and he said unto them, See that ye fall not out by the way. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And they went up out of Egypt, and came into the land of Canaan unto Jacob their father. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And they told him, saying, Joseph is yet alive, and he is ruler over all the land of Egypt. And his heart fainted, for he believed them not. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And they told him all the words of Joseph, which he had said unto them: and when he saw the wagons which Joseph had sent to carry him, the spirit of Jacob their father revived: <verse number="28" style="v"/>and Israel said, It is enough; Joseph my son is yet alive: I will go and see him before I die.</para>
	<chapter number="46" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Israel took his journey with all that he had, and came to Beer-sheba, and offered sacrifices unto the God of his father Isaac. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And God spake unto Israel in the visions of the night, and said, Jacob, Jacob. And he said, Here am I. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he said, I am God, the God of thy father: fear not to go down into Egypt; for I will there make of thee a great nation: <verse number="4" style="v"/>I will go down with thee into Egypt; and I will also surely bring thee up again: and Joseph shall put his hand upon thine eyes. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Jacob rose up from Beer-sheba: and the sons of Israel carried Jacob their father, and their little ones, and their wives, in the wagons which Pharaoh had sent to carry him. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And they took their cattle, and their goods, which they had gotten in the land of Canaan, and came into Egypt, Jacob, and all his seed with him: <verse number="7" style="v"/>his sons, and his sons&#8217; sons with him, his daughters, and his sons&#8217; daughters, and all his seed brought he with him into Egypt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And these are the names of the children of Israel, who came into Egypt, Jacob and his sons: Reuben, Jacob&#8217;s first-born. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the sons of Reuben: Hanoch, and Pallu, and Hezron, and Carmi. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And the sons of Simeon: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:12">Num. 26:12</ref>; <ref loc="1CH 4:24">1 Chr. 4:24</ref>, <char style="it">Nemuel</char>.</char></note>Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 4:24">1 Chr. 4:24</ref>, <char style="it">Jarib</char>.</char></note>Jachin, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:13">Num. 26:13</ref>; <ref loc="1CH 4:24">1 Chr. 4:24</ref>, <char style="it">Zerah</char>.</char></note>Zohar, and Shaul the son of a Canaanitish woman. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the sons of Levi: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:16">1 Chr. 6:16</ref>, <char style="it">Gershom</char>.</char></note>Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And the sons of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah, and Perez, and Zerah; but Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. And the sons of Perez were Hezron and Hamul. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And the sons of Issachar: Tola, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 7:1">1 Chr. 7:1</ref>, <char style="it">Puvah, Jashub</char>. See <ref loc="NUM 26:23">Num. 26:23</ref>, <ref loc="NUM 26:24">24</ref>.</char></note>Puvah, and Iob, and Shimron. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the sons of Zebulun: Sered, and Elon, and Jahleel. <verse number="15" style="v"/>These are the sons of Leah, whom she bare unto Jacob in Paddan-aram, with his daughter Dinah: all the souls of his sons and his daughters were thirty and three. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the sons of Gad: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:15">Num. 26:15</ref>, <char style="it">Zephon</char>.</char></note>Ziphion, and Haggi, Shuni, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:16">Num. 26:16</ref>, <char style="it">Ozni</char>.</char></note>Ezbon, Eri, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:17">Num. 26:17</ref>, <char style="it">Arod</char>.</char></note>Arodi, and Areli. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the sons of Asher: Imnah, and Ishvah, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah their sister; and the sons of Beriah: Heber, and Malchiel. <verse number="18" style="v"/>These are the sons of Zilpah, whom Laban gave to Leah his daughter; and these she bare unto Jacob, even sixteen souls. <verse number="19" style="v"/>The sons of Rachel Jacob&#8217;s wife: Joseph and Benjamin. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And unto Joseph in the land of Egypt were born Manasseh and Ephraim, whom Asenath, the daughter of Poti-phera priest of On, bare unto him. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And the sons of Benjamin: Bela, and Becher, and Ashbel, Gera, and Naaman, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:38">Num. 26:38</ref>, <char style="it">Ahiram</char>.</char></note>Ehi, and Rosh, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:39">Num. 26:39</ref>, <char style="it">Shephupham</char>. In <ref loc="1CH 7:12">1 Chr. 7:12</ref>, <char style="it">Shuppim</char>.</char></note>Muppim, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:39">Num. 26:39</ref>, <char style="it">Hupham</char>.</char></note>Huppim, and Ard. <verse number="22" style="v"/>These are the sons of Rachel, who were born to Jacob: all the souls were fourteen. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And the sons of Dan: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:42">Num. 26:42</ref>, <char style="it">Shuham</char>.</char></note>Hushim. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And the sons of Naphtali: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 7:13">1 Chr. 7:13</ref>, <char style="it">Jahziel</char>.</char></note>Jahzeel, and Guni, and Jezer, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 7:13">1 Chr. 7:13</ref>, <char style="it">Shallum</char>.</char></note>Shillem. <verse number="25" style="v"/>These are the sons of Bilhah, whom Laban gave unto Rachel his daughter, and these she bare unto Jacob: all the souls were seven. <verse number="26" style="v"/>All the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">souls belonging to Jacob that came</char></char></note>souls that came with Jacob into Egypt, that came out of his loins, besides Jacob&#8217;s sons&#8217; wives, all the souls were threescore and six; <verse number="27" style="v"/>and the sons of Joseph, who were born to him in Egypt, were two souls: all the souls of the house of Jacob, that came into Egypt, were threescore and ten.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And he sent Judah before him unto Joseph, to show the way before him unto Goshen; and they came into the land of Goshen. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Joseph made ready his chariot, and went up to meet Israel his father, to Goshen; and he presented himself unto him, and fell on his neck, and wept on his neck a good while. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And Israel said unto Joseph, Now let me die, since I have seen thy face, that thou art yet alive. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto his brethren, and unto his father&#8217;s house, I will go up, and tell Pharaoh, and will say unto him, My brethren, and my father&#8217;s house, who were in the land of Canaan, are come unto me; <verse number="32" style="v"/>and the men are shepherds, for they have been keepers of cattle; and they have brought their flocks, and their herds, and all that they have. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And it shall come to pass, when Pharaoh shall call you, and shall say, What is your occupation? <verse number="34" style="v"/>that ye shall say, Thy servants have been keepers of cattle from our youth even until now, both we, and our fathers: that ye may dwell in the land of Goshen; for every shepherd is an abomination unto the Egyptians.</para>
	<chapter number="47" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Then Joseph went in and told Pharaoh, and said, My father and my brethren, and their flocks, and their herds, and all that they have, are come out of the land of Canaan; and, behold, they are in the land of Goshen. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And from among his brethren he took five men, and presented them unto Pharaoh. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said unto his brethren, What is your occupation? And they said unto Pharaoh, Thy servants are shepherds, both we, and our fathers. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And they said unto Pharaoh, To sojourn in the land are we come; for there is no pasture for thy servants&#8217; flocks; for the famine is sore in the land of Canaan: now therefore, we pray thee, let thy servants dwell in the land of Goshen. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Pharaoh spake unto Joseph, saying, Thy father and thy brethren are come unto thee: <verse number="6" style="v"/>the land of Egypt is before thee; in the best of the land make thy father and thy brethren to dwell; in the land of Goshen let them dwell: and if thou knowest any <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">men of activity</char></char></note>able men among them, then make them rulers over my cattle. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Joseph brought in Jacob his father, and set him before Pharaoh: and Jacob blessed Pharaoh. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said unto Jacob, How many are the days of the years of thy life? <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Jacob said unto Pharaoh, The days of the years of my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sojournings</char></char></note>pilgrimage are a hundred and thirty years: few and evil have been the days of the years of my life, and they have not attained unto the days of the years of the life of my fathers in the days of their pilgrimage. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Jacob blessed Pharaoh, and went out from the presence of Pharaoh. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Joseph placed his father and his brethren, and gave them a possession in the land of Egypt, in the best of the land, in the land of Rameses, as Pharaoh had commanded. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Joseph nourished his father, and his brethren, and all his father&#8217;s household, with bread, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">according to</char> the number of <char style="it">their little ones</char></char></note>according to their families.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And there was no bread in all the land; for the famine was very sore, so that the land of Egypt and the land of Canaan fainted by reason of the famine. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Joseph gathered up all the money that was found in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, for the grain which they bought: and Joseph brought the money into Pharaoh&#8217;s house. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And when the money was all spent in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, all the Egyptians came unto Joseph, and said, Give us bread: for why should we die in thy presence? for <char style="add">our</char> money faileth. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Joseph said, Give your cattle; and I will give you for your cattle, if money fail. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And they brought their cattle unto Joseph; and Joseph gave them bread in exchange for the horses, and for the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">cattle of the flocks, and for the cattle of the herds</char>.</char></note>flocks, and for the herds, and for the asses: and he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">led them</char> as a shepherd.</char></note>fed them with bread in exchange for all their cattle for that year. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And when that year was ended, they came unto him the second year, and said unto him, We will not hide from my lord, how that our money is all spent; and the herds of cattle are my lord&#8217;s; there is nought left in the sight of my lord, but our bodies, and our lands: <verse number="19" style="v"/>wherefore should we die before thine eyes, both we and our land? buy us and our land for bread, and we and our land will be servants unto Pharaoh: and give us seed, that we may live, and not die, and that the land be not desolate.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>So Joseph bought all the land of Egypt for Pharaoh; for the Egyptians sold every man his field, because the famine was sore upon them: and the land became Pharaoh&#8217;s. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And as for the people, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">According to Septuagint and Vulgate, <char style="it">he made bondmen of them, from etc.</char></char></note>he removed them <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">according to their cities</char></char></note>to the cities from one end of the border of Egypt even to the other end thereof. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Only the land of the priests bought he not: for the priests had a portion from Pharaoh, and did eat their portion which Pharaoh gave them; wherefore they sold not their land. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Then Joseph said unto the people, Behold, I have bought you this day and your land for Pharaoh: lo, here is seed for you, and ye shall sow the land. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And it shall come to pass at the ingatherings, that ye shall give a fifth unto Pharaoh, and four parts shall be your own, for seed of the field, and for your food, and for them of your households, and for food for your little ones. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And they said, Thou hast saved our lives: let us find favor in the sight of my lord, and we will be Pharaoh&#8217;s servants. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Joseph made it a statute concerning the land of Egypt unto this day, that Pharaoh should have the fifth; only the land of the priests alone became not Pharaoh&#8217;s.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v"/>And Israel dwelt in the land of Egypt, in the land of Goshen; and they gat them possessions therein, and were fruitful, and multiplied exceedingly. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And Jacob lived in the land of Egypt seventeen years: so the days of Jacob, the years of his life, were a hundred forty and seven years. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And the time drew near that Israel must die: and he called his son Joseph, and said unto him, If now I have found favor in thy sight, put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh, and deal kindly and truly with me: bury me not, I pray thee, in Egypt; <verse number="30" style="v"/>but when I sleep with my fathers, thou shalt carry me out of Egypt, and bury me in their burying-place. And he said, I will do as thou hast said. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And he said, Swear unto me: and he sware unto him. And Israel bowed himself upon the bed&#8217;s head.</para>
	<chapter number="48" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass after these things, that one said to Joseph, Behold, thy father is sick: and he took with him his two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And one told Jacob, and said, Behold, thy son Joseph cometh unto thee: and Israel strengthened himself, and sat upon the bed. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Jacob said unto Joseph, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">El Shaddai</char>.</char></note>God Almighty appeared unto me at Luz in the land of Canaan, and blessed me, <verse number="4" style="v"/>and said unto me, Behold, I will make thee fruitful, and multiply thee, and I will make of thee a company of peoples, and will give this land to thy seed after thee for an everlasting possession. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And now thy two sons, who were born unto thee in the land of Egypt before I came unto thee into Egypt, are mine; Ephraim and Manasseh, even as Reuben and Simeon, shall be mine. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And thy issue, that thou <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hast begotten</char></char></note>begettest after them, shall be thine; they shall be called after the name of their brethren in their inheritance. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And as for me, when I came from Paddan, Rachel died <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to my sorrow</char></char></note>by me in the land of Canaan in the way, when there was still some distance to come unto Ephrath: and I buried her there in the way to Ephrath (the same is Beth-lehem).</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And Israel beheld Joseph&#8217;s sons, and said, Who are these? <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto his father, They are my sons, whom God hath given me here. And he said, Bring them, I pray thee, unto me, and I will bless them. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Now the eyes of Israel were dim for age, so that he could not see. And he brought them near unto him; and he kissed them, and embraced them. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Israel said unto Joseph, I had not thought to see thy face: and, lo, God hath let me see thy seed also. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Joseph brought them out from between his knees; and he bowed himself with his face to the earth. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Joseph took them both, Ephraim in his right hand toward Israel&#8217;s left hand, and Manasseh in his left hand toward Israel&#8217;s right hand, and brought them near unto him. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Israel stretched out his right hand, and laid it upon Ephraim&#8217;s head, who was the younger, and his left hand upon Manasseh&#8217;s head, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">crossing his hands</char></char></note>guiding his hands wittingly; for Manasseh was the first-born. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And he blessed Joseph, and said, The God before whom my fathers Abraham and Isaac did walk, the God who hath fed me all my life long unto this day, <verse number="16" style="v"/>the angel who hath redeemed me from all evil, bless the lads; and let my name be named on them, and the name of my fathers Abraham and Isaac; and let them grow into a multitude in the midst of the earth. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And when Joseph saw that his father laid his right hand upon the head of Ephraim, it displeased him: and he held up his father&#8217;s hand, to remove it from Ephraim&#8217;s head unto Manasseh&#8217;s head. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto his father, Not so, my father; for this is the first-born; put thy right hand upon his head. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And his father refused, and said, I know <char style="add">it</char>, my son, I know <char style="add">it</char>; he also shall become a people, and he also shall be great: howbeit his younger brother shall be greater than he, and his seed shall become a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">fulness</char>.</char></note>multitude of nations. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And he blessed them that day, saying, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">By</char></char></note>In thee will Israel bless, saying, God make thee as Ephraim and as Manasseh: and he set Ephraim before Manasseh. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Israel said unto Joseph, Behold, I die: but God will be with you, and bring you again unto the land of your fathers. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Moreover I have given to thee one <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">mountain slope</char>. Hebrew <char style="it">shechem</char>, shoulder</char></note>portion above thy brethren, which I took out of the hand of the Amorite with my sword and with my bow.</para>
	<chapter number="49" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Jacob called unto his sons, and said: Gather yourselves together, that I may tell you that which shall befall you in the latter days.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="2" style="v"/>Assemble yourselves, and hear, ye sons of Jacob;</para>
	<para style="q1">And hearken unto Israel your father.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="3" style="v"/>Reuben, thou art my first-born, my might, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">first-fruits</char></char></note>beginning of my strength;</para>
	<para style="q1">The pre-eminence of dignity, and the pre-eminence of power.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="4" style="v"/>Boiling over as water, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">have not thou</char></char></note>thou shalt not have the pre-eminence;</para>
	<para style="q1">Because thou wentest up to thy father&#8217;s bed;</para>
	<para style="q1">Then defiledst thou it: he went up to my couch.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="5" style="v"/>Simeon and Levi are brethren;</para>
	<para style="q1">Weapons of violence are their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">compacts</char></char></note>swords.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="6" style="v"/>O my soul, come not thou into their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">secret</char></char></note>council;</para>
	<para style="q1">Unto their assembly, my glory, be not thou united;</para>
	<para style="q1">For in their anger they slew <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">men</char></char></note>a man,</para>
	<para style="q1">And in their self-will they hocked <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">oxen</char></char></note>an ox.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="7" style="v"/>Cursed be their anger, for it was fierce;</para>
	<para style="q1">And their wrath, for it was cruel:</para>
	<para style="q1">I will divide them in Jacob,</para>
	<para style="q1">And scatter them in Israel.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="8" style="v"/>Judah, thee shall thy brethren praise:</para>
	<para style="q1">Thy hand shall be on the neck of thine enemies;</para>
	<para style="q1">Thy father&#8217;s sons shall bow down before thee.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="9" style="v"/>Judah is a lion&#8217;s whelp;</para>
	<para style="q1">From the prey, my son, thou art gone up:</para>
	<para style="q1">He stooped down, he couched as a lion,</para>
	<para style="q1">And as a lioness; who shall rouse him up?</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="10" style="v"/>The sceptre shall not depart from Judah,</para>
	<para style="q1">Nor <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a lawgiver</char></char></note>the ruler&#8217;s staff from between his feet,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Till he come to Shiloh, having the obedience of the peoples</char>. Or, according to Syriac, <char style="it">Till he come whose it is etc.</char></char></note>Until Shiloh come;</para>
	<para style="q1">And unto him shall the obedience of the peoples be.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="11" style="v"/>Binding his foal unto the vine,</para>
	<para style="q1">And his ass&#8217;s colt unto the choice vine;</para>
	<para style="q1">He hath washed his garments in wine,</para>
	<para style="q1">And his vesture in the blood of grapes:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="12" style="v"/>His eyes shall be red with wine,</para>
	<para style="q1">And his teeth white with milk.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="13" style="v"/>Zebulun shall dwell at the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">beach</char>.</char></note>haven of the sea;</para>
	<para style="q1">And he shall be for a haven of ships;</para>
	<para style="q1">And his border shall be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by</char></char></note>upon Sidon.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="14" style="v"/>Issachar is a strong ass,</para>
	<para style="q1">Couching down between the sheepfolds:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And he saw <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">rest</char></char></note>a resting-place that it was good,</para>
	<para style="q1">And the land that it was pleasant;</para>
	<para style="q1">And he bowed his shoulder to bear,</para>
	<para style="q1">And became a servant under taskwork.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="16" style="v"/>Dan shall judge his people,</para>
	<para style="q1">As one of the tribes of Israel.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="17" style="v"/>Dan shall be a serpent in the way,</para>
	<para style="q1">An <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">horned snake</char></char></note>adder in the path,</para>
	<para style="q1">That biteth the horse&#8217;s heels,</para>
	<para style="q1">So that his rider falleth backward.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="18" style="v"/>I have waited for thy salvation, O Jehovah.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="19" style="v"/>Gad, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">gedud</char>, a marauding band.</char></note>a troop <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">gad</char>, to press.</char></note>shall press upon him;</para>
	<para style="q1">But he shall press upon their heel.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="20" style="v"/>Out of Asher his bread shall be fat,</para>
	<para style="q1">And he shall yield royal dainties.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="21" style="v"/>Naphtali is a hind let loose:</para>
	<para style="q1">He giveth goodly words.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="22" style="v"/>Joseph is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">the son of a fruitful tree</char>.</char></note>a fruitful bough,</para>
	<para style="q1">A fruitful bough by a fountain;</para>
	<para style="q1">His <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">daughters</char>.</char></note>branches run over the wall.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="23" style="v"/>The archers have sorely grieved him,</para>
	<para style="q1">And shot at him, and persecuted him:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="24" style="v"/>But his bow abode in strength,</para>
	<para style="q1">And the arms of his hands were made <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">active</char></char></note>strong,</para>
	<para style="q1">By the hands of the Mighty One of Jacob</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">From thence</char>, from <char style="it">the shepherd</char>. Or, as otherwise read, <char style="it">By the name of the shepherd</char></char></note>(From thence is the shepherd, the stone of Israel),</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="25" style="v"/>Even by the God of thy father, who shall help thee,</para>
	<para style="q1">And by the Almighty, who shall bless thee,</para>
	<para style="q1">With blessings of heaven above,</para>
	<para style="q1">Blessings of the deep that coucheth beneath,</para>
	<para style="q1">Blessings of the breasts, and of the womb.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="26" style="v"/>The blessings of thy father</para>
	<para style="q1">Have prevailed above the blessings of my progenitors</para>
	<para style="q1">Unto the utmost bound of the everlasting hills:</para>
	<para style="q1">They shall be on the head of Joseph,</para>
	<para style="q1">And on the crown of the head of him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that is prince among</char></char></note>that was separate from his brethren.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="27" style="v"/>Benjamin is a wolf that raveneth:</para>
	<para style="q1">In the morning he shall devour the prey,</para>
	<para style="q1">And at even he shall divide the spoil.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>All these are the twelve tribes of Israel: and this is it that their father spake unto them and blessed them; every one according to his blessing he blessed them. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And he charged them, and said unto them, I am to be gathered unto my people: bury me with my fathers in the cave that is in the field of Ephron the Hittite, <verse number="30" style="v"/>in the cave that is in the field of Machpelah, which is before Mamre, in the land of Canaan, which Abraham bought with the field from Ephron the Hittite for a possession of a burying-place. <verse number="31" style="v"/>There they buried Abraham and Sarah his wife; there they buried Isaac and Rebekah his wife; and there I buried Leah&#8212;<verse number="32" style="v"/>the field and the cave that is therein, which was purchased from the children of Heth. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And when Jacob made an end of charging his sons, he gathered up his feet into the bed, and yielded up the ghost, and was gathered unto his people.</para>
	<chapter number="50" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Joseph fell upon his father&#8217;s face, and wept upon him, and kissed him. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Joseph commanded his servants the physicians to embalm his father: and the physicians embalmed Israel. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And forty days were fulfilled for him; for so are fulfilled the days of embalming: and the Egyptians wept for him three-score and ten days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>And when the days of weeping for him were past, Joseph spake unto the house of Pharaoh, saying, If now I have found favor in your eyes, speak, I pray you, in the ears of Pharaoh, saying, <verse number="5" style="v"/>My father made me swear, saying, Lo, I die: in my grave which I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">bought</char></char></note>have digged for me in the land of Canaan, there shalt thou bury me. Now therefore let me go up, I pray thee, and bury my father, and I will come again. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Pharaoh said, Go up, and bury thy father, according as he made thee swear. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And Joseph went up to bury his father; and with him went up all the servants of Pharaoh, the elders of his house, and all the elders of the land of Egypt, <verse number="8" style="v"/>and all the house of Joseph, and his brethren, and his father&#8217;s house: only their little ones, and their flocks, and their herds, they left in the land of Goshen. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And there went up with him both chariots and horsemen: and it was a very great company. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And they came to the threshing-floor of Atad, which is beyond the Jordan, and there they lamented with a very great and sore lamentation: and he made a mourning for his father seven days. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And when the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, saw the mourning in the floor of Atad, they said, This is a grievous <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">ebel</char>.</char></note>mourning to the Egyptians: wherefore the name of it was called Abel-mizraim, which is beyond the Jordan. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And his sons did unto him according as he commanded them: <verse number="13" style="v"/>for his sons carried him into the land of Canaan, and buried him in the cave of the field of Machpelah, which Abraham bought with the field, for a possession of a burying-place, of Ephron the Hittite, before Mamre. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Joseph returned into Egypt, he, and his brethren, and all that went up with him to bury his father, after he had buried his father.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And when Joseph&#8217;s brethren saw that their father was dead, they said, It may be that Joseph will hate us, and will fully requite us all the evil which we did unto him. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And they sent a message unto Joseph, saying, Thy father did command before he died, saying, <verse number="17" style="v"/>So shall ye say unto Joseph, Forgive, I pray thee now, the transgression of thy brethren, and their sin, for that they did unto thee evil. And now, we pray thee, forgive the transgression of the servants of the God of thy father. And Joseph wept when they spake unto him. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And his brethren also went and fell down before his face; and they said, Behold, we are thy servants. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto them, Fear not: for am I in the place of God? <verse number="20" style="v"/>And as for you, ye meant evil against me; but God meant it for good, to bring to pass, as it is this day, to save much people alive. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Now therefore fear ye not: I will nourish you, and your little ones. And he comforted them, and spake <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">to their heart</char>.</char></note>kindly unto them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And Joseph dwelt in Egypt, he, and his father&#8217;s house: and Joseph lived a hundred and ten years. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Joseph saw Ephraim&#8217;s children of the third generation: the children also of Machir the son of Manasseh were born upon Joseph&#8217;s knees. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Joseph said unto his brethren, I die; but God will surely visit you, and bring you up out of this land unto the land which he sware to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And Joseph took an oath of the children of Israel, saying, God will surely visit you, and ye shall carry up my bones from hence. <verse number="26" style="v"/>So Joseph died, being a hundred and ten years old: and they embalmed him, and he was put in a coffin in Egypt.</para>
</usx>
