<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="1CH" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Adam, Seth, Enosh, <verse number="2" style="v"/>Kenan, Mahalalel, Jared, <verse number="3" style="v"/>Enoch, Methuselah, Lamech, <verse number="4" style="v"/>Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>The sons of Japheth: Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And the sons of Gomer: Ashkenaz, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 10:3">Gen. 10:3</ref>, <char style="it">Riphath</char>.</char></note>Diphath, and Togarmah. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the sons of Javan: Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 10:4">Gen. 10:4</ref>, <char style="it">Dodanim</char>.</char></note>Rodanim.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>The sons of Ham: Cush, and Mizraim, Put, and Canaan. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the sons of Cush: Seba, and Havilah, and Sabta, and Raama, and Sabteca. And the sons of Raamah: Sheba, and Dedan. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Cush begat Nimrod; he began to be a mighty one in the earth. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Mizraim begat Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim, <verse number="12" style="v"/>and Pathrusim, and Casluhim (from whence came <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Pelishtim</char>.</char></note>the Philistines), and Caphtorim. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Canaan begat Sidon his first-born, and Heth, <verse number="14" style="v"/>and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, and the Girgashite, <verse number="15" style="v"/>and the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite, <verse number="16" style="v"/>and the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>The sons of Shem: Elam, and Asshur, and Arpachshad, and Lud, and Aram, and Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 10:23">Gen. 10:23</ref>, <char style="it">Mash</char>.</char></note>Meshech. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And Arpachshad begat Shelah, and Shelah begat Eber. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And unto Eber were born two sons: the name of the one was Peleg; for in his days the earth was divided; and his brother&#8217;s name was Joktan. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Joktan begat Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah, <verse number="21" style="v"/>and Hadoram, and Uzal, and Diklah, <verse number="22" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 10:28">Gen. 10:28</ref>, <char style="it">Obal</char>.</char></note>Ebal, and Abimael, and Sheba, <verse number="23" style="v"/>and Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab. All these were the sons of Joktan.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>Shem, Arpachshad, Shelah, <verse number="25" style="v"/>Eber, Peleg, Reu, <verse number="26" style="v"/>Serug, Nahor, Terah, <verse number="27" style="v"/>Abram (the same is Abraham).</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>The sons of Abraham: Isaac, and Ishmael. <verse number="29" style="v"/>These are their generations: the first-born of Ishmael, Nebaioth; then Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam, <verse number="30" style="v"/>Mishma, and Dumah, Massa, Hadad, and Tema, <verse number="31" style="v"/>Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah. These are the sons of Ishmael.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v"/>And the sons of Keturah, Abraham&#8217;s concubine: she bare Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. And the sons of Jokshan: Sheba, and Dedan. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And the sons of Midian: Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abida, and Eldaah. All these were the sons of Keturah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v"/>And Abraham begat Isaac. The sons of Isaac: Esau, and Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v"/>The sons of Esau: Eliphaz, Reuel, and Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah. <verse number="36" style="v"/>The sons of Eliphaz: Teman, and Omar, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:11">Gen. 36:11</ref>, <char style="it">Zepho</char>.</char></note>Zephi, and Gatam, Kenaz, and Timna, and Amalek. <verse number="37" style="v"/>The sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v"/>And the sons of Seir: Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, and Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And the sons of Lotan: Hori, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:22">Gen. 36:22</ref>, <char style="it">Hemam</char>.</char></note>Homam; and Timna was Lotan&#8217;s sister. <verse number="40" style="v"/>The sons of Shobal: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:23">Gen. 36:23</ref>, <char style="it">Alvan</char>.</char></note>Alian, and Manahath, and Ebal, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:23">Gen. 36:23</ref>, <char style="it">Shepho</char>.</char></note>Shephi, and Onam. And the sons of Zibeon: Aiah, and Anah. <verse number="41" style="v"/>The sons of Anah: Dishon. And the sons of Dishon: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:26">Gen. 36:26</ref>, <char style="it">Hemdan</char>.</char></note>Hamran, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Cheran. <verse number="42" style="v"/>The sons of Ezer: Bilhan, and Zaavan, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:27">Gen. 36:27</ref>, <char style="it">and Akan</char>.</char></note>Jaakan. The sons of Dishan: Uz, and Aran.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v"/>Now these are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom, before there reigned any king over the children of Israel: Bela the son of Beor; and the name of his city was Dinhabah. <verse number="44" style="v"/>And Bela died, and Jobab the son of Zerah of Bozrah reigned in his stead. <verse number="45" style="v"/>And Jobab died, and Husham of the land of the Temanites reigned in his stead. <verse number="46" style="v"/>And Husham died, and Hadad the son of Bedad, who smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead; and the name of his city was Avith. <verse number="47" style="v"/>And Hadad died, and Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead. <verse number="48" style="v"/>And Samlah died, and Shaul of Rehoboth by the River reigned in his stead. <verse number="49" style="v"/>And Shaul died, and Baal-hanan the son of Achbor reigned in his stead. <verse number="50" style="v"/>And Baal-hanan died, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:39">Gen. 36:39</ref>, <char style="it">Hadar</char>.</char></note>Hadad reigned in his stead; and the name of his city was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:39">Gen. 36:39</ref>, <char style="it">Pau</char>.</char></note>Pai: and his wife&#8217;s name was Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Me-zahab. <verse number="51" style="v"/>And Hadad died.</para>
	<para style="p">And the chiefs of Edom were: chief Timna, chief <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 36:40">Gen. 36:40</ref>, <char style="it">Alvah</char>.</char></note>Aliah, chief Jetheth, <verse number="52" style="v"/>chief Oholibamah, chief Elah, chief Pinon, <verse number="53" style="v"/>chief Kenaz, chief Teman, chief Mibzar, <verse number="54" style="v"/>chief Magdiel, chief Iram. These are the chiefs of Edom.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>These are the sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun, <verse number="2" style="v"/>Dan, Joseph, and Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>The sons of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah; which three were born unto him of Shua&#8217;s daughter the Canaanitess. And Er, Judah&#8217;s first-born, was wicked in the sight of Jehovah; and he slew him. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Tamar his daughter-in-law bare him Perez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah were five.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>The sons of Perez: Hezron, and Hamul. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And the sons of Zerah: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="JOS 7:1">Josh. 7:1</ref>, <char style="it">Zabdi</char>.</char></note>Zimri, and Ethan, and Heman, and Calcol, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1KI 4:31">1 Kin. 4:31</ref>, <char style="it">Darda</char>.</char></note>Dara; five of them in all. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the sons of Carmi: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="JOS 7:1">Josh. 7:1</ref>, <char style="it">Achan</char>.</char></note>Achar, the troubler of Israel, who committed a trespass in the devoted thing. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And the sons of Ethan: Azariah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>The sons also of Hezron, that were born unto him: Jerahmeel, and Ram, and Chelubai. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Ram begat Amminadab, and Amminadab begat Nahshon, prince of the children of Judah; <verse number="11" style="v"/>and Nahshon begat Salma, and Salma begat Boaz, <verse number="12" style="v"/>and Boaz begat Obed, and Obed begat Jesse; <verse number="13" style="v"/>and Jesse begat his first-born Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and Shimea the third, <verse number="14" style="v"/>Nethanel the fourth, Raddai the fifth, <verse number="15" style="v"/>Ozem the sixth, David the seventh; <verse number="16" style="v"/>and their sisters were Zeruiah and Abigail. And the sons of Zeruiah: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Abshai</char>.</char></note>Abishai, and Joab, and Asahel, three. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Abigail bare Amasa; and the father of Amasa was Jether the Ishmaelite.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Caleb the son of Hezron begat <char style="add">children</char> of Azubah <char style="add">his</char> wife, and of Jerioth; and these were her sons: Jesher, and Shobab, and Ardon. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Azubah died, and Caleb took unto him Ephrath, who bare him Hur. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Hur begat Uri, and Uri begat Bezalel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>And afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Machir the father of Gilead, whom he took <char style="add">to wife</char> when he was threescore years old; and she bare him Segub. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Segub begat Jair, who had three and twenty cities in the land of Gilead. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Geshur and Aram took <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Havvoth-jair</char></char></note>the towns of Jair from them, with Kenath, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">daughters</char>.</char></note>villages thereof, even threescore cities. All these were the sons of Machir the father of Gilead. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And after that Hezron was dead in Caleb-ephrathah, then Abijah Hezron&#8217;s wife bare him Ashhur the father of Tekoa.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And the sons of Jerahmeel the first-born of Hezron were Ram the first-born, and Bunah, and Oren, and Ozem, Ahijah. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And Jerahmeel had another wife, whose name was Atarah; she was the mother of Onam. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And the sons of Ram the first-born of Jerahmeel were Maaz, and Jamin, and Eker. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And the sons of Onam were Shammai, and Jada. And the sons of Shammai: Nadab, and Abishur. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And the name of the wife of Abishur was Abihail; and she bare him Ahban, and Molid. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And the sons of Nadab: Seled, and Appaim; but Seled died without <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sons</char></char></note>children. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And the sons of Appaim: Ishi. And the sons of Ishi: Sheshan. And the sons of Sheshan: Ahlai. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And the sons of Jada the brother of Shammai: Jether, and Jonathan; and Jether died without <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sons</char></char></note>children. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And the sons of Jonathan: Peleth, and Zaza. These were the sons of Jerahmeel. <verse number="34" style="v"/>Now Sheshan had no sons, but daughters. And Sheshan had a servant, an Egyptian, whose name was Jarha. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his servant to wife; and she bare him Attai. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And Attai begat Nathan, and Nathan begat Zabad, <verse number="37" style="v"/>and Zabad begat Ephlal, and Ephlal begat Obed, <verse number="38" style="v"/>and Obed begat Jehu, and Jehu begat Azariah, <verse number="39" style="v"/>and Azariah begat Helez, and Helez begat Eleasah, <verse number="40" style="v"/>and Eleasah begat Sismai, and Sismai begat Shallum, <verse number="41" style="v"/>and Shallum begat Jekamiah, and Jekamiah begat Elishama.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v"/>And the sons of Caleb the brother of Jerahmeel were Mesha his first-born, who was the father of Ziph; and the sons of Mareshah the father of Hebron. <verse number="43" style="v"/>And the sons of Hebron: Korah, and Tappuah, and Rekem, and Shema. <verse number="44" style="v"/>And Shema begat Raham, the father of Jorkeam; and Rekem begat Shammai. <verse number="45" style="v"/>And the son of Shammai was Maon; and Maon was the father of Beth-zur. <verse number="46" style="v"/>And Ephah, Caleb&#8217;s concubine, bare Haran, and Moza, and Gazez; and Haran begat Gazez. <verse number="47" style="v"/>And the sons of Jahdai: Regem, and Jothan, and Geshan, and Pelet, and Ephah, and Shaaph. <verse number="48" style="v"/>Maacah, Caleb&#8217;s concubine, bare Sheber and Tirhanah. <verse number="49" style="v"/>She bare also Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Machbena, and the father of Gibea; and the daughter of Caleb was Achsah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v"/>These were the sons of Caleb, the son of Hur, the first-born of Ephrathah: Shobal the father of Kiriath-jearim, <verse number="51" style="v"/>Salma the father of Beth-lehem, Hareph the father of Beth-gader. <verse number="52" style="v"/>And Shobal the father of Kiriath-jearim had sons: Haroeh, half of the Menuhoth. <verse number="53" style="v"/>And the families of Kiriath-jearim: The Ithrites, and the Puthites, and the Shumathites, and the Mishraites; of them came the Zorathites and the Eshtaolites. <verse number="54" style="v"/>The sons of Salma: Beth-lehem, and the Netophathites, Atroth-beth-joab, and half of the Manahathites, the Zorites. <verse number="55" style="v"/>And the families of scribes that dwelt at Jabez: the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, the Sucathites. These are the Kenites that came of Hammath, the father of the house of Rechab.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now these were the sons of David, that were born unto him in Hebron: the first-born, Amnon, of Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; the second, Daniel, of Abigail the Carmelitess; <verse number="2" style="v"/>the third, Absalom the son of Maacah the daughter of Talmai king of Geshur; the fourth, Adonijah the son of Haggith; <verse number="3" style="v"/>the fifth, Shephatiah of Abital; the sixth, Ithream by Eglah his wife: <verse number="4" style="v"/>six were born unto him in Hebron; and there he reigned seven years and six months. And in Jerusalem he reigned thirty and three years; <verse number="5" style="v"/>and these were born unto him in Jerusalem: Shimea, and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon, four, of Bath-shua the daughter of Ammiel; <verse number="6" style="v"/>and Ibhar, and Elishama, and Eliphelet, <verse number="7" style="v"/>and Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia, <verse number="8" style="v"/>and Elishama, and Eliada, and Eliphelet, nine. <verse number="9" style="v"/>All these were the sons of David, besides the sons of the concubines; and Tamar was their sister.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And Solomon&#8217;s son was Rehoboam, Abijah his son, Asa his son, Jehoshaphat his son, <verse number="11" style="v"/>Joram his son, Ahaziah his son, Joash his son, <verse number="12" style="v"/>Amaziah his son, Azariah his son, Jotham his son, <verse number="13" style="v"/>Ahaz his son, Hezekiah his son, Manasseh his son, <verse number="14" style="v"/>Amon his son, Josiah his son. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the sons of Josiah: the first-born Johanan, the second Jehoiakim, the third Zedekiah, the fourth Shallum. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the sons of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah his son, Zedekiah his son. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the sons of Jeconiah, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Assir</char></char></note>the captive: Shealtiel his son, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and Malchiram, and Pedaiah, and Shenazzar, Jekamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the sons of Pedaiah: Zerubbabel, and Shimei. And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">son</char>.</char></note>sons of Zerubbabel: Meshullam, and Hananiah; and Shelomith was their sister; <verse number="20" style="v"/>and Hashubah, and Ohel, and Berechiah, and Hasadiah, Jushab-hesed, five. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">son</char>.</char></note>sons of Hananiah: Pelatiah, and Jeshaiah; the sons of Rephaiah, the sons of Arnan, the sons of Obadiah, the sons of Shecaniah. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the sons of Shecaniah: Shemaiah. And the sons of Shemaiah: Hattush, and Igal, and Bariah, and Neariah, and Shaphat, six. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">son</char>.</char></note>sons of Neariah: Elioenai, and Hizkiah, and Azrikam, three. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And the sons of Elioenai: Hodaviah, and Eliashib, and Pelaiah, and Akkub, and Johanan, and Delaiah, and Anani, seven.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>The sons of Judah: Perez, Hezron, and Carmi, and Hur, and Shobal. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Reaiah the son of Shobal begat Jahath; and Jahath begat Ahumai and Lahad. These are the families of the Zorathites. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And these were <char style="add">the sons of</char> the father of Etam: Jezreel, and Ishma, and Idbash; and the name of their sister was Hazzelelponi; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and Penuel the father of Gedor, and Ezer the father of Hushah. These are the sons of Hur, the first-born of Ephrathah, the father of Beth-lehem. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Ashhur the father of Tekoa had two wives, Helah and Naarah. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Naarah bare him Ahuzzam, and Hepher, and Temeni, and Haahashtari. These were the sons of Naarah. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the sons of Helah were Zereth, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Another reading is, <char style="it">and Zohar</char>.</char></note>Izhar, and Ethnan. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Hakkoz begat Anub, and Zobebah, and the families of Aharhel the son of Harum. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Jabez was more honorable than his brethren: and his mother called his name Jabez, saying, Because I bare him with sorrow. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Jabez called on the God of Israel, saying, Oh that thou wouldest bless me indeed, and enlarge my border, and that thy hand might be with me, and that thou wouldest keep me from evil, that it be not to my sorrow! And God granted him that which he requested. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Chelub the brother of Shuhah begat Mehir, who was the father of Eshton. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And Eshton begat Beth-rapha, and Paseah, and Tehinnah the father of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the city of Nahash</char></char></note>Ir-nahash. These are the men of Recah. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And the sons of Kenaz: Othniel, and Seraiah. And the sons of Othniel: Hathath. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Meonothai begat Ophrah: and Seraiah begat Joab the father of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the valley of craftsmen</char></char></note>Ge-harashim; for they were craftsmen. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the sons of Caleb the son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam; and the sons of Elah; and Kenaz. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the sons of Jehallelel: Ziph, and Ziphah, Tiria, and Asarel. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the sons of Ezrah: Jether, and Mered, and Epher, and Jalon; and she bare Miriam, and Shammai, and Ishbah the father of Eshtemoa. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And his wife <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Ha-jehudijah</char></char></note>the Jewess bare Jered the father of Gedor, and Heber the father of Soco, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. And these are the sons of Bithiah the daughter of Pharaoh, whom Mered took. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the sons of the wife of Hodiah, the sister of Naham, were the father of Keilah the Garmite, and Eshtemoa the Maacathite. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the sons of Shimon: Amnon, and Rinnah, Ben-hanan, and Tilon. And the sons of Ishi: Zoheth, and Ben-zoheth. <verse number="21" style="v"/>The sons of Shelah the son of Judah: Er the father of Lecah, and Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of them that wrought fine linen, of the house of Ashbea; <verse number="22" style="v"/>and Jokim, and the men of Cozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who had dominion in Moab, and Jashubi-lehem. And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">words</char>.</char></note>records are ancient. <verse number="23" style="v"/>These were the potters, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">those that dwelt among plantations and hedges</char></char></note>the inhabitants of Netaim and Gederah: there they dwelt with the king for his work.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>The sons of Simeon: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 46:10">Gen. 46:10</ref>; <ref loc="EXO 6:15">Ex. 6:15</ref>, <char style="it">Jemuel</char></char></note>Nemuel, and Jamin, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 46:10">Gen. 46:10</ref>, <char style="it">Jachin</char>.</char></note>Jarib, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 46:10">Gen. 46:10</ref>, <char style="it">Zohar</char>.</char></note>Zerah, Shaul; <verse number="25" style="v"/>Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And the sons of Mishma: Hammuel his son, Zaccur his son, Shimei his son. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters; but his brethren had not many children, neither did all their family multiply like to the children of Judah. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And they dwelt at Beer-sheba, and Moladah, and Hazar-shual, <verse number="29" style="v"/>and at Bilhah, and at Ezem, and at Tolad, <verse number="30" style="v"/>and at Bethuel, and at Hormah, and at Ziklag, <verse number="31" style="v"/>and at Beth-marcaboth, and Hazar-susim, and at Beth-biri, and at Shaaraim. These were their cities unto the reign of David. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And their villages were Etam, and Ain, Rimmon, and Tochen, and Ashan, five cities; <verse number="33" style="v"/>and all their villages that were round about the same cities, unto Baal. These were their habitations, and they have their genealogy. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And Meshobab, and Jamlech, and Joshah the son of Amaziah, <verse number="35" style="v"/>and Joel, and Jehu the son of Joshibiah, the son of Seraiah, the son of Asiel, <verse number="36" style="v"/>and Elioenai, and Jaakobah, and Jeshohaiah, and Asaiah, and Adiel, and Jesimiel, and Benaiah, <verse number="37" style="v"/>and Ziza the son of Shiphi, the son of Allon, the son of Jedaiah, the son of Shimri, the son of Shemaiah&#8212;<verse number="38" style="v"/>these mentioned by name were princes in their families: and their fathers&#8217; houses increased greatly. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And they went to the entrance of Gedor, even unto the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And they found fat pasture and good, and the land was wide, and quiet, and peaceable; for they that dwelt there aforetime were of Ham. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And these written by name came in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah, and smote their tents, and the Meunim that were found there, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">devoted them</char>.</char></note>destroyed them utterly unto this day, and dwelt in their stead; because there was pasture there for their flocks. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And some of them, even of the sons of Simeon, five hundred men, went to mount Seir, having for their captains Pelatiah, and Neariah, and Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi. <verse number="43" style="v"/>And they smote the remnant of the Amalekites that escaped, and have dwelt there unto this day.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the sons of Reuben the first-born of Israel (for he was the first-born; but, forasmuch as he defiled his father&#8217;s couch, his birthright was given unto the sons of Joseph the son of Israel; and the genealogy is not to be reckoned after the birthright. <verse number="2" style="v"/>For Judah prevailed above his brethren, and of him came the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">leader</char></char></note>prince; but the birthright was Joseph&#8217;s), <verse number="3" style="v"/>the sons of Reuben the first-born of Israel: Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi. <verse number="4" style="v"/>The sons of Joel: Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son, <verse number="5" style="v"/>Micah his son, Reaiah his son, Baal his son, <verse number="6" style="v"/>Beerah his son, whom <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2KI 15:29">2 Kin. 15:29</ref>; <ref loc="2KI 16:7">16:7</ref>, <char style="it">Tiglath-pileser</char></char></note>Tilgath-pilneser king of Assyria carried away captive: he was prince of the Reubenites. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And his brethren by their families, when the genealogy of their generations was reckoned: the chief, Jeiel, and Zechariah, <verse number="8" style="v"/>and Bela the son of Azaz, the son of Shema, the son of Joel, who dwelt in Aroer, even unto Nebo and Baal-meon: <verse number="9" style="v"/>and eastward he dwelt even unto the entrance of the wilderness from the river Euphrates, because their cattle were multiplied in the land of Gilead. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And in the days of Saul, they made war with the Hagrites, who fell by their hand; and they dwelt in their tents throughout all the <char style="add">land</char> east of Gilead.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And the sons of Gad dwelt over against them, in the land of Bashan unto Salecah: <verse number="12" style="v"/>Joel the chief, and Shapham the second, and Janai, and Shaphat in Bashan. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And their brethren of their fathers&#8217; houses: Michael, and Meshullam, and Sheba, and Jorai, and Jacan, and Zia, and Eber, seven. <verse number="14" style="v"/>These were the sons of Abihail, the son of Huri, the son of Jaroah, the son of Gilead, the son of Michael, the son of Jeshishai, the son of Jahdo, the son of Buz; <verse number="15" style="v"/>Ahi the son of Abdiel, the son of Guni, chief of their fathers&#8217; houses. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And they dwelt in Gilead in Bashan, and in its <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">daughters</char>.</char></note>towns, and in all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pasture lands</char></char></note>suburbs of Sharon, as far as their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">goings forth</char>.</char></note>borders. <verse number="17" style="v"/>All these were reckoned by genealogies in the days of Jotham king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam king of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>The sons of Reuben, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, of valiant men, men able to bear buckler and sword, and to shoot with bow, and skilful in war, were forty and four thousand seven hundred and threescore, that were able to go forth to war. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And they made war with the Hagrites, with Jetur, and Naphish, and Nodab. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And they were helped against them, and the Hagrites were delivered into their hand, and all that were with them; for they cried to God in the battle, and he was entreated of them, because they put their trust in him. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And they took away their cattle; of their camels fifty thousand, and of sheep two hundred and fifty thousand, and of asses two thousand, and of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">souls of men</char>.</char></note>men a hundred thousand. <verse number="22" style="v"/>For there fell many slain, because the war was of God. And they dwelt in their stead until the captivity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>And the children of the half-tribe of Manasseh dwelt in the land: they increased from Bashan unto Baal-hermon and Senir and mount Hermon. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And these were the heads of their fathers&#8217; houses: even Epher, and Ishi, and Eliel, and Azriel, and Jeremiah, and Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, mighty men of valor, famous men, heads of their fathers&#8217; houses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And they trespassed against the God of their fathers, and played the harlot after the gods of the peoples of the land, whom God destroyed before them. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tilgath-pilneser king of Assyria, and he carried them away, even the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, and brought them unto Halah, and Habor, and Hara, and to the river of Gozan, unto this day.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>The sons of Levi: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:16">verse 16</ref>, <char style="it">Gershom</char>.</char></note>Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And the children of Amram: Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam. And the sons of Aaron: Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Eleazar begat Phinehas, Phinehas begat Abishua, <verse number="5" style="v"/>and Abishua begat Bukki, and Bukki begat Uzzi, <verse number="6" style="v"/>and Uzzi begat Zerahiah, and Zerahiah begat Meraioth, <verse number="7" style="v"/>Meraioth begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub, <verse number="8" style="v"/>and Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Ahimaaz, <verse number="9" style="v"/>and Ahimaaz begat Azariah, and Azariah begat Johanan, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and Johanan begat Azariah (he it is that executed the priest&#8217;s office in the house that Solomon built in Jerusalem), <verse number="11" style="v"/>and Azariah begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub, <verse number="12" style="v"/>and Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 9:11">9:11</ref>, <char style="it">Meshullam</char>.</char></note>Shallum, <verse number="13" style="v"/>and Shallum begat Hilkiah, and Hilkiah begat Azariah, <verse number="14" style="v"/>and Azariah begat Seraiah, and Seraiah begat Jehozadak; <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Jehozadak went <char style="add">into captivity</char>, when Jehovah carried away Judah and Jerusalem by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>The sons of Levi: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:1">verse 1</ref>, <char style="it">Gershon</char>.</char></note>Gershom, Kohath, and Merari. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And these are the names of the sons of Gershom: Libni and Shimei. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the sons of Kohath were Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel. <verse number="19" style="v"/>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. And these are the families of the Levites according to their fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char>. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Of Gershom: Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son, <verse number="21" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:42">verse 42</ref>, <char style="it">Ethan</char>.</char></note>Joah his son, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:41">verse 41</ref>, <char style="it">Adaiah</char>.</char></note>Iddo his son, Zerah his son, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:41">verse 41</ref>, <char style="it">Ethni</char>.</char></note>Jeatherai his son. <verse number="22" style="v"/>The sons of Kohath: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In verses <ref loc="1CH 6:2">2</ref>, <ref loc="1CH 6:18">18</ref>, <ref loc="1CH 6:38">38</ref> <char style="it">Izhar</char></char></note>Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son, <verse number="23" style="v"/>Elkanah his son, and Ebiasaph his son, and Assir his son, <verse number="24" style="v"/>Tahath his son, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:36">verse 36</ref>, <char style="it">Zephaniah, Azariah, Joel</char>.</char></note>Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And the sons of Elkanah: Amasai, and Ahimoth. <verse number="26" style="v"/>As for Elkanah, the sons of Elkanah: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:35">verse 35</ref>, <char style="it">Zuph</char>.</char></note>Zophai his son, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:34">verse 34</ref>, <char style="it">Toah</char>.</char></note>Nahath his son, <verse number="27" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:34">verse 34</ref>, <char style="it">Eliel</char>.</char></note>Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, Elkanah his son. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And the sons of Samuel: the first-born, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See <ref loc="1CH 6:33">verse 33</ref> and <ref loc="1SA 8:2">1 Sam. 8:2</ref>. The Hebrew text has <char style="it">Vashni, and Abiah</char>.</char></note><char style="add">Joel</char>, and the second Abijah. <verse number="29" style="v"/>The sons of Merari: Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzzah his son, <verse number="30" style="v"/>Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, Asaiah his son.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>And these are they whom David set over the service of song in the house of Jehovah, after that the ark had rest. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And they ministered with song before the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, until Solomon had built the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem: and they <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">stood</char>.</char></note>waited on their office according to their order. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And these are they that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">stood</char>.</char></note>waited, and their sons. Of the sons of the Kohathites: Heman the singer, the son of Joel, the son of Samuel, <verse number="34" style="v"/>the son of Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Eliel, the son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:26">verse 26</ref>, <char style="it">Nahath</char>.</char></note>Toah, <verse number="35" style="v"/>the son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:26">verse 26</ref>, <char style="it">Zophai</char>.</char></note>Zuph, the son of Elkanah, the son of Mahath, the son of Amasai, <verse number="36" style="v"/>the son of Elkanah, the son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:24">verse 24</ref>, <char style="it">Shaul, Uzziah, Uriel</char>.</char></note>Joel, the son of Azariah, the son of Zephaniah, <verse number="37" style="v"/>the son of Tahath, the son of Assir, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, <verse number="38" style="v"/>the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, the son of Israel. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And his brother Asaph, who stood on his right hand, even Asaph the son of Berechiah, the son of Shimea, <verse number="40" style="v"/>the son of Michael, the son of Baaseiah, the son of Malchijah, <verse number="41" style="v"/>the son of Ethni, the son of Zerah, the son of Adaiah, <verse number="42" style="v"/>the son of Ethan, the son of Zimmah, the son of Shimei, <verse number="43" style="v"/>the son of Jahath, the son of Gershom, the son of Levi. <verse number="44" style="v"/>And on the left hand their brethren the sons of Merari: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 9:16">9:16</ref>, <char style="it">Jeduthun</char>.</char></note>Ethan the son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 15:17">15:17</ref>, <char style="it">Kushaiah</char>.</char></note>Kishi, the son of Abdi, the son of Malluch, <verse number="45" style="v"/>the son of Hashabiah, the son of Amaziah, the son of Hilkiah, <verse number="46" style="v"/>the son of Amzi, the son of Bani, the son of Shemer, <verse number="47" style="v"/>the son of Mahli, the son of Mushi, the son of Merari, the son of Levi. <verse number="48" style="v"/>And their brethren the Levites were <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">given</char>. See <ref loc="NUM 3:9">Num. 3:9</ref>.</char></note>appointed for all the service of the tabernacle of the house of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v"/>But Aaron and his sons <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">burnt incense</char></char></note>offered upon the altar of burnt-offering, and upon the altar of incense, for all the work of the most holy place, and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God had commanded. <verse number="50" style="v"/>And these are the sons of Aaron: Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son, <verse number="51" style="v"/>Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son, <verse number="52" style="v"/>Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son, <verse number="53" style="v"/>Zadok his son, Ahimaaz his son.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v"/>Now these are their dwelling-places according to their encampments in their borders: to the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites (for theirs was the <char style="add">first</char> lot), <verse number="55" style="v"/>to them they gave Hebron in the land of Judah, and the suburbs thereof round about it; <verse number="56" style="v"/>but the fields of the city, and the villages thereof, they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh. <verse number="57" style="v"/>And to the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge, Hebron; Libnah also with its suburbs, and Jattir, and Eshtemoa with its suburbs, <verse number="58" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="JOS 21:15">Josh. 21:15</ref>, <char style="it">Holon</char>.</char></note>Hilen with its suburbs, Debir with its suburbs, <verse number="59" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="JOS 21:16">Josh. 21:16</ref>, <char style="it">Ain</char>.</char></note>Ashan with its suburbs, and Beth-shemesh with its suburbs; <verse number="60" style="v"/>and out of the tribe of Benjamin, Geba with its suburbs, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="JOS 21:18">Josh. 21:18</ref>, <char style="it">Almon</char>.</char></note>Allemeth with its suburbs, and Anathoth with its suburbs. All their cities throughout their families were thirteen cities.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="61" style="v"/>And unto the rest of the sons of Kohath <char style="add">were given</char> by lot, out of the family of the tribe, out of the half-tribe, the half of Manasseh, ten cities. <verse number="62" style="v"/>And to the sons of Gershom, according to their families, out of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities. <verse number="63" style="v"/>Unto the sons of Merari <char style="add">were given</char> by lot, according to their families, out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities. <verse number="64" style="v"/>And the children of Israel gave to the Levites the cities with their suburbs. <verse number="65" style="v"/>And they gave by lot out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, and out of the tribe of the children of Benjamin, these cities which are mentioned by name.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="66" style="v"/>And some of the families of the sons of Kohath had cities of their borders out of the tribe of Ephraim. <verse number="67" style="v"/>And they gave unto them the cities of refuge, Shechem in the hill-country of Ephraim with its suburbs; Gezer also with its suburbs, <verse number="68" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See <ref loc="JOS 21:22-21:29">Josh. 21:22&#8211;29</ref> where some of the names are different.</char></note>and Jokmeam with its suburbs, and Beth-horon with its suburbs, <verse number="69" style="v"/>and Aijalon with its suburbs, and Gath-rimmon with its suburbs; <verse number="70" style="v"/>and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Aner with its suburbs, and Bileam with its suburbs, for the rest of the family of the sons of Kohath.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="71" style="v"/>Unto the sons of Gershom <char style="add">were given</char>, out of the family of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with its suburbs, and Ashtaroth with its suburbs; <verse number="72" style="v"/>and out of the tribe of Issachar, Kedesh with its suburbs, Daberath with its suburbs, <verse number="73" style="v"/>and Ramoth with its suburbs, and Anem with its suburbs; <verse number="74" style="v"/>and out of the tribe of Asher, Mashal with its suburbs, and Abdon with its suburbs, <verse number="75" style="v"/>and Hukok with its suburbs, and Rehob with its suburbs; <verse number="76" style="v"/>and out of the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with its suburbs, and Hammon with its suburbs, and Kiriathaim with its suburbs.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="77" style="v"/>Unto the rest of <char style="add">the Levites</char>, the sons of Merari, <char style="add">were given</char>, out of the tribe of Zebulun, Rimmono with its suburbs, Tabor with its suburbs; <verse number="78" style="v"/>and beyond the Jordan at Jericho, on the east side of the Jordan, <char style="add">were given them</char>, out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness with its suburbs, and Jahzah with its suburbs, <verse number="79" style="v"/>and Kedemoth with its suburbs, and Mephaath with its suburbs; <verse number="80" style="v"/>and out of the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with its suburbs, and Mahanaim with its suburbs, <verse number="81" style="v"/>and Heshbon with its suburbs, and Jazer with its suburbs.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And of the sons of Issachar: Tola, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 46:13">Gen. 46:13</ref>, <char style="it">Puvah and Iob</char>.</char></note>Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the sons of Tola: Uzzi, and Rephaiah, and Jeriel, and Jahmai, and Ibsam, and Shemuel, heads of their fathers&#8217; houses, <char style="add">to wit</char>, of Tola; mighty men of valor in their generations: their number in the days of David was two and twenty thousand and six hundred. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And the sons of Uzzi: Izrahiah. And the sons of Izrahiah: Michael, and Obadiah, and Joel, Isshiah, five; all of them chief men. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And with them, by their generations, after their fathers&#8217; houses, were bands of the host for war, six and thirty thousand; for they had many wives and sons. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And their brethren among all the families of Issachar, mighty men of valor, reckoned in all by genealogy, were fourscore and seven thousand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/><char style="add">The sons of</char> Benjamin: Bela, and Becher, and Jediael, three. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the sons of Bela: Ezbon, and Uzzi, and Uzziel, and Jerimoth, and Iri, five; heads of fathers&#8217; houses, mighty men of valor; and they were reckoned by genealogy twenty and two thousand and thirty and four. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And the sons of Becher: Zemirah, and Joash, and Eliezer, and Elioenai, and Omri, and Jeremoth, and Abijah, and Anathoth, and Alemeth. All these were the sons of Becher. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And they were reckoned by genealogy, after their generations, heads of their fathers&#8217; houses, mighty men of valor, twenty thousand and two hundred. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And the sons of Jediael: Bilhan. And the sons of Bilhan: Jeush, and Benjamin, and Ehud, and Chenaanah, and Zethan, and Tarshish, and Ahishahar. <verse number="11" style="v"/>All these were sons of Jediael, according to the heads of their fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char>, mighty men of valor, seventeen thousand and two hundred, that were able to go forth in the host for war. <verse number="12" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:39">Num. 26:39</ref>, <char style="it">Shephupham</char> and <char style="it">Hupham</char></char></note>Shuppim also, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:39">Num. 26:39</ref>, <char style="it">Shephupham</char> and <char style="it">Hupham</char></char></note>Huppim, the sons of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 7:7">verse 7</ref>, <char style="it">Iri</char>.</char></note>Ir, Hushim, the sons of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:38">Num. 26:38</ref>, <char style="it">Ahiram</char>.</char></note>Aher.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>The sons of Naphtali: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 46:24">Gen. 46:24</ref>, <char style="it">Jahzeel</char>.</char></note>Jahziel, and Guni, and Jezer, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 46:24">Gen. 46:24</ref>, <char style="it">Shillem</char>.</char></note>Shallum, the sons of Bilhah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>The sons of Manasseh: Asriel, whom his concubine the Aramitess bare; she bare Machir the father of Gilead. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Machir took a wife <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for</char></char></note>of Huppim and Shuppim, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and his</char></char></note>whose sister&#8217;s name was Maacah; and the name of the second was Zelophehad: and Zelophehad had daughters. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Maacah the wife of Machir bare a son, and she called his name Peresh; and the name of his brother was Sheresh; and his sons were Ulam and Rakem. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the sons of Ulam: Bedan. These were the sons of Gilead the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And his sister Hammolecheth bare Ishhod, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:30">Num. 26:30</ref>, <char style="it">Iezer</char>.</char></note>Abiezer, and Mahlah. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the sons of Shemida were Ahian, and Shechem, and Likhi, and Aniam.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And the sons of Ephraim: Shuthelah, and Bered his son, and Tahath his son, and Eleadah his son, and Tahath his son, <verse number="21" style="v"/>and Zabad his son, and Shuthelah his son, and Ezer, and Elead, whom the men of Gath that were born in the land slew, because they came down to take away their cattle. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Ephraim their father mourned many days, and his brethren came to comfort him. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he went in to his wife, and she conceived, and bare a son, and he called his name Beriah, because it went evil with his house. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And his daughter was Sheerah, who built Beth-horon the nether and the upper, and Uzzen-sheerah. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And Rephah was his son, and Resheph, and Telah his son, and Tahan his son, <verse number="26" style="v"/>Ladan his son, Ammihud his son, Elishama his son, <verse number="27" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Non</char>.</char></note>Nun his son, Joshua his son.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And their possessions and habitations were Beth-el and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">daughters</char>.</char></note>towns thereof, and eastward <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="JOS 16:7">Josh. 16:7</ref>, <char style="it">Naarah</char>.</char></note>Naaran, and westward Gezer, with the towns thereof; Shechem also and the towns thereof, unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many manuscripts read, <char style="it">Ayyah</char></char></note>Azzah and the towns thereof; <verse number="29" style="v"/>and by the borders of the children of Manasseh, Beth-shean and its towns, Taanach and its towns, Megiddo and its towns, Dor and its towns. In these dwelt the children of Joseph the son of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>The sons of Asher: Imnah, and Ishvah, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah their sister. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And the sons of Beriah: Heber, and Malchiel, who was the father of Birzaith. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And Heber begat Japhlet, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 7:34">verse 34</ref>, <char style="it">Shemer</char>.</char></note>Shomer, and Hotham, and Shua their sister. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And the sons of Japhlet: Pasach, and Bimhal, and Ashvath. These are the children of Japhlet. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And the sons of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 7:32">verse 32</ref>, <char style="it">Shomer</char>.</char></note>Shemer: Ahi, and Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">son</char>.</char></note>sons of Helem his brother: Zophah, and Imna, and Shelesh, and Amal. <verse number="36" style="v"/>The sons of Zophah: Suah, and Harnepher, and Shual, and Beri, and Imrah, <verse number="37" style="v"/>Bezer, and Hod, and Shamma, and Shilshah, and Ithran, and Beera. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And the sons of Jether: Jephunneh, and Pispa, and Ara. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And the sons of Ulla: Arah, and Hanniel, and Rizia. <verse number="40" style="v"/>All these were the children of Asher, heads of the fathers&#8217; houses, choice and mighty men of valor, chief of the princes. And the number of them reckoned by genealogy for service in war was twenty and six thousand men.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Benjamin begat Bela his first-born, Ashbel the second, and Aharah the third, <verse number="2" style="v"/>Nohah the fourth, and Rapha the fifth. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Bela had sons: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="GEN 46:21">Gen. 46:21</ref>, <char style="it">Ard</char>.</char></note>Addar, and Gera, and Abihud, <verse number="4" style="v"/>and Abishua, and Naaman, and Ahoah, <verse number="5" style="v"/>and Gera, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NUM 26:39">Num. 26:39</ref>, <char style="it">Shephupham</char>.</char></note>Shephuphan, and Huram. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And these are the sons of Ehud: these are the heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of the inhabitants of Geba, and they carried them captive to Manahath: <verse number="7" style="v"/>and Naaman, and Ahijah, and Gera, he carried them captive; and he begat Uzza and Ahihud. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Shaharaim begat children in the field of Moab, after he had <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sent away Hushim and Baara his wives</char></char></note>sent them away; Hushim and Baara were his wives. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And he begat of Hodesh his wife, Jobab, and Zibia, and Mesha, and Malcam, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and Jeuz, and Shachia, and Mirmah. These were his sons, heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char>. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And of Hushim he begat Abitub and Elpaal. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And the sons of Elpaal: Eber, and Misham, and Shemed, who built Ono and Lod, with the towns thereof; <verse number="13" style="v"/>and Beriah, and Shema, who were heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of the inhabitants of Aijalon, who put to flight the inhabitants of Gath; <verse number="14" style="v"/>and Ahio, Shashak, and Jeremoth, <verse number="15" style="v"/>and Zebadiah, and Arad, and Eder, <verse number="16" style="v"/>and Michael, and Ishpah, and Joha, the sons of Beriah, <verse number="17" style="v"/>and Zebadiah, and Meshullam, and Hizki, and Heber, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and Ishmerai, and Izliah, and Jobab, the sons of Elpaal, <verse number="19" style="v"/>and Jakim, and Zichri, and Zabdi, <verse number="20" style="v"/>and Elienai, and Zillethai, and Eliel, <verse number="21" style="v"/>and Adaiah, and Beraiah, and Shimrath, the sons of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 8:13">verse 13</ref>, <char style="it">Shema</char>.</char></note>Shimei, <verse number="22" style="v"/>and Ishpan, and Eber, and Eliel, <verse number="23" style="v"/>and Abdon, and Zichri, and Hanan, <verse number="24" style="v"/>and Hananiah, and Elam, and Anthothijah, <verse number="25" style="v"/>and Iphdeiah, and Penuel, the sons of Shashak, <verse number="26" style="v"/>and Shamsherai, and Shehariah, and Athaliah, <verse number="27" style="v"/>and Jaareshiah, and Elijah, and Zichri, the sons of Jeroham. <verse number="28" style="v"/>These were heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> throughout their generations, chief men: these dwelt in Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v"/>And in Gibeon there dwelt the father of Gibeon, <char style="add">Jeiel</char>, whose wife&#8217;s name was Maacah; <verse number="30" style="v"/>and his first-born son Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Nadab, <verse number="31" style="v"/>and Gedor, and Ahio, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 9:37">9:37</ref>, <char style="it">Zechariah</char>.</char></note>Zecher. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And Mikloth begat <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 9:38">9:38</ref>, <char style="it">Shimeam</char>.</char></note>Shimeah. And they also dwelt with their brethren in Jerusalem, over against their brethren. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And Ner begat Kish; and Kish begat Saul; and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchi-shua, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1SA 14:49">1 Sam. 14:49</ref>, <char style="it">Ishvi</char>.</char></note>Abinadab, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 2:8">2 Sam. 2:8</ref>, <char style="it">Ishbosheth</char>.</char></note>Eshbaal. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And the son of Jonathan was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 4:4">2 Sam. 4:4</ref>; <ref loc="2SA 9:6">9:6</ref>, <ref loc="2SA 9:10">10</ref>, <char style="it">Mephibosheth</char></char></note>Merib-baal; and Merib-baal begat Micah. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And the sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melech, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 9:41">9:41</ref>, <char style="it">Tahrea</char>.</char></note>Tarea, and Ahaz. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And Ahaz begat <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 9:42">9:42</ref>, <char style="it">Jarah</char>.</char></note>Jehoaddah; and Jehoaddah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And Moza begat Binea; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 9:43">9:43</ref>, <char style="it">Rephaiah</char>.</char></note>Raphah was his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And Azel had six sons, whose names are these: Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan. All these were the sons of Azel. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And the sons of Eshek his brother: Ulam his first-born, Jeush the second, and Eliphelet the third. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And the sons of Ulam were mighty men of valor, archers, and had many sons, and sons&#8217; sons, a hundred and fifty. All these were of the sons of Benjamin.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>So all Israel were reckoned by genealogies; and, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel. And Judah was carried away captive to Babylon for their transgression. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Now the first inhabitants that dwelt in their possessions in their cities were Israel, the priests, the Levites, and the Nethinim. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And in Jerusalem dwelt of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin, and of the children of Ephraim and Manasseh: <verse number="4" style="v"/>Uthai the son of Ammihud, the son of Omri, the son of Imri, the son of Bani, of the children of Perez the son of Judah. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And of the Shilonites: Asaiah the first-born, and his sons. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And of the sons of Zerah: Jeuel, and their brethren, six hundred and ninety. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And of the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Hodaviah, the son of Hassenuah, <verse number="8" style="v"/>and Ibneiah the son of Jeroham, and Elah the son of Uzzi, the son of Michri, and Meshullam the son of Shephatiah, the son of Reuel, the son of Ibnijah; <verse number="9" style="v"/>and their brethren, according to their generations, nine hundred and fifty and six. All these men were heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> by their fathers&#8217; houses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And of the priests: Jedaiah, and Jehoiarib, Jachin, <verse number="11" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NEH 11:11">Neh. 11:11</ref>, <char style="it">Seraiah</char>.</char></note>Azariah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malchijah, and Maasai the son of Adiel, the son of Jahzerah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Meshillemith, the son of Immer; <verse number="13" style="v"/>and their brethren, heads of their fathers&#8217; houses, a thousand and seven hundred and threescore; very able men for the work of the service of the house of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, of the sons of Merari; <verse number="15" style="v"/>and Bakbakkar, Heresh, and Galal, and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NEH 11:17">Neh. 11:17</ref>, <char style="it">Zabdi</char>.</char></note>Zichri, the son of Asaph, <verse number="16" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NEH 11:17">Neh. 11:17</ref>, <char style="it">Abda</char>.</char></note>Obadiah the son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="NEH 11:17">Neh. 11:17</ref>, <char style="it">Shammua</char>.</char></note>Shemaiah, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun, and Berechiah the son of Asa, the son of Elkanah, that dwelt in the villages of the Netophathites.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And the porters: Shallum, and Akkub, and Talmon, and Ahiman, and their brethren (Shallum was the chief), <verse number="18" style="v"/>who hitherto <char style="add">waited</char> in the king&#8217;s gate eastward: they were the porters for the camp of the children of Levi. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Shallum the son of Kore, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, and his brethren, of his father&#8217;s house, the Korahites, were over the work of the service, keepers of the thresholds of the tent: and their fathers had been over the camp of Jehovah, keepers of the entry. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Phinehas the son of Eleazar was ruler over them in time past, <char style="add">and</char> Jehovah was with him. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah was porter of the door of the tent of meeting. <verse number="22" style="v"/>All these that were chosen to be porters in the thresholds were two hundred and twelve. These were reckoned by genealogy in their villages, whom David and Samuel the seer did ordain in their office of trust. <verse number="23" style="v"/>So they and their children had the oversight of the gates of the house of Jehovah, even the house of the tent, by wards. <verse number="24" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Towards the four winds</char>.</char></note>On the four sides were the porters, toward the east, west, north, and south. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And their brethren, in their villages, were to come in every seven days from time to time to be with them: <verse number="26" style="v"/>for the four chief porters, who were Levites, were in an office of trust, and were over the chambers and over the treasuries in the house of God. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And they lodged round about the house of God, because the charge <char style="add">thereof</char> was upon them; and to them pertained the opening thereof morning by morning.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And certain of them had charge of the vessels of service; for by count were these brought in and by count were these taken out. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Some of them also were appointed over the furniture, and over all the vessels of the sanctuary, and over the fine flour, and the wine, and the oil, and the frankincense, and the spices. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And some of the sons of the priests prepared the confection of the spices. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And Mattithiah, one of the Levites, who was the first-born of Shallum the Korahite, had the office of trust over the things that were baked in pans. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And some of their brethren, of the sons of the Kohathites, were over the showbread, to prepare it every sabbath.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v"/>And these are the singers, heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of the Levites, <char style="add">who dwelt</char> in the chambers <char style="add">and were</char> free <char style="add">from other service</char>; for they were employed in their work day and night. <verse number="34" style="v"/>These were heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of the Levites, throughout their generations, chief men: these dwelt at Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v"/>And in Gibeon there dwelt the father of Gibeon, Jeiel, whose wife&#8217;s name was Maacah; <verse number="36" style="v"/>and his first-born son Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Ner, and Nadab, <verse number="37" style="v"/>and Gedor, and Ahio, and Zechariah, and Mikloth. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And Mikloth begat Shimeam. And they also dwelt with their brethren in Jerusalem, over against their brethren. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And Ner begat Kish; and Kish begat Saul; and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchishua, and Abinadab, and Eshbaal. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And the son of Jonathan was Merib-baal; and Merib-baal begat Micah. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And the sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melech, and Tahrea, <char style="add">and Ahaz</char>. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And Ahaz begat Jarah; and Jarah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza; <verse number="43" style="v"/>and Moza begat Binea; and Rephaiah his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son. <verse number="44" style="v"/>And Azel had six sons, whose names are these: Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan: these were the sons of Azel.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now the Philistines fought against Israel: and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wounded</char></char></note>slain in mount Gilboa. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the Philistines followed hard after Saul and after his sons; and the Philistines slew Jonathan, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1SA 14:49">1 Sam. 14:49</ref>, <char style="it">Ishvi</char>.</char></note>Abinadab, and Malchi-shua, the sons of Saul. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And the battle went sore against Saul, and the archers overtook him; and he was distressed by reason of the archers. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Then said Saul unto his armorbearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through therewith, lest these uncircumcised come and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">make a mock of me</char></char></note>abuse me. But his armorbearer would not; for he was sore afraid. Therefore Saul took his sword, and fell upon it. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And when his armorbearer saw that Saul was dead, he likewise fell upon his sword, and died. <verse number="6" style="v"/>So Saul died, and his three sons; and all his house died together.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And when all the men of Israel that were in the valley saw that they fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they forsook their cities, and fled; and the Philistines came and dwelt in them. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And it came to pass on the morrow, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his sons fallen in mount Gilboa. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And they stripped him, and took his head, and his armor, and sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to carry the tidings unto their idols, and to the people. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And they put his armor in the house of their gods, and fastened his head in the house of Dagon. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And when all Jabesh-gilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul, <verse number="12" style="v"/>all the valiant men arose, and took away the body of Saul, and the bodies of his sons, and brought them to Jabesh, and buried their bones under the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">terebinth</char></char></note>oak in Jabesh, and fasted seven days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>So Saul died <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char></char></note>for his trespass which he committed against Jehovah, because of the word of Jehovah, which he kept not; and also for that he asked counsel of one that had a familiar spirit, to inquire <char style="add">thereby</char>, <verse number="14" style="v"/>and inquired not of Jehovah: therefore he slew him, and turned the kingdom unto David the son of Jesse.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Then all Israel gathered themselves to David unto Hebron, saying, Behold, we are thy bone and thy flesh. <verse number="2" style="v"/>In times past, even when Saul was king, it was thou that leddest out and broughtest in Israel: and Jehovah thy God said unto thee, Thou shalt be shepherd of my people Israel, and thou shalt be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">leader</char></char></note>prince over my people Israel. <verse number="3" style="v"/>So all the elders of Israel came to the king to Hebron; and David made a covenant with them in Hebron before Jehovah; and they anointed David king over Israel, according to the word of Jehovah by Samuel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>And David and all Israel went to Jerusalem (the same is Jebus); and the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land, were there. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the inhabitants of Jebus said to David, Thou shalt not come in hither. Nevertheless David took the stronghold of Zion; the same is the city of David. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And David said, Whosoever smiteth the Jebusites first shall be chief and captain. And Joab the son of Zeruiah went up first, and was made chief. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And David dwelt in the stronghold; therefore they called it the city of David. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he built the city round about, from Millo even round about; and Joab <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">revived</char>.</char></note>repaired the rest of the city. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And David waxed greater and greater; for Jehovah of hosts was with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>Now these are the chief of the mighty men whom David had, who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">held strongly with him</char></char></note>showed themselves strong with him in his kingdom, together with all Israel, to make him king, according to the word of Jehovah concerning Israel. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And this is the number of the mighty men whom David had: Jashobeam, the son of a Hachmonite, the chief of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Another reading is, <char style="it">captains</char>.</char></note>thirty; he lifted up his spear against three hundred <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">slain</char>.</char></note>and slew them at one time. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And after him was Eleazar the son of Dodo, the Ahohite, who was one of the three mighty men. <verse number="13" style="v"/>He was with David at <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1SA 17:1">1 Sam. 17:1</ref>, <char style="it">Ephes-dammim</char>.</char></note>Pasdammim, and there the Philistines were gathered together to battle, where was a plot of ground full of barley; and the people fled from before the Philistines. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And they stood in the midst of the plot, and defended it, and slew the Philistines; and Jehovah saved them by a great <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">salvation</char>.</char></note>victory.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And three of the thirty chief men went down to the rock to David, into the cave of Adullam; and the host of the Philistines were encamped in the valley of Rephaim. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And David was then in the stronghold, and the garrison of the Philistines was then in Beth-lehem. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And David longed, and said, Oh that one would give me water to drink of the well of Beth-lehem, which is by the gate! <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the three brake through the host of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Beth-lehem, that was by the gate, and took it, and brought it to David: but David would not drink thereof, but poured it out unto Jehovah, <verse number="19" style="v"/>and said, My God forbid it me, that I should do this: shall I drink the blood of these men <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">with their lives</char>.</char></note>that have put their lives in jeopardy? for with <char style="add">the jeopardy of</char> their lives they brought it. Therefore he would not drink it. These things did the three mighty men.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Abshai</char>.</char></note>Abishai, the brother of Joab, he was chief of the three; for he lifted up his spear against three hundred <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">slain</char>.</char></note>and slew them, and had a name among the three. <verse number="21" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Of the three in the second rank he was the most honorable</char></char></note>Of the three, he was more honorable than the two, and was made their captain: howbeit he attained not to the <char style="add">first</char> three.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man of Kabzeel, who had done mighty deeds, he slew the two <char style="add">sons of</char> Ariel of Moab: he went down also and slew a lion in the midst of a pit in time of snow. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he slew an Egyptian, a man of great stature, five cubits high; and in the Egyptian&#8217;s hand was a spear like a weaver&#8217;s beam; and he went down to him with a staff, and plucked the spear out of the Egyptian&#8217;s hand, and slew him with his own spear. <verse number="24" style="v"/>These things did Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and had a name among the three mighty men. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Behold, he was more honorable than the thirty, but he attained not to the <char style="add">first</char> three: and David set him over his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">council</char></char></note>guard.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>Also the mighty men of the armies: Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo of Beth-lehem, <verse number="27" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:25">2 Sam. 23:25</ref>, <char style="it">Shammath the Harodite</char>.</char></note>Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:26">2 Sam. 23:26</ref>, <char style="it">Paltite</char>.</char></note>Pelonite, <verse number="28" style="v"/>Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abiezer the Anathothite, <verse number="29" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:27">2 Sam. 23:27</ref>, <char style="it">Mebunnai</char>.</char></note>Sibbecai the Hushathite, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:28">2 Sam. 23:28</ref>, <char style="it">Zalmon</char>.</char></note>Ilai the Ahohite, <verse number="30" style="v"/>Maharai the Netophathite, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:29">2 Sam. 23:29</ref>, <char style="it">Heleb</char>.</char></note>Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite, <verse number="31" style="v"/>Ithai the son of Ribai of Gibeah of the children of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite, <verse number="32" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:30">2 Sam. 23:30</ref>, <char style="it">Hiddai</char>.</char></note>Hurai of the brooks of Gaash, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:31">2 Sam. 23:31</ref>, <char style="it">Abi-albon</char>.</char></note>Abiel the Arbathite, <verse number="33" style="v"/>Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite, <verse number="34" style="v"/>the sons of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:32">2 Sam. 23:32</ref>, <char style="it">Jashen</char>.</char></note>Hashem the Gizonite, Jonathan the son of Shagee the Hararite, <verse number="35" style="v"/>Ahiam the son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:33">2 Sam. 23:33</ref>, <char style="it">Sharar</char>.</char></note>Sacar the Hararite, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:34">2 Sam. 23:34</ref>, <char style="it">Eliphelet the son of Ahasbai</char>.</char></note>Eliphal the son of Ur, <verse number="36" style="v"/>Hepher the Mecherathite, Ahijah the Pelonite, <verse number="37" style="v"/>Hezro the Carmelite, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 23:35">2 Sam. 23:35</ref>, <char style="it">Paarai the Arbite</char>.</char></note>Naarai the son of Ezbai, <verse number="38" style="v"/>Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Hagri, <verse number="39" style="v"/>Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, the armorbearer of Joab the son of Zeruiah, <verse number="40" style="v"/>Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite, <verse number="41" style="v"/>Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai, <verse number="42" style="v"/>Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a chief of the Reubenites, and thirty with him, <verse number="43" style="v"/>Hanan the son of Maacah, and Joshaphat the Mithnite, <verse number="44" style="v"/>Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jeiel the sons of Hotham the Aroerite, <verse number="45" style="v"/>Jediael the son of Shimri, and Joha his brother, the Tizite, <verse number="46" style="v"/>Eliel the Mahavite, and Jeribai, and Joshaviah, the sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah the Moabite, <verse number="47" style="v"/>Eliel, and Obed, and Jaasiel the Mezobaite.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now these are they that came to David to Ziklag, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew being <char style="it">yet shut up</char></char></note>while he yet kept himself close because of Saul the son of Kish; and they were among the mighty men, his helpers in war. <verse number="2" style="v"/>They <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">drew the bow</char></char></note>were armed with bows, and could use both the right hand and the left in slinging stones and in shooting arrows from the bow: they were of Saul&#8217;s brethren of Benjamin. <verse number="3" style="v"/>The chief was Ahiezer; then Joash, the sons of Shemaah the Gibeathite, and Jeziel, and Pelet, the sons of Azmaveth, and Beracah, and Jehu the Anathothite, <verse number="4" style="v"/>and Ishmaiah the Gibeonite, a mighty man among the thirty, and over the thirty, and Jeremiah, and Jahaziel, and Johanan, and Jozabad the Gederathite, <verse number="5" style="v"/>Eluzai, and Jerimoth, and Bealiah, and Shemariah, and Shephatiah the Haruphite, <verse number="6" style="v"/>Elkanah, and Isshiah, and Azarel, and Joezer, and Jashobeam, the Korahites, <verse number="7" style="v"/>and Joelah, and Zebadiah, the sons of Jeroham of Gedor.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And of the Gadites there separated themselves unto David to the stronghold in the wilderness, mighty men of valor, men trained for war, that could handle shield and spear; whose faces were like the faces of lions, and they were as swift as the roes upon the mountains: <verse number="9" style="v"/>Ezer the chief, Obadiah the second, Eliab the third, <verse number="10" style="v"/>Mishmannah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth, <verse number="11" style="v"/>Attai the sixth, Eliel the seventh, <verse number="12" style="v"/>Johanan the eighth, Elzabad the ninth, <verse number="13" style="v"/>Jeremiah the tenth, Machbannai the eleventh. <verse number="14" style="v"/>These of the sons of Gad were captains of the host: he that was least was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">over</char></char></note>equal to a hundred, and the greatest <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">over</char></char></note>to a thousand. <verse number="15" style="v"/>These are they that went over the Jordan in the first month, when it had overflowed all its banks; and they put to flight all them of the valleys, both toward the east and toward the west.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And there came of the children of Benjamin and Judah to the stronghold unto David. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And David went out to meet them, and answered and said unto them, If ye be come peaceably unto me to help me, my heart shall be knit unto you; but if <char style="add">ye be come</char> to betray me to mine adversaries, seeing there is no <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">violence</char></char></note>wrong in my hands, the God of our fathers look thereon, and rebuke it. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Then the Spirit <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">clothed</char>.</char></note>came upon Amasai, who was chief of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Another reading is, <char style="it">captains</char>.</char></note>thirty, <char style="add">and he said</char>, Thine are we, David, and on thy side, thou son of Jesse: peace, peace be unto thee, and peace be to thy helpers; for thy God helpeth thee. Then David received them, and made them captains of the band.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>Of Manasseh also there fell away some to David, when he came with the Philistines against Saul to battle: but they helped them not; for the lords of the Philistines upon advisement sent him away, saying, He will fall away to his master Saul to the jeopardy of our heads. <verse number="20" style="v"/>As he went to Ziklag, there fell to him of Manasseh, Adnah, and Jozabad, and Jediael, and Michael, and Jozabad, and Elihu, and Zillethai, captains of thousands that were of Manasseh. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And they helped David against the band of rovers: for they were all mighty men of valor, and were captains in the host. <verse number="22" style="v"/>For from day to day men came to David to help him, until there was a great host, like the host of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>And these are the numbers of the heads of them that were armed for war, who came to David to Hebron, to turn the kingdom of Saul to him, according to the word of Jehovah. <verse number="24" style="v"/>The children of Judah that bare shield and spear were six thousand and eight hundred, armed for war. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Of the children of Simeon, mighty men of valor for the war, seven thousand and one hundred. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Of the children of Levi four thousand and six hundred. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Jehoiada was the leader of <char style="add">the house of</char> Aaron; and with him were three thousand and seven hundred, <verse number="28" style="v"/>and Zadok, a young man mighty of valor, and of his father&#8217;s house twenty and two captains. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And of the children of Benjamin, the brethren of Saul, three thousand: for hitherto the greatest part of them had <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">kept the charge of the house</char>.</char></note>kept their allegiance to the house of Saul. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And of the children of Ephraim twenty thousand and eight hundred, mighty men of valor, famous men in their fathers&#8217; houses. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And of the half-tribe of Manasseh eighteen thousand, who were mentioned by name, to come and make David king. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And of the children of Issachar, men that had understanding of the times, to know what Israel ought to do, the heads of them were two hundred; and all their brethren were at their commandment. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Of Zebulun, such as were able to go out in the host, that could set the battle in array, with all manner of instruments of war, fifty thousand, and that could order <char style="add">the battle array, and were</char> not of double heart. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And of Naphtali a thousand captains, and with them with shield and spear thirty and seven thousand. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And of the Danites that could set the battle in array, twenty and eight thousand and six hundred. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And of Asher, such as were able to go out in the host, that could set the battle in array, forty thousand. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And on the other side of the Jordan, of the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and of the half-tribe of Manasseh, with all manner of instruments of war for the battle, a hundred and twenty thousand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v"/>All these, being men of war, that could order the battle array, came with a perfect heart to Hebron, to make David king over all Israel: and all the rest also of Israel were of one heart to make David king. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And they were there with David three days, eating and drinking; for their brethren had made preparation for them. <verse number="40" style="v"/>Moreover they that were nigh unto them, <char style="add">even</char> as far as Issachar and Zebulun and Naphtali, brought bread on asses, and on camels, and on mules, and on oxen, victuals of meal, cakes of figs, and clusters of raisins, and wine, and oil, and oxen, and sheep in abundance: for there was joy in Israel.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And David consulted with the captains of thousands and of hundreds, even with every leader. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And David said unto all the assembly of Israel, If it seem good unto you, and if it be of Jehovah our God, let us send abroad every where unto our brethren that are left in all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">lands</char>.</char></note>land of Israel, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and with them to the priests and Levites that are etc.</char></char></note>with whom the priests and Levites are in their cities that have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pasture lands</char></char></note>suburbs, that they may gather themselves unto us; <verse number="3" style="v"/>and let us bring again the ark of our God to us: for we sought not unto it in the days of Saul. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And all the assembly said that they would do so; for the thing was right in the eyes of all the people. <verse number="5" style="v"/>So David assembled all Israel together, from the Shihor <char style="add">the brook</char> of Egypt even unto the entrance of Hamath, to bring the ark of God from Kiriath-jearim. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And David went up, and all Israel, to Baalah, <char style="add">that is</char>, to Kiriath-jearim, which belonged to Judah, to bring up from thence the ark of God Jehovah that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">is enthroned</char></char></note>sitteth <char style="add">above</char> the cherubim, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">where the Name is called on</char></char></note>that is called by the Name. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And they carried the ark of God upon a new cart, <char style="add">and brought it</char> out of the house of Abinadab: and Uzza and Ahio drove the cart. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And David and all Israel played before God with all their might, even with songs, and with harps, and with psalteries, and with timbrels, and with cymbals, and with trumpets.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And when they came unto the threshing-floor of Chidon, Uzza put forth his hand to hold the ark; for the oxen <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">were restive</char>. Or, <char style="it">threw</char> it <char style="it">down</char></char></note>stumbled. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Uzza, and he smote him, because he put forth his hand to the ark; and there he died before God. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And David was displeased, because Jehovah had broken forth upon Uzza: and he called that place <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The breach of Uzza</char>.</char></note>Perez-uzza, unto this day. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And David was afraid of God that day, saying, How shall I bring the ark of God home to me? <verse number="13" style="v"/>So David removed not the ark unto him into the city of David, but carried it aside into the house of Obed-edom the Gittite. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the ark of God remained with the family of Obed-edom in his house three months: and Jehovah blessed the house of Obed-edom, and all that he had.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Hiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David, and cedar-trees, and masons, and carpenters, to build him a house. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And David perceived that Jehovah had established him king over Israel; for his kingdom was exalted on high, for his people Israel&#8217;s sake.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>And David took more wives at Jerusalem; and David begat more sons and daughters. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And these are the names of the children whom he had in Jerusalem: Shammua, and Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon, <verse number="5" style="v"/>and Ibhar, and Elishua, and Elpelet, <verse number="6" style="v"/>and Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia, <verse number="7" style="v"/>and Elishama, and Beeliada, and Eliphelet.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And when the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over all Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David: and David heard of it, and went out <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">before</char></char></note>against them. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Now the Philistines had come and made a raid in the valley of Rephaim. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And David inquired of God, saying, Shall I go up against the Philistines? and wilt thou deliver them into my hand? And Jehovah said unto him, Go up; for I will deliver them into thy hand. <verse number="11" style="v"/>So they came up to Baal-perazim, and David smote them there; and David said, God hath <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">broken forth upon mine enemies</char></char></note>broken mine enemies by my hand, like the breach of waters. Therefore they called the name of that place <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">The place of breakings forth</char>.</char></note>Baal-perazim. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And they left their gods there; and David gave commandment, and they were burned with fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And the Philistines yet again made a raid in the valley. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And David inquired again of God; and God said unto him, Thou shalt not go up after them: turn away from them, and come upon them over against the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">balsam-trees</char></char></note>mulberry-trees. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And it shall be, when thou hearest the sound of marching in the tops of the mulberry-trees, that then thou shalt go out to battle; for God is gone out before thee to smite the host of the Philistines. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And David did as God commanded him: and they smote the host of the Philistines from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 5:25">2 Sam. 5:25</ref>, <char style="it">Geba</char>.</char></note>Gibeon even to Gezer. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the fame of David went out into all lands; and Jehovah brought the fear of him upon all nations.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And <char style="add">David</char> made him houses in the city of David; and he prepared a place for the ark of God, and pitched for it a tent. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Then David said, None ought to carry the ark of God but the Levites: for them hath Jehovah chosen to carry the ark of God, and to minister unto him for ever. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And David assembled all Israel at Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of Jehovah unto its place, which he had prepared for it. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And David gathered together the sons of Aaron, and the Levites: <verse number="5" style="v"/>of the sons of Kohath, Uriel the chief, and his brethren a hundred and twenty; <verse number="6" style="v"/>of the sons of Merari, Asaiah the chief, and his brethren two hundred and twenty; <verse number="7" style="v"/>of the sons of Gershom, Joel the chief, and his brethren a hundred and thirty; <verse number="8" style="v"/>of the sons of Elizaphan, Shemaiah the chief, and his brethren two hundred; <verse number="9" style="v"/>of the sons of Hebron, Eliel the chief, and his brethren fourscore; <verse number="10" style="v"/>of the sons of Uzziel, Amminadab the chief, and his brethren a hundred and twelve. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And David called for Zadok and Abiathar the priests, and for the Levites, for Uriel, Asaiah, and Joel, Shemaiah, and Eliel, and Amminadab, <verse number="12" style="v"/>and said unto them, Ye are the heads of the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of the Levites: sanctify yourselves, both ye and your brethren, that ye may bring up the ark of Jehovah, the God of Israel, unto <char style="add">the place</char> that I have prepared for it. <verse number="13" style="v"/>For because ye <char style="add">bare it</char> not at the first, Jehovah our God made a breach upon us, for that we sought him not according to the ordinance. <verse number="14" style="v"/>So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of Jehovah, the God of Israel. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the children of the Levites bare the ark of God upon their shoulders with the staves thereon, as Moses commanded according to the word of Jehovah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And David spake to the chief of the Levites to appoint their brethren the singers, with instruments of music, psalteries and harps and cymbals, sounding aloud and lifting up the voice with joy. <verse number="17" style="v"/>So the Levites appointed Heman the son of Joel; and of his brethren, Asaph the son of Berechiah; and of the sons of Merari their brethren, Ethan the son of Kushaiah; <verse number="18" style="v"/>and with them their brethren of the second degree, Zechariah, Ben, and Jaaziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, Eliab, and Benaiah, and Maaseiah, and Mattithiah, and Eliphelehu, and Mikneiah, and Obed-edom, and Jeiel, the doorkeepers. <verse number="19" style="v"/>So the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, <char style="add">were appointed</char>, with cymbals of brass to sound aloud; <verse number="20" style="v"/>and Zechariah, and Aziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, and Eliab, and Maaseiah, and Benaiah, with psalteries set to Alamoth; <verse number="21" style="v"/>and Mattithiah, and Eliphelehu, and Mikneiah, and Obed-edom, and Jeiel, and Azaziah, with harps set to the Sheminith, to lead. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Chenaniah, chief of the Levites, was over <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the carrying</char> of the ark. Hebrew <char style="it">the lifting up</char>.</char></note>the song: he instructed about <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the carrying</char> of the ark. Hebrew <char style="it">the lifting up</char>.</char></note>the song, because he was skilful. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Berechiah and Elkanah were doorkeepers for the ark. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Shebaniah, and Joshaphat, and Nethanel, and Amasai, and Zechariah, and Benaiah, and Eliezer, the priests, did blow the trumpets before the ark of God; and Obed-edom and Jehiah were doorkeepers for the ark.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>So David, and the elders of Israel, and the captains over thousands, went to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah out of the house of Obed-edom with joy. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when God helped the Levites that bare the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, that they sacrificed seven bullocks and seven rams. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And David was clothed with a robe of fine linen, and all the Levites that bare the ark, and the singers, and Chenaniah the master of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the carrying</char> of the ark. Hebrew <char style="it">the lifting up</char>.</char></note>the song <char style="add">with</char> the singers: and David had upon him an ephod of linen. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Thus all Israel brought up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah with shouting, and with sound of the cornet, and with trumpets, and with cymbals, sounding aloud with psalteries and harps.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as the ark of the covenant of Jehovah came to the city of David, that Michal the daughter of Saul looked out at the window, and saw king David dancing and playing; and she despised him in her heart.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And they brought in the ark of God, and set it in the midst of the tent that David had pitched for it: and they offered burnt-offerings and peace-offerings before God. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And when David had made an end of offering the burnt-offering and the peace-offerings, he blessed the people in the name of Jehovah. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he dealt to every one of Israel, both man and woman, to every one a loaf of bread, and a portion <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, of wine</char></note><char style="add">of flesh</char>, and a cake of raisins.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>And he appointed certain of the Levites to minister before the ark of Jehovah, and to celebrate and to thank and praise Jehovah, the God of Israel: <verse number="5" style="v"/>Asaph the chief, and second to him Zechariah, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 15:18">15:18</ref>, <char style="it">Jaaziel</char>.</char></note>Jeiel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Mattithiah, and Eliab, and Benaiah, and Obed-edom, and Jeiel, with psalteries and with harps; and Asaph with cymbals, sounding aloud; <verse number="6" style="v"/>and Benaiah and Jahaziel the priests with trumpets continually, before the ark of the covenant of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>Then on that day did David <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">make it the chief work</char></char></note>first ordain to give thanks unto Jehovah, by the hand of Asaph and his brethren.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="8" style="v"/>O give thanks unto Jehovah, call upon his name;</para>
	<para style="q1">Make known his doings among the peoples.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="9" style="v"/>Sing unto him, sing praises unto him;</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Meditate</char></char></note>Talk ye of all his marvellous works.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="10" style="v"/>Glory ye in his holy name;</para>
	<para style="q1">Let the heart of them rejoice that seek Jehovah.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="11" style="v"/>Seek ye Jehovah and his strength;</para>
	<para style="q1">Seek his face evermore.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Remember his marvellous works that he hath done,</para>
	<para style="q1">His wonders, and the judgments of his mouth,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="13" style="v"/>O ye seed of Israel his servant,</para>
	<para style="q1">Ye children of Jacob, his chosen ones.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="14" style="v"/>He is Jehovah our God;</para>
	<para style="q1">His judgments are in all the earth.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="15" style="v"/>Remember his covenant for ever,</para>
	<para style="q1">The word which he commanded to a thousand generations,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="16" style="v"/><char style="add">The covenant</char> which he made with Abraham,</para>
	<para style="q1">And his oath unto Isaac,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And confirmed the same unto Jacob for a statute,</para>
	<para style="q1">To Israel for an everlasting covenant,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="18" style="v"/>Saying, Unto thee will I give the land of Canaan,</para>
	<para style="q1">The <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">cord</char>, or, <char style="it">line</char>.</char></note>lot of your inheritance;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="19" style="v"/>When ye were but a few men in number,</para>
	<para style="q1">Yea, very few, and sojourners in it;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And they went about from nation to nation,</para>
	<para style="q1">And from one kingdom to another people.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="21" style="v"/>He suffered no man to do them wrong;</para>
	<para style="q1">Yea, he reproved kings for their sakes,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="22" style="v"/><char style="add">Saying</char>, Touch not mine anointed ones,</para>
	<para style="q1">And do my prophets no harm.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="23" style="v"/>Sing unto Jehovah, all the earth;</para>
	<para style="q1">Show forth his salvation from day to day.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="24" style="v"/>Declare his glory among the nations,</para>
	<para style="q1">His marvellous works among all the peoples.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="25" style="v"/>For great is Jehovah, and greatly to be praised:</para>
	<para style="q1">He also is to be feared above all gods.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="26" style="v"/>For all the gods of the peoples are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">things of nought</char></char></note>idols:</para>
	<para style="q1">But Jehovah made the heavens.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="27" style="v"/>Honor and majesty are before him:</para>
	<para style="q1">Strength and gladness are in his place.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="28" style="v"/>Ascribe unto Jehovah, ye kindreds of the peoples,</para>
	<para style="q1">Ascribe unto Jehovah glory and strength;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="29" style="v"/>Ascribe unto Jehovah the glory due unto his name:</para>
	<para style="q1">Bring an offering, and come before him;</para>
	<para style="q1">Worship Jehovah <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in the beauty of holiness</char></char></note>in holy array.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="30" style="v"/>Tremble before him, all the earth:</para>
	<para style="q1">The world also is established that it cannot be moved.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="31" style="v"/>Let the heavens be glad, and let the earth rejoice;</para>
	<para style="q1">And let them say among the nations, Jehovah reigneth.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="32" style="v"/>Let the sea roar, and the fulness thereof;</para>
	<para style="q1">Let the field exult, and all that is therein;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="33" style="v"/>Then shall the trees of the wood sing for joy before Jehovah;</para>
	<para style="q1">For he cometh to judge the earth.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="34" style="v"/>O give thanks unto Jehovah; for he is good;</para>
	<para style="q1">For his lovingkindness <char style="add">endureth</char> for ever.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="35" style="v"/>And say ye, Save us, O God of our salvation,</para>
	<para style="q1">And gather us together and deliver us from the nations,</para>
	<para style="q1">To give thanks unto thy holy name,</para>
	<para style="q1">And to triumph in thy praise.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="36" style="v"/>Blessed be Jehovah, the God of Israel,</para>
	<para style="q1">From everlasting even to everlasting.</para>
	<para style="m">And all the people said, Amen, and praised Jehovah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v"/>So he left there, before the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, Asaph and his brethren, to minister before the ark continually, as every day&#8217;s work required; <verse number="38" style="v"/>and Obed-edom with their brethren, threescore and eight; Obed-edom also the son of Jeduthun and Hosah to be doorkeepers; <verse number="39" style="v"/>and Zadok the priest, and his brethren the priests, before the tabernacle of Jehovah in the high place that was at Gibeon, <verse number="40" style="v"/>to offer burnt-offerings unto Jehovah upon the altar of burnt-offering continually morning and evening, even according to all that is written in the law of Jehovah, which he commanded unto Israel; <verse number="41" style="v"/>and with them Heman and Jeduthun, and the rest that were chosen, who were mentioned by name, to give thanks to Jehovah, because his lovingkindness <char style="add">endureth</char> for ever; <verse number="42" style="v"/>and with them Heman and Jeduthun <char style="add">with</char> trumpets and cymbals for those that should sound aloud, and <char style="add">with</char> instruments for the songs of God; and the sons of Jeduthun to be at the gate. <verse number="43" style="v"/>And all the people departed every man to his house: and David returned to bless his house.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass, when David dwelt in his house, that David said to Nathan the prophet, Lo, I dwell in a house of cedar, but the ark of the covenant of Jehovah <char style="add">dwelleth</char> under curtains. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Nathan said unto David, Do all that is in thy heart; for God is with thee. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And it came to pass the same night, that the word of God came to Nathan, saying, <verse number="4" style="v"/>Go and tell David my servant, Thus saith Jehovah, Thou shalt not build me a house to dwell in: <verse number="5" style="v"/>for I have not dwelt in a house since the day that I brought up Israel, unto this day, but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">have been</char>.</char></note>have gone from tent to tent, and from <char style="add">one</char> tabernacle <char style="add">to another</char>. <verse number="6" style="v"/>In all places wherein I have walked with all Israel, spake I a word with any of the judges of Israel, whom I commanded to be shepherd of my people, saying, Why have ye not built me a house of cedar? <verse number="7" style="v"/>Now therefore thus shalt thou say unto my servant David, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, I took thee from the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pasture</char></char></note>sheepcote, from following the sheep, that thou shouldest be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">leader</char></char></note>prince over my people Israel: <verse number="8" style="v"/>and I have been with thee whithersoever thou hast gone, and have cut off all thine enemies from before thee; and I will make thee a name, like unto the name of the great ones that are in the earth. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, that they may dwell in their own place, and be moved no more; neither shall the children of wickedness waste them any more, as at the first, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and <char style="add">as</char> from the day that I commanded judges to be over my people Israel; and I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">have subdued</char></char></note>will subdue all thine enemies. Moreover I tell thee that Jehovah will build thee a house. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And it shall come to pass, when thy days are fulfilled that thou must go to be with thy fathers, that I will set up thy seed after thee, who shall be of thy sons; and I will establish his kingdom. <verse number="12" style="v"/>He shall build me a house, and I will establish his throne for ever. <verse number="13" style="v"/>I will be his father, and he shall be my son: and I will not take my lovingkindness away from him, as I took it from him that was before thee; <verse number="14" style="v"/>but I will settle him in my house and in my kingdom for ever; and his throne shall be established for ever. <verse number="15" style="v"/>According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speak unto David.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>Then David the king went in, and sat before Jehovah; and he said, Who am I, O Jehovah God, and what is my house, that thou hast brought me thus far? <verse number="17" style="v"/>And this was a small thing in thine eyes, O God; but thou hast spoken of thy servant&#8217;s house for a great while to come, and hast regarded me according to the estate of a man of high degree, O Jehovah God. <verse number="18" style="v"/>What can David <char style="add">say</char> yet more unto thee concerning the honor which is done to thy servant? for thou knowest thy servant. <verse number="19" style="v"/>O Jehovah, for thy servant&#8217;s sake, and according to thine own heart, hast thou wrought all this greatness, to make known all <char style="add">these</char> great things. <verse number="20" style="v"/>O Jehovah, there is none like thee, neither is there any God besides thee, according to all that we have heard with our ears. <verse number="21" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">And who is like thy people Israel, a nation that is alone in the earth etc.</char></char></note>And what one nation in the earth is like thy people Israel, whom God went to redeem unto himself for a people, to make thee a name by great and terrible things, in driving out nations from before thy people, whom thou redeemedst out of Egypt? <verse number="22" style="v"/>For thy people Israel didst thou make thine own people for ever; and thou, Jehovah, becamest their God. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And now, O Jehovah, let the word that thou hast spoken concerning thy servant, and concerning his house, be established for ever, and do as thou hast spoken. <verse number="24" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Yea, let it be established, and let thy name be magnified etc.</char></char></note>And let thy name be established and magnified for ever, saying, Jehovah of hosts is the God of Israel, even a God to Israel: and the house of David thy servant is established before thee. <verse number="25" style="v"/>For thou, O my God, hast revealed to thy servant that thou wilt build him a house: therefore hath thy servant found <char style="add">in his heart</char> to pray before thee. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And now, O Jehovah, thou art God, and hast promised this good thing unto thy servant: <verse number="27" style="v"/>and now it hath pleased thee to bless the house of thy servant, that it may continue for ever before thee: for thou, O Jehovah, hast blessed, and it is blessed for ever.</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And after this it came to pass, that David smote the Philistines, and subdued them, and took Gath and its towns out of the hand of the Philistines. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he smote Moab; and the Moabites became servants to David, and brought tribute.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>And David smote Hadarezer king of Zobah <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by</char></char></note>unto Hamath, as he went to establish his dominion by the river Euphrates. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And David took from him a thousand chariots, and seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen; and David hocked all the chariot horses, but reserved of them for a hundred chariots.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>And when <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Aram</char>.</char></note>the Syrians of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Darmesek</char>.</char></note>Damascus came to succor Hadarezer king of Zobah, David smote of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Aram</char>.</char></note>the Syrians two and twenty thousand men. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Then David put <char style="add">garrisons</char> in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Aram</char>.</char></note>Syria of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Darmesek</char>.</char></note>Damascus; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Aram</char>.</char></note>the Syrians became servants to David, and brought tribute. And Jehovah <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">saved David</char></char></note>gave victory to David whithersoever he went. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadarezer, and brought them to Jerusalem. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And from Tibhath and from Cun, cities of Hadarezer, David took very much brass, wherewith Solomon made the brazen sea, and the pillars, and the vessels of brass.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And when Tou king of Hamath heard that David had smitten all the host of Hadarezer king of Zobah, <verse number="10" style="v"/>he sent Hadoram his son to king David, to salute him, and to bless him, because he had fought against Hadarezer and smitten him (for Hadarezer had wars with Tou); and <char style="add">he had with him</char> all manner of vessels of gold and silver and brass. <verse number="11" style="v"/>These also did king David dedicate unto Jehovah, with the silver and the gold that he carried away from all the nations; from Edom, and from Moab, and from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines, and from Amalek.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Moreover <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Abshai</char>.</char></note>Abishai the son of Zeruiah smote of the Edomites in the Valley of Salt eighteen thousand. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And he put garrisons in Edom; and all the Edomites became servants to David. And Jehovah gave victory to David whithersoever he went.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And David reigned over all Israel; and he executed justice and righteousness unto all his people. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the host; and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">chronicler</char></char></note>recorder; <verse number="16" style="v"/>and Zadok the son of Ahitub, and Abimelech the son of Abiathar, were priests; and Shavsha was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">secretary</char></char></note>scribe; <verse number="17" style="v"/>and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and the sons of David were chief about the king.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass after this, that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon died, and his son reigned in his stead. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And David said, I will show kindness unto Hanun the son of Nahash, because his father showed kindness to me. So David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. And David&#8217;s servants came into the land of the children of Ammon to Hanun, to comfort him. <verse number="3" style="v"/>But the princes of the children of Ammon said to Hanun, Thinkest thou that David doth honor thy father, in that he hath sent comforters unto thee? are not his servants come unto thee to search, and to overthrow, and to spy out the land? <verse number="4" style="v"/>So Hanun took David&#8217;s servants, and shaved them, and cut off their garments in the middle, even to their buttocks, and sent them away. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Then there went certain persons, and told David how the men were served. And he sent to meet them; for the men were greatly ashamed. And the king said, Tarry at Jericho until your beards be grown, and then return.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And when the children of Ammon saw that they had made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the children of Ammon sent a thousand talents of silver to hire them chariots and horsemen out of Mesopotamia, and out of Aram-maacah, and out of Zobah. <verse number="7" style="v"/>So they hired them thirty and two thousand chariots, and the king of Maacah and his people, who came and encamped before Medeba. And the children of Ammon gathered themselves together from their cities, and came to battle. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And when David heard of it, he sent Joab, and all the host of the mighty men. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the children of Ammon came out, and put the battle in array at the gate of the city: and the kings that were come were by themselves in the field.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>Now when Joab saw that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">the face of the battle was against</char>.</char></note>the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose of all the choice men of Israel, and put them in array against the Syrians. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the rest of the people he committed into the hand of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Abshai</char>.</char></note>Abishai his brother; and they put themselves in array against the children of Ammon. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he said, If the Syrians be too strong for me, then thou shalt help me; but if the children of Ammon be too strong for thee, then I will help thee. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Be of good courage, and let us play the man for our people, and for the cities of our God: and Jehovah do that which seemeth him good. <verse number="14" style="v"/>So Joab and the people that were with him drew nigh before the Syrians unto the battle; and they fled before him. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And when the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians were fled, they likewise fled before Abishai his brother, and entered into the city. Then Joab came to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And when the Syrians saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they sent messengers, and drew forth the Syrians that were beyond the River, with Shophach the captain of the host of Hadarezer at their head. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And it was told David; and he gathered all Israel together, and passed over the Jordan, and came upon them, and set the battle in array against them. So when David had put the battle in array against the Syrians, they fought with him. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the Syrians fled before Israel; and David slew of the Syrians <char style="add">the men of</char> seven thousand chariots, and forty thousand footmen, and killed Shophach the captain of the host. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And when the servants of Hadarezer saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they made peace with David, and served him: neither would the Syrians help the children of Ammon any more.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass, at the time of the return of the year, at the time when kings go out <char style="add">to battle</char>, that Joab led forth the army, and wasted the country of the children of Ammon, and came and besieged Rabbah. But David tarried at Jerusalem. And Joab smote Rabbah, and overthrew it. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And David took the crown of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Malcam</char>. See <ref loc="ZEP 1:5">Zeph. 1:5</ref>.</char></note>their king from off his head, and found it to weigh a talent of gold, and there were precious stones in it; and it was set upon David&#8217;s head: and he brought forth the spoil of the city, exceeding much. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he brought forth the people that were therein, and cut <char style="add">them</char> with saws, and with harrows of iron, and with axes. And thus did David unto all the cities of the children of Ammon. And David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>And it came to pass after this, that there arose war at <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 21:18">2 Sam. 21:18</ref>, <char style="it">Gob</char>.</char></note>Gezer with the Philistines: then Sibbecai the Hushathite slew Sippai, of the sons of the giant; and they were subdued. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And there was again war with the Philistines; and Elhanan the son of Jair slew Lahmi the brother of Goliath the Gittite, the staff of whose spear was like a weaver&#8217;s beam. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And there was again war at Gath, where was a man of great stature, whose fingers and toes were four and twenty, six <char style="add">on each hand</char>, and six <char style="add">on each foot</char>; and he also was born unto the giant. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And when he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">reproached</char></char></note>defied Israel, Jonathan the son of Shimea David&#8217;s brother slew him. <verse number="8" style="v"/>These were born unto the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">an adversary</char></char></note>Satan stood up against Israel, and moved David to number Israel. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And David said to Joab and to the princes of the people, Go, number Israel from Beer-sheba even to Dan; and bring me word, that I may know the sum of them. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Joab said, Jehovah make his people a hundred times as many as they are: but, my lord the king, are they not all my lord&#8217;s servants? why doth my lord require this thing? why will he be a cause of guilt unto Israel? <verse number="4" style="v"/>Nevertheless the king&#8217;s word prevailed against Joab. Wherefore Joab departed, and went throughout all Israel, and came to Jerusalem. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Joab gave up the sum of the numbering of the people unto David. And all they of Israel were a thousand thousand and a hundred thousand men that drew sword: and Judah was four hundred threescore and ten thousand men that drew sword. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But Levi and Benjamin counted he not among them; for the king&#8217;s word was abominable to Joab. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And God was displeased with this thing; therefore he smote Israel. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And David said unto God, I have sinned greatly, in that I have done this thing: but now, put away, I beseech thee, the iniquity of thy servant; for I have done very foolishly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And Jehovah spake unto Gad, David&#8217;s seer, saying, <verse number="10" style="v"/>Go and speak unto David, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">stretch out unto</char>.</char></note>offer thee three things: choose thee one of them, that I may do it unto thee. <verse number="11" style="v"/>So Gad came to David, and said unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, Take which thou wilt: <verse number="12" style="v"/>either three years of famine; or three months to be consumed before thy foes, while the sword of thine enemies overtaketh thee; or else three days the sword of Jehovah, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and</char></char></note>even pestilence in the land, and the angel of Jehovah destroying throughout all the borders of Israel. Now therefore consider what answer I shall return to him that sent me. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And David said unto Gad, I am in a great strait: let me fall, I pray, into the hand of Jehovah; for very <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">many</char></char></note>great are his mercies: and let me not fall into the hand of man. <verse number="14" style="v"/>So Jehovah sent a pestilence upon Israel; and there fell of Israel seventy thousand men. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And God sent an angel unto Jerusalem to destroy it: and as he was about to destroy, Jehovah beheld, and he repented him of the evil, and said to the destroying angel, It is enough; now stay thy hand. And the angel of Jehovah was standing by the threshing-floor of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="2SA 24:16">2 Sam. 24:16</ref>, etc., <char style="it">Araunah</char></char></note>Ornan the Jebusite. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And David lifted up his eyes, and saw the angel of Jehovah standing between earth and heaven, having a drawn sword in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem. Then David and the elders, clothed in sackcloth, fell upon their faces. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And David said unto God, Is it not I that commanded the people to be numbered? even I it is that have sinned and done very wickedly; but these sheep, what have they done? let thy hand, I pray thee, O Jehovah my God, be against me, and against my father&#8217;s house; but not against thy people, that they should be plagued.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>Then the angel of Jehovah commanded Gad to say to David, that David should go up, and rear an altar unto Jehovah in the threshing-floor of Ornan the Jebusite. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And David went up at the saying of Gad, which he spake in the name of Jehovah. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And Ornan turned back, and saw the angel; and his four sons that were with him hid themselves. Now Ornan was threshing wheat. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And as David came to Ornan, Ornan looked and saw David, and went out of the threshing-floor, and bowed himself to David with his face to the ground. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Then David said to Ornan, Give me the place of this threshing-floor, that I may build thereon an altar unto Jehovah: for the full price shalt thou give it me, that the plague may be stayed from the people. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Ornan said unto David, Take it to thee, and let my lord the king do that which is good in his eyes: lo, I give <char style="add">thee</char> the oxen for burnt-offerings, and the threshing instruments for wood, and the wheat for the meal-offering; I give it all. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And king David said to Ornan, Nay; but I will verily buy it for the full price: for I will not take that which is thine for Jehovah, nor offer a burnt-offering without cost. <verse number="25" style="v"/>So David gave to Ornan for the place six hundred shekels of gold by weight. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And David built there an altar unto Jehovah, and offered burnt-offerings and peace-offerings, and called upon Jehovah; and he answered him from heaven by fire upon the altar of burnt-offering. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And Jehovah commanded the angel; and he put up his sword again into the sheath thereof.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>At that time, when David saw that Jehovah had answered him in the threshing-floor of Ornan the Jebusite, then he sacrificed there. <verse number="29" style="v"/>For the tabernacle of Jehovah, which Moses made in the wilderness, and the altar of burnt-offering, were at that time in the high place at Gibeon. <verse number="30" style="v"/>But David could not go before it to inquire of God; for he was afraid because of the sword of the angel of Jehovah.</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Then David said, This is the house of Jehovah God, and this is the altar of burnt-offering for Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>And David commanded to gather together the sojourners that were in the land of Israel; and he set masons to hew wrought stones to build the house of God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And David prepared iron in abundance for the nails for the doors of the gates, and for the couplings; and brass in abundance without weight; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and cedar-trees without number: for the Sidonians and they of Tyre brought cedar-trees in abundance to David. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And David said, Solomon my son is young and tender, and the house that is to be builded for Jehovah must be exceeding magnificent, of fame and of glory throughout all countries: I will therefore make preparation for it. So David prepared abundantly before his death.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>Then he called for Solomon his son, and charged him to build a house for Jehovah, the God of Israel. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And David said to Solomon <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">According to another reading, <char style="it">My son, as for me etc.</char></char></note>his son, As for me, it was in my heart to build a house unto the name of Jehovah my God. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, Thou hast shed blood abundantly, and hast made great wars: thou shalt not build a house unto my name, because thou hast shed much blood upon the earth in my sight. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Behold, a son shall be born to thee, who shall be a man of rest; and I will give him rest from all his enemies round about; for his name shall be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Peaceful</char>.</char></note>Solomon, and I will give peace and quietness unto Israel in his days. <verse number="10" style="v"/>He shall build a house for my name; and he shall be my son, and I will be his father; and I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel for ever. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Now, my son, Jehovah be with thee; and prosper thou, and build the house of Jehovah thy God, as he hath spoken concerning thee. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Only Jehovah give thee discretion and understanding, and give thee charge concerning Israel; that so thou mayest keep the law of Jehovah thy God. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Then shalt thou prosper, if thou observe to do the statutes and the ordinances which Jehovah charged Moses with concerning Israel: be strong, and of good courage; fear not, neither be dismayed. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Now, behold, in my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">low estate</char></char></note>affliction I have prepared for the house of Jehovah a hundred thousand talents of gold, and a thousand thousand talents of silver, and of brass and iron without weight; for it is in abundance: timber also and stone have I prepared; and thou mayest add thereto. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Moreover there are workmen with thee in abundance, hewers and workers of stone and timber, and all men that are skilful in every manner of work: <verse number="16" style="v"/>of the gold, the silver, and the brass, and the iron, there is no number. Arise and be doing, and Jehovah be with thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>David also commanded all the princes of Israel to help Solomon his son, <char style="add">saying</char>, <verse number="18" style="v"/>Is not Jehovah your God with you? and hath he not given you rest on every side? for he hath delivered the inhabitants of the land into my hand; and the land is subdued before Jehovah, and before his people. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Now set your heart and your soul to seek after Jehovah your God; arise therefore, and build ye the sanctuary of Jehovah God, to bring the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, and the holy vessels of God, into the house that is to be built to the name of Jehovah.</para>
	<chapter number="23" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now David was old and full of days; and he made Solomon his son king over Israel. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he gathered together all the princes of Israel, with the priests and the Levites. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And the Levites were numbered from thirty years old and upward: and their number by their polls, man by man, was thirty and eight thousand. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Of these, twenty and four thousand were to oversee the work of the house of Jehovah; and six thousand were officers and judges; <verse number="5" style="v"/>and four thousand were doorkeepers; and four thousand praised Jehovah with the instruments which I made, <char style="add">said David</char>, to praise therewith. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And David divided them into <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">divisions</char>.</char></note>courses according to the sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>Of the Gershonites: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:17">6:17</ref>, <char style="it">Libni</char>.</char></note>Ladan and Shimei. <verse number="8" style="v"/>The sons of Ladan: Jehiel the chief, and Zetham, and Joel, three. <verse number="9" style="v"/>The sons of Shimei: Shelomoth, and Haziel, and Haran, three. These were the heads of the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of Ladan. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And the sons of Shimei: Jahath, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 23:11">verse 11</ref>, <char style="it">Zizah</char>.</char></note>Zina, and Jeush, and Beriah. These four were the sons of Shimei. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And Jahath was the chief, and Zizah the second: but Jeush and Beriah had not many sons; therefore they became a fathers&#8217; house in one reckoning.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four. <verse number="13" style="v"/>The sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses; and Aaron was separated, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to sanctify as most holy him etc.</char></char></note>that he should sanctify the most holy things, he and his sons, for ever, to burn incense before Jehovah, to minister unto him, and to bless in his name, for ever. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But as for Moses the man of God, his sons were named among the tribe of Levi. <verse number="15" style="v"/>The sons of Moses: Gershom and Eliezer. <verse number="16" style="v"/>The sons of Gershom: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 24:20">24:20</ref>, <char style="it">Shubael</char>.</char></note>Shebuel the chief. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the sons of Eliezer were: Rehabiah the chief; and Eliezer had no other sons; but the sons of Rehabiah were very many. <verse number="18" style="v"/>The sons of Izhar: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 24:22">24:22</ref>, <char style="it">Shelomoth</char>.</char></note>Shelomith the chief. <verse number="19" style="v"/>The sons of Hebron: Jeriah the chief, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth. <verse number="20" style="v"/>The sons of Uzziel: Micah the chief, and Isshiah the second.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Eleazar died, and had no sons, but daughters only: and their brethren the sons of Kish took them <char style="add">to wife</char>. <verse number="23" style="v"/>The sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jeremoth, three.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>These were the sons of Levi after their fathers&#8217; houses, even the heads of the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of those of them that were counted, in the number of names by their polls, who did the work for the service of the house of Jehovah, from twenty years old and upward. <verse number="25" style="v"/>For David said, Jehovah, the God of Israel, hath given rest unto his people; and he dwelleth in Jerusalem for ever: <verse number="26" style="v"/>and also the Levites shall no more have need to carry the tabernacle and all the vessels of it for the service thereof. <verse number="27" style="v"/>For <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in the last acts</char></char></note>by the last words of David the sons of Levi were numbered, from twenty years old and upward. <verse number="28" style="v"/>For <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">their station was at the hand of the sons of Aaron</char>. See <ref loc="NEH 11:24">Neh. 11:24</ref>.</char></note>their office was to wait on the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of Jehovah, in the courts, and in the chambers, and in the purifying of all holy things, even the work of the service of the house of God; <verse number="29" style="v"/>for the showbread also, and for the fine flour for a meal-offering, whether of unleavened wafers, or of that which is baked in the pan, or of that which is soaked, and for all manner of measure and size; <verse number="30" style="v"/>and to stand every morning to thank and praise Jehovah, and likewise at even; <verse number="31" style="v"/>and to offer all burnt-offerings unto Jehovah, on the sabbaths, on the new moons, and on the set feasts, in number according to the ordinance concerning them, continually before Jehovah; <verse number="32" style="v"/>and that they should keep the charge of the tent of meeting, and the charge of the holy place, and the charge of the sons of Aaron their brethren, for the service of the house of Jehovah.</para>
	<chapter number="24" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the courses of the sons of Aaron <char style="add">were these</char>. The sons of Aaron: Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar. <verse number="2" style="v"/>But Nadab and Abihu died before their father, and had no children: therefore Eleazar and Ithamar executed the priest&#8217;s office. <verse number="3" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">And David divided them, even Zadok etc.</char></char></note>And David with Zadok of the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, divided them according to their ordering in their service. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And there were more chief men found of the sons of Eleazar than of the sons of Ithamar; and <char style="add">thus</char> were they divided: of the sons of Eleazar there were sixteen, heads of fathers&#8217; houses; and of the sons of Ithamar, according to their fathers&#8217; houses, eight. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Thus were they divided by lot, one sort with another; for there were princes of the sanctuary, and princes of God, both of the sons of Eleazar, and of the sons of Ithamar. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And Shemaiah the son of Nethanel the scribe, who was of the Levites, wrote them in the presence of the king, and the princes, and Zadok the priest, and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, and the heads of the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of the priests and of the Levites; one fathers&#8217; house being taken for Eleazar, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The Hebrew text has <char style="it">taken, taken</char>.</char></note>one taken for Ithamar.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>Now the first lot came forth to Jehoiarib, the second to Jedaiah, <verse number="8" style="v"/>the third to Harim, the fourth to Seorim, <verse number="9" style="v"/>the fifth to Malchijah, the sixth to Mijamin, <verse number="10" style="v"/>the seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah, <verse number="11" style="v"/>the ninth to Jeshua, the tenth to Shecaniah, <verse number="12" style="v"/>the eleventh to Eliashib, the twelfth to Jakim, <verse number="13" style="v"/>the thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Jeshebeab, <verse number="14" style="v"/>the fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer, <verse number="15" style="v"/>the seventeenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Happizzez, <verse number="16" style="v"/>the nineteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Jehezkel, <verse number="17" style="v"/>the one and twentieth to Jachin, the two and twentieth to Gamul, <verse number="18" style="v"/>the three and twentieth to Delaiah, the four and twentieth to Maaziah. <verse number="19" style="v"/>This was the ordering of them in their service, to come into the house of Jehovah according to the ordinance <char style="add">given</char> unto them by Aaron their father, as Jehovah, the God of Israel, had commanded him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And of the rest of the sons of Levi: of the sons of Amram, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 23:16">23:16</ref>, <char style="it">Shebuel</char>.</char></note>Shubael; of the sons of Shubael, Jehdeiah. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Of Rehabiah: of the sons of Rehabiah, Isshiah the chief. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Of the Izharites, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 23:18">23:18</ref>, <char style="it">Shelomith</char>.</char></note>Shelomoth; of the sons of Shelomoth, Jahath. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And the sons <char style="add">of Hebron</char>: Jeriah <char style="add">the chief</char>, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth. <verse number="24" style="v"/>The sons of Uzziel, Micah; of the sons of Micah, Shamir. <verse number="25" style="v"/>The brother of Micah, Isshiah; of the sons of Isshiah, Zechariah. <verse number="26" style="v"/>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; the sons of Jaaziah: Beno. <verse number="27" style="v"/>The sons of Merari: of Jaaziah, Beno, and Shoham, and Zaccur, and Ibri. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Of Mahli: Eleazar, who had no sons. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Of Kish; the sons of Kish: Jerahmeel. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And the sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth. These were the sons of the Levites after their fathers&#8217; houses. <verse number="31" style="v"/>These likewise cast lots even as their brethren the sons of Aaron in the presence of David the king, and Zadok, and Ahimelech, and the heads of the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of the priests and of the Levites; the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> of the chief even as those of his younger brother.</para>
	<chapter number="25" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Moreover David and the captains of the host set apart for the service certain of the sons of Asaph, and of Heman, and of Jeduthun, who should prophesy with harps, with psalteries, and with cymbals: and the number of them that did the work according to their service was: <verse number="2" style="v"/>of the sons of Asaph: Zaccur, and Joseph, and Nethaniah, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 25:14">verse 14</ref>, <char style="it">Jesharelah</char>.</char></note>Asharelah, the sons of Asaph, under the hand of Asaph, who prophesied <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">by the hands of the king</char>.</char></note>after the order of the king. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Of Jeduthun; the sons of Jeduthun: Gedaliah, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 25:11">verse 11</ref>, <char style="it">Izri</char>.</char></note>Zeri, and Jeshaiah, Hashabiah, and Mattithiah, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">With Shimei, mentioned in <ref loc="1CH 25:17">verse 17</ref></char></note>six, under the hands of their father Jeduthun with the harp, who prophesied in giving thanks and praising Jehovah. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Of Heman; the sons of Heman: Bukkiah, Mattaniah, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 25:18">verse 18</ref>, <char style="it">Azarel</char>.</char></note>Uzziel, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 25:20">verse 20</ref>, <char style="it">Shubael</char>.</char></note>Shebuel, and Jerimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliathah, Giddalti, and Romamti-ezer, Joshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, Mahazioth. <verse number="5" style="v"/>All these were the sons of Heman the king&#8217;s seer in the words of God, to lift up the horn. And God gave to Heman fourteen sons and three daughters. <verse number="6" style="v"/>All these were under the hands of their father for song in the house of Jehovah, with cymbals, psalteries, and harps, for the service of the house of God; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">after the order of the king</char>, even <char style="it">Asaph etc.</char></char></note>Asaph, Jeduthun, and Heman being under the order of the king. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the number of them, with their brethren that were instructed in singing unto Jehovah, even all that were skilful, was two hundred fourscore and eight. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And they cast lots <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">ward against</char> ward, <char style="it">as well etc.</char></char></note>for their offices, all alike, as well the small as the great, the teacher as the scholar.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>Now the first lot came forth for Asaph to Joseph: the second to Gedaliah; he and his brethren and sons were twelve: <verse number="10" style="v"/>the third to Zaccur, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="11" style="v"/>the fourth to Izri, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="12" style="v"/>the fifth to Nethaniah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="13" style="v"/>the sixth to Bukkiah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="14" style="v"/>the seventh to Jesharelah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="15" style="v"/>the eighth to Jeshaiah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="16" style="v"/>the ninth to Mattaniah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="17" style="v"/>the tenth to Shimei, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="18" style="v"/>the eleventh to Azarel, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="19" style="v"/>the twelfth to Hashabiah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="20" style="v"/>for the thirteenth, Shubael, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="21" style="v"/>for the fourteenth, Mattithiah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="22" style="v"/>for the fifteenth to Jeremoth, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="23" style="v"/>for the sixteenth to Hananiah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="24" style="v"/>for the seventeenth to Joshbekashah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="25" style="v"/>for the eighteenth to Hanani, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="26" style="v"/>for the nineteenth to Mallothi, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="27" style="v"/>for the twentieth to Eliathah, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="28" style="v"/>for the one and twentieth to Hothir, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="29" style="v"/>for the two and twentieth to Giddalti, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="30" style="v"/>for the three and twentieth to Mahazioth, his sons and his brethren, twelve: <verse number="31" style="v"/>for the four and twentieth to Romamtiezer, his sons and his brethren, twelve.</para>
	<chapter number="26" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>For the courses of the doorkeepers: of the Korahites, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 26:14">verse 14</ref>, <char style="it">Shelemiah</char>.</char></note>Meshelemiah the son of Kore, of the sons of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 9:19">9:19</ref>, <char style="it">Ebiasaph</char>.</char></note>Asaph. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And Meshelemiah had sons: Zechariah the first-born, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth, <verse number="3" style="v"/>Elam the fifth, Jehohanan the sixth, Eliehoenai the seventh. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Obed-edom had sons: Shemaiah the first-born, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, and Sacar the fourth, and Nethanel the fifth, <verse number="5" style="v"/>Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peullethai the eighth; for God blessed him. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Also unto Shemaiah his son were sons born, that ruled over the house of their father; for they were mighty men of valor. <verse number="7" style="v"/>The sons of Shemaiah: Othni, and Rephael, and Obed, Elzabad, whose brethren were valiant men, Elihu, and Semachiah. <verse number="8" style="v"/>All these were of the sons of Obed-edom: they and their sons and their brethren, able men in strength for the service; threescore and two of Obed-edom. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And Meshelemiah had sons and brethren, valiant men, eighteen. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Also Hosah, of the children of Merari, had sons: Shimri the chief (for though he was not the first-born, yet his father made him chief), <verse number="11" style="v"/>Hilkiah the second, Tebaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth: all the sons and brethren of Hosah were thirteen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Of these were the courses of the doorkeepers, even of the chief men, having <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wards over against their brethren</char></char></note>offices like their brethren, to minister in the house of Jehovah. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And they cast lots, as well the small as the great, according to their fathers&#8217; houses, for every gate. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the lot eastward fell to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 26:1">verse 1</ref>, <char style="it">Meshelemiah</char>.</char></note>Shelemiah. Then for Zechariah his son, a discreet counsellor, they cast lots; and his lot came out northward. <verse number="15" style="v"/>To Obed-edom southward; and to his sons the store-house. <verse number="16" style="v"/>To Shuppim and Hosah westward, by the gate of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Casting forth</char>.</char></note>Shallecheth, at the causeway that goeth up, watch against watch. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Eastward were six Levites, northward four a day, southward four a day, and for the store-house two and two. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the precinct</char></char></note>Parbar westward, four at the causeway, and two at <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the precinct</char></char></note>Parbar. <verse number="19" style="v"/>These were the courses of the doorkeepers; of the sons of the Korahites, and of the sons of Merari.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And of the Levites, Ahijah was over the treasures of the house of God, and over the treasures of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">holy things</char>.</char></note>dedicated things. <verse number="21" style="v"/>The sons of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 6:17">6:17</ref>, <char style="it">Libni</char>.</char></note>Ladan, the sons of the Gershonites belonging to Ladan, the heads of the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> belonging to Ladan the Gershonite: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 23:8">23:8</ref>, <char style="it">Jehiel</char>.</char></note>Jehieli. <verse number="22" style="v"/>The sons of Jehieli: Zetham, and Joel his brother, over the treasures of the house of Jehovah. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Of the Amramites, of the Izharites, of the Hebronites, of the Uzzielites: <verse number="24" style="v"/>and Shebuel the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, was ruler over the treasures. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And his brethren: of Eliezer <char style="add">came</char> Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zichri his son, and Shelomoth his son. <verse number="26" style="v"/>This Shelomoth and his brethren were over all the treasures of the dedicated things, which David the king, and the heads of the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char>, the captains over thousands and hundreds, and the captains of the host, had dedicated. <verse number="27" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Out of the battles and the spoil</char>.</char></note>Out of the spoil won in battles did they dedicate to repair the house of Jehovah. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And all that Samuel the seer, and Saul the son of Kish, and Abner the son of Ner, and Joab the son of Zeruiah, had dedicated, whosoever had dedicated anything, it was under the hand of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Shelomith</char>.</char></note>Shelomoth, and of his brethren.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v"/>Of the Izharites, Chenaniah and his sons were for the outward business over Israel, for officers and judges. <verse number="30" style="v"/>Of the Hebronites, Hashabiah and his brethren, men of valor, a thousand and seven hundred, had the oversight of Israel beyond the Jordan westward, for all the business of Jehovah, and for the service of the king. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Of the Hebronites was Jerijah the chief, even of the Hebronites, according to their generations by fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char>. In the fortieth year of the reign of David they were sought for, and there were found among them mighty men of valor at Jazer of Gilead. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And his brethren, men of valor, were two thousand and seven hundred, heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char>, whom king David made overseers over the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of the Manassites, for every matter pertaining to God, and for the affairs of the king.</para>
	<chapter number="27" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now the children of Israel after their number, <char style="add">to wit</char>, the heads of fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char> and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and their officers that served the king, in any matter of the courses which came in and went out month by month throughout all the months of the year&#8212;of every course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Over the first course for the first month was Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="3" style="v"/><char style="add">He was</char> of the children of Perez, the chief of all the captains of the host for the first month. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And over the course of the second month was Dodai the Ahohite, and his course; and Mikloth the ruler: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="5" style="v"/>The third captain of the host for the third month was Benaiah, the son of Jehoiada the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">chief minister</char>. See <ref loc="2SA 8:18">2 Sam. 8:18</ref>.</char></note>priest, chief: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="6" style="v"/>This is that Benaiah, who was the mighty man of the thirty, and over the thirty: and <char style="add">of</char> his course was Ammizabad his son. <verse number="7" style="v"/>The fourth <char style="add">captain</char> for the fourth month was Asahel the brother of Joab, and Zebadiah his son after him: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="8" style="v"/>The fifth captain for the fifth month was Shamhuth the Izrahite: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="9" style="v"/>The sixth <char style="add">captain</char> for the sixth month was Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="10" style="v"/>The seventh <char style="add">captain</char> for the seventh month was Helez the Pelonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="11" style="v"/>The eighth <char style="add">captain</char> for the eighth month was Sibbecai the Hushathite, of the Zerahites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="12" style="v"/>The ninth <char style="add">captain</char> for the ninth month was Abiezer the Anathothite, of the Benjamites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="13" style="v"/>The tenth <char style="add">captain</char> for the tenth month was Maharai the Netophathite, of the Zerahites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="14" style="v"/>The eleventh <char style="add">captain</char> for the eleventh month was Benaiah the Pirathonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. <verse number="15" style="v"/>The twelfth <char style="add">captain</char> for the twelfth month was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1CH 11:30">11:30</ref>, <char style="it">Heled</char>.</char></note>Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>Furthermore over the tribes of Israel: of the Reubenites was Eliezer the son of Zichri the ruler: of the Simeonites, Shephatiah the son of Maacah: <verse number="17" style="v"/>of Levi, Hashabiah the son of Kemuel: of Aaron, Zadok: <verse number="18" style="v"/>of Judah, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">In <ref loc="1SA 16:6">1 Sam. 16:6</ref>, <char style="it">Eliab</char>.</char></note>Elihu, one of the brethren of David: of Issachar, Omri the son of Michael: <verse number="19" style="v"/>of Zebulun, Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah: of Naphtali, Jeremoth the son of Azriel: <verse number="20" style="v"/>of the children of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Azaziah: of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Joel the son of Pedaiah: <verse number="21" style="v"/>of the half-<char style="add">tribe</char> of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo the son of Zechariah: of Benjamin, Jaasiel the son of Abner: <verse number="22" style="v"/>of Dan, Azarel the son of Jeroham. These were the captains of the tribes of Israel. <verse number="23" style="v"/>But David took not the number of them from twenty years old and under, because Jehovah had said he would increase Israel like to the stars of heaven. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Joab the son of Zeruiah began to number, but finished not; and there came wrath for this upon Israel; neither was the number put into the account in the chronicles of king David.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And over the king&#8217;s treasures was Azmaveth the son of Adiel: and over the treasures in the fields, in the cities, and in the villages, and in the castles, was Jonathan the son of Uzziah: <verse number="26" style="v"/>and over them that did the work of the field for tillage of the ground was Ezri the son of Chelub: <verse number="27" style="v"/>and over the vineyards was Shimei the Ramathite: and over the increase of the vineyards for the wine-cellars was Zabdi the Shiphmite: <verse number="28" style="v"/>and over the olive-trees and the sycomore-trees that were in the lowland was Baal-hanan the Gederite: and over the cellars of oil was Joash: <verse number="29" style="v"/>and over the herds that fed in Sharon was Shitrai the Sharonite: and over the herds that were in the valleys was Shaphat the son of Adlai: <verse number="30" style="v"/>and over the camels was Obil the Ishmaelite: and over the asses was Jehdeiah the Meronothite: and over the flocks was Jaziz the Hagrite. <verse number="31" style="v"/>All these were the rulers of the substance which was king David&#8217;s.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v"/>Also Jonathan, David&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">brother&#8217;s son</char></char></note>uncle, was a counsellor, a man of understanding, and a scribe: and Jehiel the son of Hachmoni was with the king&#8217;s sons: <verse number="33" style="v"/>and Ahithophel was the king&#8217;s counsellor: and Hushai the Archite was the king&#8217;s friend: <verse number="34" style="v"/>and after Ahithophel was Jehoiada the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar: and the captain of the king&#8217;s host was Joab.</para>
	<chapter number="28" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And David assembled all the princes of Israel, the princes of the tribes, and the captains of the companies that served the king by course, and the captains of thousands, and the captains of hundreds, and the rulers over all the substance and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cattle</char></char></note>possessions of the king and of his sons, with the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">eunuchs</char></char></note>officers, and the mighty men, even all the mighty men of valor, unto Jerusalem. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Then David the king stood up upon his feet, and said, Hear me, my brethren, and my people: as for me, it was in my heart to build a house of rest for the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, and for the footstool of our God; and I had made ready for the building. <verse number="3" style="v"/>But God said unto me, Thou shalt not build a house for my name, because thou art a man of war, and hast shed blood. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Howbeit Jehovah, the God of Israel, chose me out of all the house of my father to be king over Israel for ever: for he hath chosen Judah to be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">leader</char></char></note>prince; and in the house of Judah, the house of my father; and among the sons of my father he took pleasure in me to make me king over all Israel; <verse number="5" style="v"/>and of all my sons (for Jehovah hath given me many sons), he hath chosen Solomon my son to sit upon the throne of the kingdom of Jehovah over Israel. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he said unto me, Solomon thy son, he shall build my house and my courts; for I have chosen him to be my son, and I will be his father. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And I will establish his kingdom for ever, if he be constant to do my commandments and mine ordinances, as at this day. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Now therefore, in the sight of all Israel, the assembly of Jehovah, and in the audience of our God, observe and seek out all the commandments of Jehovah your God; that ye may possess this good land, and leave it for an inheritance to your children after you for ever.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And thou, Solomon my son, know thou the God of thy father, and serve him with a perfect heart and with a willing mind; for Jehovah searcheth all hearts, and understandeth all the imaginations of the thoughts. If thou seek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forsake him, he will cast thee off for ever. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Take heed now; for Jehovah hath chosen thee to build a house for the sanctuary: be strong, and do it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>Then David gave to Solomon his son the pattern of the porch <char style="add">of the temple</char>, and of the houses thereof, and of the treasuries thereof, and of the upper rooms thereof, and of the inner chambers thereof, and of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">house</char>.</char></note>place of the mercy-seat; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and the pattern of all that he had <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in his spirit</char></char></note>by the Spirit, for the courts of the house of Jehovah, and for all the chambers round about, for the treasuries of the house of God, and for the treasuries of the dedicated things; <verse number="13" style="v"/>also for the courses of the priests and the Levites, and for all the work of the service of the house of Jehovah, and for all the vessels of service in the house of Jehovah; <verse number="14" style="v"/>of gold by weight for the <char style="add">vessels of</char> gold, for all vessels of every kind of service; <char style="add">of silver</char> for all the vessels of silver by weight, for all vessels of every kind of service; <verse number="15" style="v"/>by weight also for the candlesticks of gold, and for the lamps thereof, of gold, by weight for every candlestick and for the lamps thereof; and for the candlesticks of silver, <char style="add">silver</char> by weight for <char style="add">every</char> candlestick and for the lamps thereof, according to the use of every candlestick; <verse number="16" style="v"/>and the gold by weight for the tables of showbread, for every table; and silver for the tables of silver; <verse number="17" style="v"/>and the flesh-hooks, and the basins, and the cups, of pure gold; and for the golden bowls by weight for every bowl; and for the silver bowls by weight for every bowl; <verse number="18" style="v"/>and for the altar of incense refined gold by weight; and gold for the pattern of the chariot, <char style="add">even</char> the cherubim, that spread out <char style="add">their wings</char>, and covered the ark of the covenant of Jehovah. <verse number="19" style="v"/>All this, <char style="add">said David</char>, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Jehovah made me understand in writing by his hand upon me, even etc.</char></char></note>have I been made to understand in writing from the hand of Jehovah, even all the works of this pattern.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And David said to Solomon his son, Be strong and of good courage, and do it: fear not, nor be dismayed; for Jehovah God, even my God, is with thee; he will not fail thee, nor forsake thee, until all the work for the service of the house of Jehovah be finished. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And, behold, there are the courses of the priests and the Levites, for all the service of the house of God: and there shall be with thee in all manner of work every willing man that hath skill, for any manner of service: also the captains and all the people will be wholly at thy commandment.</para>
	<chapter number="29" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And David the king said unto all the assembly, Solomon my son, whom alone God hath chosen, is yet young and tender, and the work is great; for the palace is not for man, but for Jehovah God. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Now I have prepared with all my might for the house of my God the gold for the <char style="add">things of</char> gold, and the silver for the <char style="add">things of</char> silver, and the brass for the <char style="add">things of</char> brass, the iron for the <char style="add">things of</char> iron, and wood for the <char style="add">things of</char> wood; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">beryl</char></char></note>onyx stones, and <char style="add">stones</char> to be set, stones for inlaid work, and of divers colors, and all manner of precious stones, and marble stones in abundance. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Moreover also, because I have set my affection on the house of my God, seeing that I have a treasure of mine own of gold and silver, I give it unto the house of my God, over and above all that I have prepared for the holy house, <verse number="4" style="v"/>even three thousand talents of gold, of the gold of Ophir, and seven thousand talents of refined silver, wherewith to overlay the walls of the houses; <verse number="5" style="v"/>of gold for the <char style="add">things of</char> gold, and of silver for the <char style="add">things of</char> silver, and for all manner of work <char style="add">to be made</char> by the hands of artificers. Who then offereth willingly <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">to fill his hand</char>.</char></note>to consecrate himself this day unto Jehovah?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>Then the princes of the fathers&#8217; <char style="add">houses</char>, and the princes of the tribes of Israel, and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, with the rulers over the king&#8217;s work, offered willingly; <verse number="7" style="v"/>and they gave for the service of the house of God of gold five thousand talents and ten thousand darics, and of silver ten thousand talents, and of brass eighteen thousand talents, and of iron a hundred thousand talents. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And they with whom <char style="add">precious</char> stones were found gave them to the treasure of the house of Jehovah, under the hand of Jehiel the Gershonite. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Then the people rejoiced, for that they offered willingly, because with a perfect heart they offered willingly to Jehovah: and David the king also rejoiced with great joy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>Wherefore David blessed Jehovah before all the assembly; and David said, Blessed be thou, O Jehovah, the God of Israel our father, for ever and ever. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Thine, O Jehovah, is the greatness, and the power, and the glory, and the victory, and the majesty: for all that is in the heavens and in the earth <char style="add">is thine</char>; thine is the kingdom, O Jehovah, and thou art exalted as head above all. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Both riches and honor come of thee, and thou rulest over all; and in thy hand is power and might; and in thy hand it is to make great, and to give strength unto all. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Now therefore, our God, we thank thee, and praise thy glorious name. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But who am I, and what is my people, that we should <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">retain strength</char>.</char></note>be able to offer so willingly after this sort? for all things come of thee, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">of thy hand</char>.</char></note>of thine own have we given thee. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For we are strangers before thee, and sojourners, as all our fathers were: our days on the earth are as a shadow, and there is no <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">hope</char>.</char></note>abiding. <verse number="16" style="v"/>O Jehovah our God, all this store that we have prepared to build thee a house for thy holy name cometh of thy hand, and is all thine own. <verse number="17" style="v"/>I know also, my God, that thou triest the heart, and hast pleasure in uprightness. As for me, in the uprightness of my heart I have willingly offered all these things: and now have I seen with joy thy people, that are present here, offer willingly unto thee. <verse number="18" style="v"/>O Jehovah, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Israel, our fathers, keep this for ever in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of thy people, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">establish</char></char></note>prepare their heart unto thee; <verse number="19" style="v"/>and give unto Solomon my son a perfect heart, to keep thy commandments, thy testimonies, and thy statutes, and to do all these things, and to build the palace, for which I have made provision.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And David said to all the assembly, Now bless Jehovah your God. And all the assembly blessed Jehovah, the God of their fathers, and bowed down their heads, and worshipped Jehovah, and the king. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And they sacrificed sacrifices unto Jehovah, and offered burnt-offerings unto Jehovah, on the morrow after that day, even a thousand bullocks, a thousand rams, and a thousand lambs, with their drink-offerings, and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel, <verse number="22" style="v"/>and did eat and drink before Jehovah on that day with great gladness.</para>
	<para style="p">And they made Solomon the son of David king the second time, and anointed him unto Jehovah to be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">leader</char></char></note>prince, and Zadok to be priest. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Then Solomon sat on the throne of Jehovah as king instead of David his father, and prospered; and all Israel obeyed him. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And all the princes, and the mighty men, and all the sons likewise of king David, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">gave the hand under Solomon</char>.</char></note>submitted themselves unto Solomon the king. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And Jehovah magnified Solomon exceedingly in the sight of all Israel, and bestowed upon him such royal majesty as had not been on any king before him in Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>Now David the son of Jesse reigned over all Israel. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And the time that he reigned over Israel was forty years; seven years reigned he in Hebron, and thirty and three <char style="add">years</char> reigned he in Jerusalem. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And he died in a good old age, full of days, riches, and honor: and Solomon his son reigned in his stead. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Now the acts of David the king, first and last, behold, they are written in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">words</char>.</char></note>history of Samuel the seer, and in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">words</char>.</char></note>history of Nathan the prophet, and in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">words</char>.</char></note>history of Gad the seer, <verse number="30" style="v"/>with all his reign and his might, and the times that went over him, and over Israel, and over all the kingdoms of the countries.</para>
</usx>