<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="ECC" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>The words of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Koheleth</char>.</char></note>the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher; vanity of vanities, all is vanity. <verse number="3" style="v"/>What profit hath man of all his labor wherein he laboreth under the sun? <verse number="4" style="v"/>One generation goeth, and another generation cometh; but the earth abideth for ever. <verse number="5" style="v"/>The sun also ariseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to its place where it ariseth. <verse number="6" style="v"/>The wind goeth toward the south, and turneth about unto the north; it turneth about continually in its course, and the wind returneth again to its circuits. <verse number="7" style="v"/>All the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">torrents</char></char></note>rivers run into the sea, yet the sea is not full; unto the place whither the rivers go, thither they go again. <verse number="8" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">All words are feeble</char></char></note>All things are full of weariness; man cannot utter <char style="add">it</char>: the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>That which hath been is that which shall be; and that which hath been done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Is there a thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new? it hath been long ago, in the ages which were before us. <verse number="11" style="v"/>There is no remembrance of the former <char style="add">generations</char>; neither shall there be any remembrance of the latter <char style="add">generations</char> that are to come, among those that shall come after. <verse number="12" style="v"/>I the Preacher was king over Israel in Jerusalem. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And I applied my heart to seek and to search out by wisdom concerning all that is done under heaven: it is a sore travail that God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised therewith. <verse number="14" style="v"/>I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and, behold, all is vanity and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a feeding on wind</char> (See <ref loc="HOS 12:1">Hos. 12:1</ref>). Or, <char style="it">vexation of spirit</char> (and so elsewhere).</char></note>a striving after wind. <verse number="15" style="v"/>That which is crooked cannot be made straight; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">defect</char>.</char></note>that which is wanting cannot be numbered. <verse number="16" style="v"/>I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I have gotten me great wisdom <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">yea, more than all</char></char></note>above all that were before me <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">over</char>.</char></note>in Jerusalem; yea, my heart <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">hath seen abundantly</char>.</char></note>hath had great experience of wisdom and knowledge. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I perceived that this also was a striving after wind. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For in much wisdom is much grief; and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>I said in my heart, Come now, I will prove thee with mirth; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and thou shalt enjoy</char></char></note>therefore enjoy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">good</char></char></note>pleasure: and, behold, this also was vanity. <verse number="2" style="v"/>I said of laughter, It is mad; and of mirth, What doeth it? <verse number="3" style="v"/>I searched in my heart how to cheer my flesh with wine, my heart yet <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">holding its course</char></char></note>guiding <char style="add">me</char> with wisdom, and how to lay hold on folly, till I might see what it was good for the sons of men that they should do under heaven <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">the number of days of their life</char>.</char></note>all the days of their life. <verse number="4" style="v"/>I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards; <verse number="5" style="v"/>I made me gardens and parks, and I planted trees in them of all kinds of fruit; <verse number="6" style="v"/>I made me pools of water, to water therefrom the forest where trees were reared; <verse number="7" style="v"/>I bought men-servants and maid-servants, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of herds and flocks, above all that were before me in Jerusalem; <verse number="8" style="v"/>I gathered me also silver and gold, and the treasure of kings and of the provinces; I gat me men-singers and women-singers, and the delights of the sons of men, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">concubines very many</char>. The meaning of the Hebrew is very uncertain.</char></note>musical instruments, and that of all sorts. <verse number="9" style="v"/>So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stood by me</char></char></note>remained with me. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them; I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced because of all my labor; and this was my portion from all my labor. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labor that I had labored to do; and, behold, all was vanity and a striving after wind, and there was no profit under the sun. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and folly: for what <char style="add">can</char> the man <char style="add">do</char> that cometh <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">after the king, even him whom they made king long ago?</char> Or, <char style="it">after the king, in those things which have been already done?</char></char></note>after the king? <char style="add">even</char> that which hath been done long ago. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Then I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness. <verse number="14" style="v"/>The wise man&#8217;s eyes are in his head, and the fool walketh in darkness: and yet I perceived that one event happeneth to them all. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Then said I in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool, so will it happen even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then said I in my heart, that this also is vanity. <verse number="16" style="v"/>For of the wise man, even as of the fool, there is no remembrance for ever; seeing that in the days to come all will have been long forgotten. And how doth the wise man die even as the fool! <verse number="17" style="v"/>So I hated life, because the work that is wrought under the sun was grievous unto me; for all is vanity and a striving after wind. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And I hated all my labor wherein I labored under the sun, seeing that I must leave it unto the man that shall be after me. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And who knoweth whether he will be a wise man or a fool? yet will he have rule over all my labor wherein I have labored, and wherein I have showed myself wise under the sun. This also is vanity. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Therefore I turned about to cause my heart to despair concerning all the labor wherein I had labored under the sun. <verse number="21" style="v"/>For there is a man whose labor is with wisdom, and with knowledge, and with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">success</char></char></note>skilfulness; yet to a man that hath not labored therein shall he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">give</char>.</char></note>leave it for his portion. This also is vanity and a great evil. <verse number="22" style="v"/>For what hath a man of all his labor, and of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">vexation</char></char></note>striving of his heart, wherein he laboreth under the sun? <verse number="23" style="v"/>For all his days are <char style="add">but</char> sorrows, and his travail is grief; yea, even in the night his heart taketh no rest. This also is vanity. <verse number="24" style="v"/>There is nothing better for a man <char style="add">than</char> that he should eat and drink, and make his soul enjoy good in his labor. This also I saw, that it is from the hand of God. <verse number="25" style="v"/>For who can eat, or who can <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hasten</char> thereto</char></note>have enjoyment, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">According to Septuagint and Syriac, <char style="it">apart from him</char>.</char></note>more than I? <verse number="26" style="v"/>For to the man that pleaseth him <char style="add">God</char> giveth wisdom, and knowledge, and joy; but to the sinner he giveth travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to him that pleaseth God. This also is vanity and a striving after wind.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>For everything there is a season, and a time for every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">matter</char></char></note>purpose under heaven: <verse number="2" style="v"/>a time to be born, and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to pluck up that which is planted; <verse number="3" style="v"/>a time to kill, and a time to heal; a time to break down, and a time to build up; <verse number="4" style="v"/>a time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance; <verse number="5" style="v"/>a time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together; a time to embrace, and a time to refrain from embracing; <verse number="6" style="v"/>a time to seek, and a time to lose; a time to keep, and a time to cast away; <verse number="7" style="v"/>a time to rend, and a time to sew; a time to keep silence, and a time to speak; <verse number="8" style="v"/>a time to love, and a time to hate; a time for war, and a time for peace. <verse number="9" style="v"/>What profit hath he that worketh in that wherein he laboreth? <verse number="10" style="v"/>I have seen the travail which God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised therewith. <verse number="11" style="v"/>He hath made everything beautiful in its time: also he hath set <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the world</char></char></note>eternity in their heart, yet so that man cannot find out the work that God hath done from the beginning even to the end. <verse number="12" style="v"/>I know that there is nothing better for them, than to rejoice, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to get good</char></char></note>to do good so long as they live. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy good in all his labor, is the gift of God. <verse number="14" style="v"/>I know that, whatsoever God doeth, it shall be for ever: nothing can be put to it, nor anything taken from it; and God hath done it, that men should fear before him. <verse number="15" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">That which hath been is now</char></char></note>That which is hath been long ago; and that which is to be hath long ago been: and God seeketh again that which is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">driven away</char>.</char></note>passed away. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And moreover I saw under the sun, in the place of justice, that wickedness was there; and in the place of righteousness, that wickedness was there. <verse number="17" style="v"/>I said in my heart, God will judge the righteous and the wicked; for there is a time there for every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">matter</char></char></note>purpose and for every work. <verse number="18" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">I said in my heart concerning the sons of men.</char> It is <char style="it">that God etc.</char></char></note>I said in my heart, <char style="add">It is</char> because of the sons of men, that God may prove them, and that they may see that they themselves are <char style="add">but as</char> beasts. <verse number="19" style="v"/>For that which befalleth the sons of men befalleth beasts; even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea, they have all one <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">spirit</char></char></note>breath; and man hath no preeminence above the beasts: for all is vanity. <verse number="20" style="v"/>All go unto one place; all are of the dust, and all turn to dust again. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Who knoweth the spirit <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">of the sons of men</char>.</char></note>of man, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that goeth</char></char></note>whether it goeth upward, and the spirit of the beast, whether it goeth downward to the earth? <verse number="22" style="v"/>Wherefore I saw that there is nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his works; for that is his portion: for who shall bring him <char style="add">back</char> to see what shall be after him?</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Then I returned and saw all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and, behold, the tears of such as were oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was power; but they had no comforter. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Wherefore I praised the dead that have been long dead more than the living that are yet alive; <verse number="3" style="v"/>yea, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">better than they both is he that etc.</char></char></note>better than them both <char style="add">did I esteem</char> him that hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Then I saw all labor and every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">successful</char></char></note>skilful work, that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">it cometh of a man&#8217;s rivalry with his neighbor</char></char></note>for this a man is envied of his neighbor. This also is vanity and a striving after wind. <verse number="5" style="v"/>The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Better is a handful, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of</char></char></note>with quietness, than two handfuls <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of</char></char></note>with labor and striving after wind. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Then I returned and saw vanity under the sun. <verse number="8" style="v"/>There is one that is alone, and he hath not a second; yea, he hath neither son nor brother; yet is there no end of all his labor, neither are his eyes satisfied with riches. For whom then, <char style="add">saith he</char>, do I labor, and deprive my soul of good? This also is vanity, yea, it is a sore travail. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Two are better than one, because they have a good reward for their labor. <verse number="10" style="v"/>For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow; but woe to him that is alone when he falleth, and hath not another to lift him up. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Again, if two lie together, then they have warmth; but how can one be warm <char style="add">alone</char>? <verse number="12" style="v"/>And if a man prevail against him that is alone, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Better is a poor and wise youth than an old and foolish king, who knoweth not how to receive admonition any more. <verse number="14" style="v"/>For out of prison he came forth to be king; yea, even in his kingdom he was born poor. <verse number="15" style="v"/>I saw all the living that walk under the sun, that they were with the youth, the second, that stood up in his stead. <verse number="16" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">There is no end, in the mind of all the people, to all that hath been before them; they also etc.</char></char></note>There was no end of all the people, even of all them over whom he was: yet they that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and a striving after wind.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God; for to draw nigh to hear is better than to give the sacrifice of fools: for they know not that they do evil. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be hasty to utter <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a word</char></char></note>anything before God; for God is in heaven, and thou upon earth: therefore let thy words be few. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For a dream cometh with a multitude of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">travail</char></char></note>business, and a fool&#8217;s voice with a multitude of words. <verse number="4" style="v"/>When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he hath no pleasure in fools: pay that which thou vowest. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Better is it that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou shouldest vow and not pay. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say thou before the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">messenger</char> of God. See <ref loc="MAL 2:7">Mal. 2:7</ref>.</char></note>angel, that it was an error: wherefore should God be angry at thy voice, and destroy the work of thy hands? <verse number="7" style="v"/>For in the multitude of dreams there are vanities, and in many words: but fear thou God. <verse number="8" style="v"/>If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and the violent taking away of justice and righteousness in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the state</char></char></note>a province, marvel not at the matter: for one higher than the high regardeth; and there are higher than they. <verse number="9" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">But the profit of a land every way is a king that maketh himself servant to the field</char> (or, <char style="it">is a king over the cultivated field</char>)</char></note>Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king <char style="add">himself</char> is served by the field. <verse number="10" style="v"/>He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he that loveth abundance, with increase: this also is vanity. <verse number="11" style="v"/>When goods increase, they are increased that eat them; and what advantage is there to the owner thereof, save the beholding <char style="add">of them</char> with his eyes? <verse number="12" style="v"/>The sleep of a laboring man is sweet, whether he eat little or much; but the fulness of the rich will not suffer him to sleep. <verse number="13" style="v"/>There is a grievous evil which I have seen under the sun, <char style="add">namely</char>, riches kept by the owner thereof to his hurt: <verse number="14" style="v"/>and those riches perish by evil <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">travail</char></char></note>adventure; and if he hath begotten a son, there is nothing in his hand. <verse number="15" style="v"/>As he came forth from his mother&#8217;s womb, naked shall he go again as he came, and shall take nothing for his labor, which he may carry away in his hand. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And this also is a grievous evil, that in all points as he came, so shall he go: and what profit hath he that he laboreth for the wind? <verse number="17" style="v"/>All his days also he eateth in darkness, and he is sore vexed, and hath sickness and wrath. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Behold, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that which I have seen: it is good and comely for one etc.</char></char></note>that which I have seen to be good and to be comely is for one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy good in all his labor, wherein he laboreth under the sun, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">the number of the days</char>.</char></note>all the days of his life which God hath given him: for this is his portion. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labor&#8212;this is the gift of God. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For he shall not much remember the days of his life; because God answereth <char style="add">him</char> in the joy of his heart.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it is heavy upon men: <verse number="2" style="v"/>a man to whom God giveth riches, wealth, and honor, so that he lacketh nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but an alien eateth it; this is vanity, and it is an evil disease. <verse number="3" style="v"/>If a man beget a hundred children, and live many years, so that the days of his years are many, but his soul be not filled with good, and moreover he have no burial; I say, that an untimely birth is better than he: <verse number="4" style="v"/>for it cometh in vanity, and departeth in darkness, and the name thereof is covered with darkness; <verse number="5" style="v"/>moreover it hath not seen the sun <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">neither had any knowledge</char></char></note>nor known it; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">it is better with this than with the other</char></char></note>this hath rest rather than the other: <verse number="6" style="v"/>yea, though he live a thousand years twice told, and yet enjoy no good, do not all go to one place? <verse number="7" style="v"/>All the labor of man is for his mouth, and yet the appetite is not filled. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For what advantage hath the wise more than the fool? <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, or <char style="it">the poor man that hath understanding, in walking before the living</char></char></note><char style="add">or</char> what hath the poor man, that knoweth how to walk before the living? <verse number="9" style="v"/>Better is the sight of the eyes than the wandering of the desire: this also is vanity and a striving after wind. <verse number="10" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Whatsoever he be, his name was given him long ago, and it is known that he is man</char></char></note>Whatsoever hath been, the name thereof was given long ago; and it is known what <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Adam</char>. See <ref loc="GEN 2:7">Gen. 2:7</ref>.</char></note>man is; neither can he contend with him that is mightier than he. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Seeing there are many <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">words</char></char></note>things that increase vanity, what is man the better? <verse number="12" style="v"/>For who knoweth what is good for man in <char style="add">his</char> life, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">the number of the days</char>.</char></note>all the days of his vain life which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can tell a man what shall be after him under the sun?</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>A <char style="add">good</char> name is better than precious oil; and the day of death, than the day of one&#8217;s birth. <verse number="2" style="v"/>It is better to go to the house of mourning than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the end of all men; and the living will lay it to his heart. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Sorrow is better than laughter; for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">better</char></char></note>glad. <verse number="4" style="v"/>The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house of mirth. <verse number="5" style="v"/>It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the fool: this also is vanity. <verse number="7" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">For</char></char></note>Surely extortion maketh the wise man foolish; and a bribe destroyeth the understanding. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Better is the end of a thing than the beginning thereof; <char style="add">and</char> the patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Be not hasty in thy spirit to be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">vexed</char></char></note>angry; for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">vexation</char></char></note>anger resteth in the bosom of fools. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Say not thou, What is the cause that the former days were better than these? for thou dost not inquire <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">out of wisdom</char>.</char></note>wisely concerning this. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Wisdom <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">is good together with an inheritance, and profitable unto them etc.</char></char></note>is as good as an inheritance; yea, more excellent is it for them that see the sun. <verse number="12" style="v"/>For wisdom is a defence, even as money is a defence; but the excellency of knowledge is, that wisdom preserveth the life of him that hath it. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Consider the work of God: for who can make that straight, which he hath made crooked? <verse number="14" style="v"/>In the day of prosperity be joyful, and in the day of adversity consider; yea, God hath made the one side by side with the other, to the end that man should not find out anything <char style="add">that shall be</char> after him. <verse number="15" style="v"/>All this have I seen in my days of vanity: there is a righteous man that perisheth in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man that prolongeth <char style="add">his life</char> in his evil-doing. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Be not righteous overmuch; neither make thyself overwise: why shouldest thou destroy thyself? <verse number="17" style="v"/>Be not overmuch wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die before thy time? <verse number="18" style="v"/>It is good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also from that withdraw not thy hand: for he that feareth God shall come forth from them all. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Wisdom is a strength to the wise man more than ten rulers that are in a city. <verse number="20" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">For</char></char></note>Surely there is not a righteous man upon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth not. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Also <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">give not thy heart</char>.</char></note>take not heed unto all words that are spoken, lest thou hear thy servant curse thee; <verse number="22" style="v"/>for oftentimes also thine own heart knoweth that thou thyself likewise hast cursed others. <verse number="23" style="v"/>All this have I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">tried by</char></char></note>proved in wisdom: I said, I will be wise; but it was far from me. <verse number="24" style="v"/>That which <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hath been</char></char></note>is, is far off and exceeding deep; who can find it out? <verse number="25" style="v"/>I turned about, and my heart <char style="add">was set</char> to know and to search out, and to seek wisdom and the reason <char style="add">of things</char>, and to know <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the wickedness of folly, and foolishness</char> which is <char style="it">madness</char></char></note>that wickedness is folly, and that foolishness is madness. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And I find more bitter than death the woman <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">who is a snare, and her heart is</char> as <char style="it">nets</char></char></note>whose heart is snares and nets, <char style="add">and</char> whose hands are bands: whoso pleaseth God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Behold, this have I found, saith the Preacher, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, weighing <char style="it">one thing after another, to find out the reason</char></char></note><char style="add">laying</char> one thing to another, to find out the account; <verse number="28" style="v"/>which my soul still seeketh, but I have not found: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all those have I not found. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Behold, this only have I found: that God made man upright; but they have sought out many inventions.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Who is as the wise man? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? A man&#8217;s wisdom maketh his face to shine, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">strength</char>.</char></note>hardness of his face is changed. <verse number="2" style="v"/>I <char style="add">counsel thee</char>, Keep the king&#8217;s command, and that in regard of the oath of God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Be not hasty to go out of his presence; persist not in an evil thing: for he doeth whatsoever pleaseth him. <verse number="4" style="v"/>For the king&#8217;s word <char style="add">hath</char> power; and who may say unto him, What doest thou? <verse number="5" style="v"/>Whoso keepeth the commandment shall know no evil thing; and a wise man&#8217;s heart discerneth time and judgment: <verse number="6" style="v"/>for to every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">matter</char></char></note>purpose there is a time and judgment; because the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">evil</char></char></note>misery of man is great upon him: <verse number="7" style="v"/>for he knoweth not that which shall be; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for</char> even <char style="it">when it cometh to pass, who shall declare it unto him?</char></char></note>for who can tell him how it shall be? <verse number="8" style="v"/>There is no man that hath power over the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wind</char></char></note>spirit to retain the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wind</char></char></note>spirit; neither hath he power over the day of death; and there is no discharge <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in battle</char></char></note>in war: neither shall wickedness deliver him that is given to it. <verse number="9" style="v"/>All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work that is done under the sun: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">what time one man had etc.</char></char></note><char style="add">there is</char> a time wherein one man hath power over another <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to his own hurt</char></char></note>to his hurt. <verse number="10" style="v"/>So I saw the wicked buried, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">who had come and gone away from the holy place; and they were forgotten in the city where they had so done</char>. Or, <char style="it">and men came and went etc.</char></char></note>and they came <char style="add">to the grave</char>; and they that had done right went away from the holy place, and were forgotten in the city: this also is vanity. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">emboldened</char></char></note>fully set in them to do evil. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Though a sinner do evil a hundred times, and prolong his <char style="add">days</char>, yet surely I know that it shall be well with them that fear God, that fear before him: <verse number="13" style="v"/>but it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he prolong <char style="add">his</char> days, <char style="add">which are</char> as a shadow; because he feareth not before God. <verse number="14" style="v"/>There is a vanity which is done upon the earth, that there are righteous men unto whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked; again, there are wicked men to whom it happeneth according to the work of the righteous: I said that this also is vanity. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be joyful: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and that this should accompany him</char></char></note>for that shall abide with him in his labor <char style="add">all</char> the days of his life which God hath given him under the sun. <verse number="16" style="v"/>When I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to see the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">travail</char></char></note>business that is done upon the earth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">how that neither by day nor by night do men see sleep with their eyes</char></char></note>(for also there is that neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes), <verse number="17" style="v"/>then I beheld all the work of God, that man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because however much a man labor to seek it out, yet he shall not find it; yea moreover, though a wise man think to know it, yet shall he not be able to find it.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>For all this I laid to my heart, even to explore all this: that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of God; whether it be love or hatred, man knoweth it not; all is before them. <verse number="2" style="v"/>All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth and to him that sacrificeth not; as is the good, so is the sinner; <char style="add">and</char> he that sweareth, as he that feareth an oath. <verse number="3" style="v"/>This is an evil in all that is done under the sun, that there is one event unto all: yea also, the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that <char style="add">they go</char> to the dead. <verse number="4" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Another reading is, <char style="it">For who is exempted? With all etc.</char>, or <char style="it">who can choose? With all etc.</char></char></note>For to him that is joined with all the living there is hope; for a living dog is better than a dead lion. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not anything, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten. <verse number="6" style="v"/>As well their love, as their hatred and their envy, is perished long ago; neither have they any more a portion for ever in anything that is done under the sun. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart; for God hath already accepted thy works. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Let thy garments be always white; and let not thy head lack oil. <verse number="9" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Enjoy</char> (Hebrew <char style="it">See</char>) <char style="it">life</char></char></note>Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of thy life of vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all thy days of vanity: for that is thy portion in life, and in thy labor wherein thou laborest under the sun. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Whatsoever thy hand <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">attaineth to do by they strength</char>, that <char style="it">do</char></char></note>findeth to do, do <char style="add">it</char> with thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in Sheol, whither thou goest. <verse number="11" style="v"/>I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favor to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all. <verse number="12" style="v"/>For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare, even so are the sons of men snared in an evil time, when it falleth suddenly upon them. <verse number="13" style="v"/>I have also seen wisdom under the sun on this wise, and it seemed great unto me: <verse number="14" style="v"/>There was a little city, and few men within it; and there came a great king against it, and besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Now there was found in it a poor wise man, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength: nevertheless the poor man&#8217;s wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard. <verse number="17" style="v"/>The words of the wise heard in quiet are better than the cry of him that ruleth among fools. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Wisdom is better than weapons of war; but one sinner destroyeth much good.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Dead flies cause the oil of the perfumer <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to stink and putrefy</char></char></note>to send forth an evil odor; <char style="add">so</char> doth a little folly <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">him that is valued for wisdom</char></char></note>outweigh wisdom and honor. <verse number="2" style="v"/>A wise man&#8217;s heart is at his right hand; but a fool&#8217;s heart at his left. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Yea also, when the fool walketh by the way, his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">heart</char>.</char></note>understanding faileth him, and he saith <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of</char></char></note>to every one <char style="add">that</char> he is a fool. <verse number="4" style="v"/>If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">calmness leaveth great sins undone</char></char></note>gentleness allayeth great offences. <verse number="5" style="v"/>There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, as it were an error which proceedeth from the ruler: <verse number="6" style="v"/>folly is set in great <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">heights</char>.</char></note>dignity, and the rich sit in a low place. <verse number="7" style="v"/>I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking like servants upon the earth. <verse number="8" style="v"/>He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it; and whoso breaketh through a wall, a serpent shall bite him. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Whoso <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">moveth stones</char></char></note>heweth out stones shall be hurt therewith; <char style="add">and</char> he that cleaveth wood is endangered thereby. <verse number="10" style="v"/>If the iron be blunt, and one do not whet the edge, then must he put to more strength: but wisdom is profitable to direct. <verse number="11" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Surely the serpent will bite where there is no enchantment; and the slanderer is no better</char></char></note>If the serpent bite <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">without enchantment</char>.</char></note>before it is charmed, then is there no advantage in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">the master of the tongue</char>.</char></note>the charmer. <verse number="12" style="v"/>The words of a wise man&#8217;s mouth are gracious; but the lips of a fool will swallow up himself. <verse number="13" style="v"/>The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness; and the end of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">his mouth</char>.</char></note>his talk is mischievous madness. <verse number="14" style="v"/>A fool also multiplieth words: <char style="add">yet</char> man knoweth not what shall be; and that which shall be after him, who can tell him? <verse number="15" style="v"/>The labor of fools wearieth every one of them; for he knoweth not how to go to the city. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">servant</char></char></note>child, and thy princes eat in the morning! <verse number="17" style="v"/>Happy art thou, O land, when thy king is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a free man</char></char></note>the son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness! <verse number="18" style="v"/>By slothfulness the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">rafters sink</char></char></note>roof sinketh in; and through idleness of the hands the house leaketh. <verse number="19" style="v"/>A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh glad the life; and money answereth all things. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Revile not the king, no, not in thy thought; and revile not the rich in thy bedchamber: for a bird of the heavens shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Send forth</char></char></note>Cast thy bread <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">upon the face of the waters</char>.</char></note>upon the waters; for thou shalt find it after many days. <verse number="2" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Divide a portion into seven, yea, even into eight</char></char></note>Give a portion to seven, yea, even unto eight; for thou knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth. <verse number="3" style="v"/>If the clouds be full of rain, they empty themselves upon the earth; and if a tree fall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char></char></note>toward the south, or <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char></char></note>toward the north, in the place where the tree falleth, there shall it be. <verse number="4" style="v"/>He that observeth the wind shall not sow; and he that regardeth the clouds shall not reap. <verse number="5" style="v"/>As thou knowest not what is the way of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">spirit</char></char></note>wind, <char style="add">nor</char> how the bones <char style="add">do grow</char> in the womb of her that is with child; even so thou knowest not the work of God who doeth all. <verse number="6" style="v"/>In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold not thy hand; for thou knowest not which shall prosper, whether this or that, or whether they both shall be alike good. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Truly the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to behold the sun. <verse number="8" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">For</char></char></note>Yea, if a man live many years, let him rejoice in them all; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and remember</char></char></note>but let him remember the days of darkness, for they shall be many. All that cometh is vanity. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the sight of thine eyes; but know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgment. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Therefore remove <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">vexation</char>. Or, <char style="it">provocation</char></char></note>sorrow from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh; for youth and the dawn of life are vanity.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Remember also thy Creator in the days of thy youth, before the evil days come, and the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say, I have no pleasure in them; <verse number="2" style="v"/>before the sun, and the light, and the moon, and the stars, are darkened, and the clouds return after the rain; <verse number="3" style="v"/>in the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">grinding women</char></char></note>grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows shall be darkened, <verse number="4" style="v"/>and the doors shall be shut in the street; when the sound of the grinding is low, and one shall rise up at the voice of a bird, and all the daughters of music shall be brought low; <verse number="5" style="v"/>yea, they shall be afraid <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, of danger <char style="it">from on high</char></char></note>of <char style="add">that which is</char> high, and terrors <char style="add">shall be</char> in the way; and the almond-tree shall blossom, and the grasshopper <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">shall drag itself along</char></char></note>shall be a burden, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the caperberry</char></char></note>desire shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">burst</char></char></note>fail; because man goeth to his everlasting home, and the mourners go about the streets: <verse number="6" style="v"/>before the silver cord is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">snapped asunder</char></char></note>loosed, or the golden bowl is broken, or the pitcher is broken at the fountain, or the wheel broken at the cistern, <verse number="7" style="v"/>and the dust returneth to the earth as it was, and the spirit returneth unto God who gave it. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher; all is vanity. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And further, because the Preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge; yea, he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gave ear</char></char></note>pondered, and sought out, <char style="add">and</char> set in order many proverbs. <verse number="10" style="v"/>The Preacher sought to find out <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">words of delight</char>.</char></note>acceptable words, and that which was written uprightly, <char style="add">even</char> words of truth. <verse number="11" style="v"/>The words of the wise are as goads; and as nails well fastened are <char style="add">the words of</char> the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">collectors of sentences</char></char></note>masters of assemblies, <char style="add">which</char> are given from one shepherd. <verse number="12" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">And as for more than these, my son, be warned</char></char></note>And furthermore, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh. <verse number="13" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Let us hear the conclusion of the whole matter</char></char></note><char style="add">This is</char> the end of the matter; all hath been heard: Fear God, and keep his commandments; for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">this is</char> the duty of <char style="it">all men</char></char></note>this is the whole <char style="add">duty</char> of man. <verse number="14" style="v"/>For God will bring every work into judgment, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">concerning</char></char></note>with every hidden thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</para>
</usx>