<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="HAG" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet unto Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying, <verse number="2" style="v"/>Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, saying, This people say, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, as otherwise read, <char style="it">The time is not come for Jehovah&#8217;s house etc.</char></char></note>It is not the time <char style="add">for us</char> to come, the time for Jehovah&#8217;s house to be built. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Then came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying, <verse number="4" style="v"/>Is it a time for you yourselves to dwell in your ceiled houses, while this house lieth waste? <verse number="5" style="v"/>Now therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">Set your heart on your ways</char>.</char></note>Consider your ways. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Ye have sown much, and bring in little; ye eat, but ye have not enough; ye drink, but ye are not filled with drink; ye clothe you, but there is none warm; and he that earneth wages earneth wages <char style="add">to put it</char> into a bag with holes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Consider your ways. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Go up to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hill-country</char></char></note>mountain, and bring wood, and build the house; and I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified, saith Jehovah. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Ye looked for much, and, lo, it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">blow it away</char></char></note>blow upon it. Why? saith Jehovah of hosts. Because of my house that lieth waste, while ye run every man to his own house. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Therefore <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">over you</char></char></note>for your sake the heavens withhold the dew, and the earth withholdeth its fruit. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the mountains, and upon the grain, and upon the new wine, and upon the oil, and upon that which the ground bringeth forth, and upon men, and upon cattle, and upon all the labor of the hands.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed the voice of Jehovah their God, and the words of Haggai the prophet, as Jehovah their God had sent him; and the people did fear before Jehovah. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Then spake Haggai Jehovah&#8217;s messenger in Jehovah&#8217;s message unto the people, saying, I am with you, saith Jehovah. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Jehovah stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and did work on the house of Jehovah of hosts, their God, <verse number="15" style="v"/>in the four and twentieth day of the month, in the sixth <char style="add">month</char>, in the second year of Darius the king.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>In the seventh <char style="add">month</char>, in the one and twentieth <char style="add">day</char> of the month, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying, <verse number="2" style="v"/>Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying, <verse number="3" style="v"/>Who is left among you that saw this house in its former glory? and how do ye see it now? is it not in your eyes as nothing? <verse number="4" style="v"/>Yet now be strong, O Zerubbabel, saith Jehovah; and be strong, O Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest; and be strong, all ye people of the land, saith Jehovah, and work: for I am with you, saith Jehovah of hosts, <verse number="5" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, Remember <char style="it">the word etc.</char></char></note><char style="add">according to</char> the word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of Egypt, and my Spirit <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">abideth</char></char></note>abode among you: fear ye not. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the sea, and the dry land; <verse number="7" style="v"/>and I will shake all nations; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the things desired</char> (Hebrew <char style="it">desire</char>) <char style="it">of all nations shall come</char></char></note>the precious things of all nations shall come; and I will fill this house with glory, saith Jehovah of hosts. <verse number="8" style="v"/>The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, saith Jehovah of hosts. <verse number="9" style="v"/>The latter glory of this house shall be greater than the former, saith Jehovah of hosts; and in this place will I give peace, saith Jehovah of hosts.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>In the four and twentieth <char style="add">day</char> of the ninth <char style="add">month</char>, in the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying, <verse number="11" style="v"/>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying, <verse number="12" style="v"/>If one bear holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or any food, shall it become holy? And the priests answered and said, No. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Then said Haggai, If one that is unclean by reason of a dead body touch any of these, shall it be unclean? And the priests answered and said, It shall be unclean. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Then answered Haggai and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before me, saith Jehovah; and so is every work of their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And now, I pray you, consider from this day and backward, before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of Jehovah. <verse number="16" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Hebrew <char style="it">since those</char> days <char style="it">were</char>.</char></note>Through all that time, when one came to a heap of twenty <char style="add">measures</char>, there were but ten; when one came to the winevat to draw out fifty <char style="add">vessels</char>, there were but twenty. <verse number="17" style="v"/>I smote you with blasting and with mildew and with hail in all the work of your hands; yet ye <char style="add">turned</char> not to me, saith Jehovah. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Consider, I pray you, from this day and backward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth <char style="add">month</char>, since the day that the foundation of Jehovah&#8217;s temple was laid, consider it. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Is the seed yet in the barn? yea, the vine, and the fig-tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive-tree have not brought forth; from this day will I bless <char style="add">you</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And the word of Jehovah came the second time unto Haggai in the four and twentieth <char style="add">day</char> of the month, saying, <verse number="21" style="v"/>Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, I will shake the heavens and the earth; <verse number="22" style="v"/>and I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms; and I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations; and I will overthrow the chariots, and those that ride in them; and the horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword of his brother. <verse number="23" style="v"/>In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, will I take thee, O Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of Shealtiel, saith Jehovah, and will make thee as a signet; for I have chosen thee, saith Jehovah of hosts.</para>
</usx>