<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="JHN" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. <verse number="2" style="v"/>The same was in the beginning with God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>All things were made through him; and without him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was not anything made. That which hath been made was life in him; and the life etc.</char></char></note>was not anything made that hath been made. <verse number="4" style="v"/>In him was life; and the life was the light of men. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the light shineth in the darkness; and the darkness <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">overcame</char>. See <ref loc="JHN 12:35">12:35</ref> (Greek).</char></note>apprehended it not. <verse number="6" style="v"/>There came a man, sent from God, whose name was John. <verse number="7" style="v"/>The same came for witness, that he might bear witness of the light, that all might believe through him. <verse number="8" style="v"/>He was not the light, but <char style="add">came</char> that he might bear witness of the light. <verse number="9" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the true light, which lighteth every man, was coming</char></char></note>There was the true light, <char style="add">even the light</char> which lighteth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">every man as he cometh</char></char></note>every man, coming into the world. <verse number="10" style="v"/>He was in the world, and the world was made through him, and the world knew him not. <verse number="11" style="v"/>He came unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">his own things</char>.</char></note>his own, and they that were his own received him not. <verse number="12" style="v"/>But as many as received him, to them gave he the right to become children of God, <char style="add">even</char> to them that believe on his name: <verse number="13" style="v"/>who were <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">begotten</char></char></note>born, not of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bloods</char>.</char></note>blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the Word became flesh, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">tabernacled</char>.</char></note>dwelt among us (and we beheld his glory, glory as of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">an only begotten from a father</char>. Compare <ref loc="HEB 11:17">Heb. 11:17</ref>.</char></note>the only begotten from the Father), full of grace and truth. <verse number="15" style="v"/>John beareth witness of him, and crieth, saying, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">(this was he that said)</char>.</char></note>This was he of whom I said, He that cometh after me is become before me: for he was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">first in regard of me</char>.</char></note>before me. <verse number="16" style="v"/>For of his fulness we all received, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">grace upon grace</char></char></note>grace for grace. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For the law was given through Moses; grace and truth came through Jesus Christ. <verse number="18" style="v"/>No man hath seen God at any time; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many very ancient authorities read <char style="it">God only begotten</char>.</char></note>the only begotten Son, who is in the bosom of the Father, he hath declared <char style="add">him</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>And this is the witness of John, when the Jews sent unto him from Jerusalem priests and Levites to ask him, Who art thou? <verse number="20" style="v"/>And he confessed, and denied not; and he confessed, I am not the Christ. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And they asked him, What then? Art thou Elijah? And he saith, I am not. Art thou the prophet? And he answered, No. <verse number="22" style="v"/>They said therefore unto him, Who art thou? that we may give an answer to them that sent us. What sayest thou of thyself? <verse number="23" style="v"/>He said, I am the voice of one crying in the wilderness, Make straight the way of the Lord, as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 40:3">Isa. 40:3</ref>.</char></note>said Isaiah the prophet. <verse number="24" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">And</char> certain <char style="it">had been sent from among the Pharisees</char>.</char></note>And they had been sent from the Pharisees. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And they asked him, and said unto him, Why then baptizest thou, if thou art not the Christ, neither Elijah, neither the prophet? <verse number="26" style="v"/>John answered them, saying, I baptize <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with</char></char></note>in water: in the midst of you standeth one whom ye know not, <verse number="27" style="v"/><char style="add">even</char> he that cometh after me, the latchet of whose shoe I am not worthy to unloose. <verse number="28" style="v"/>These things were done in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">Bethabarah</char>, some <char style="it">Betharabah</char>. Compare <ref loc="JOS 15:6">Josh. 15:6</ref>, <ref loc="JOS 15:61">61</ref>; <ref loc="JOS 18:22">18:22</ref>.</char></note>Bethany beyond the Jordan, where John was baptizing.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v"/>On the morrow he seeth Jesus coming unto him, and saith, Behold, the Lamb of God, that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">beareth the sin</char></char></note>taketh away the sin of the world! <verse number="30" style="v"/>This is he of whom I said, After me cometh a man who is become before me: for he was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">first in regard of me</char>.</char></note>before me. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And I knew him not; but that he should be made manifest to Israel, for this cause came I baptizing <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with</char></char></note>in water. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And John bare witness, saying, I have beheld the Spirit descending as a dove out of heaven; and it abode upon him. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And I knew him not: but he that sent me to baptize <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with</char></char></note>in water, he said unto me, Upon whomsoever thou shalt see the Spirit descending, and abiding upon him, the same is he that baptizeth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with</char></char></note>in the Holy Spirit. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And I have seen, and have borne witness that this is the Son of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v"/>Again on the morrow John was standing, and two of his disciples; <verse number="36" style="v"/>and he looked upon Jesus as he walked, and saith, Behold, the Lamb of God! <verse number="37" style="v"/>And the two disciples heard him speak, and they followed Jesus. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And Jesus turned, and beheld them following, and saith unto them, What seek ye? And they said unto him, Rabbi (which is to say, being interpreted, Teacher), where abidest thou? <verse number="39" style="v"/>He saith unto them, Come, and ye shall see. They came therefore and saw where he abode; and they abode with him that day: it was about the tenth hour. <verse number="40" style="v"/>One of the two that heard John <char style="add">speak</char>, and followed him, was Andrew, Simon Peter&#8217;s brother. <verse number="41" style="v"/>He findeth first his own brother Simon, and saith unto him, We have found the Messiah (which is, being interpreted, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Anointed</char>. Compare <ref loc="PSA 2:2">Ps. 2:2</ref>.</char></note>Christ). <verse number="42" style="v"/>He brought him unto Jesus. Jesus looked upon him, and said, Thou art Simon the son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Joanes</char>: called in <ref loc="MAT 16:17">Mt. 16:17</ref> <char style="it">Jonah</char>.</char></note>John: thou shalt be called Cephas (which is by interpretation, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Rock</char> or <char style="it">Stone</char>.</char></note>Peter).</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v"/>On the morrow he was minded to go forth into Galilee, and he findeth Philip: and Jesus saith unto him, Follow me. <verse number="44" style="v"/>Now Philip was from Bethsaida, of the city of Andrew and Peter. <verse number="45" style="v"/>Philip findeth Nathanael, and saith unto him, We have found him, of whom Moses in the law, and the prophets, wrote, Jesus of Nazareth, the son of Joseph. <verse number="46" style="v"/>And Nathanael said unto him, Can any good thing come out of Nazareth? Philip saith unto him, Come and see. <verse number="47" style="v"/>Jesus saw Nathanael coming to him, and saith of him, Behold, an Israelite indeed, in whom is no guile! <verse number="48" style="v"/>Nathanael saith unto him, Whence knowest thou me? Jesus answered and said unto him, Before Philip called thee, when thou wast under the fig tree, I saw thee. <verse number="49" style="v"/>Nathanael answered him, Rabbi, thou art the Son of God; thou art King of Israel. <verse number="50" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto him, Because I said unto thee, I saw thee underneath the fig tree, believest thou? thou shalt see greater things than these. <verse number="51" style="v"/>And he saith unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Ye shall see the heaven opened, and the angels of God ascending and descending upon the Son of man.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the third day there was a marriage in Cana of Galilee; and the mother of Jesus was there: <verse number="2" style="v"/>and Jesus also was bidden, and his disciples, to the marriage. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And when the wine failed, the mother of Jesus saith unto him, They have no wine. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Jesus saith unto her, Woman, what have I to do with thee? mine hour is not yet come. <verse number="5" style="v"/>His mother saith unto the servants, Whatsoever he saith unto you, do it. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Now there were six waterpots of stone set there after the Jews&#8217; manner of purifying, containing two or three firkins apiece. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto them, Fill the waterpots with water. And they filled them up to the brim. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he saith unto them, Draw out now, and bear unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">steward</char></char></note>ruler of the feast. And they bare it. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And when the ruler of the feast tasted the water <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that it had become</char></char></note>now become wine, and knew not whence it was (but the servants that had drawn the water knew), the ruler of the feast calleth the bridegroom, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and saith unto him, Every man setteth on first the good wine; and when <char style="add">men</char> have drunk freely, <char style="add">then</char> that which is worse: thou hast kept the good wine until now. <verse number="11" style="v"/>This beginning of his signs did Jesus in Cana of Galilee, and manifested his glory; and his disciples believed on him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>After this he went down to Capernaum, he, and his mother, and <char style="add">his</char> brethren, and his disciples; and there they abode not many days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And the passover of the Jews was at hand, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And he found in the temple those that sold oxen and sheep and doves, and the changers of money sitting: <verse number="15" style="v"/>and he made a scourge of cords, and cast all out of the temple, both the sheep and the oxen; and he poured out the changers&#8217; money, and overthrew their tables; <verse number="16" style="v"/>and to them that sold the doves he said, Take these things hence; make not my Father&#8217;s house a house of merchandise. <verse number="17" style="v"/>His disciples remembered that it was written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 69:9">Ps. 69:9</ref>.</char></note>Zeal for thy house shall eat me up. <verse number="18" style="v"/>The Jews therefore answered and said unto him, What sign showest thou unto us, seeing that thou doest these things? <verse number="19" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto them, Destroy this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple, and in three days I will raise it up. <verse number="20" style="v"/>The Jews therefore said, Forty and six years was this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple in building, and wilt thou raise it up in three days? <verse number="21" style="v"/>But he spake of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple of his body. <verse number="22" style="v"/>When therefore he was raised from the dead, his disciples remembered that he spake this; and they believed the scripture, and the word which Jesus had said.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>Now when he was in Jerusalem at the passover, during the feast, many believed on his name, beholding his signs which he did. <verse number="24" style="v"/>But Jesus did not trust himself unto them, for that he knew all men, <verse number="25" style="v"/>and because he needed not that any one should bear witness concerning <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a man; for&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. the man</char>.</char></note>man; for he himself knew what was in man.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now there was a man of the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews: <verse number="2" style="v"/>the same came unto him by night, and said to him, Rabbi, we know that thou art a teacher come from God; for no one can do these signs that thou doest, except God be with him. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except one be born <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">from above</char>. See <ref loc="JHN 3:31">verse 31</ref>; <ref loc="JHN 19:11">19:11</ref>; <ref loc="JAS 1:17">Jas. 1:17</ref>; <ref loc="JAS 3:15">3:15</ref>, <ref loc="JAS 3:17">17</ref>.</char></note>anew, he cannot see the kingdom of God. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Nicodemus saith unto him, How can a man be born when he is old? can he enter a second time into his mother&#8217;s womb, and be born? <verse number="5" style="v"/>Jesus answered, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except one be born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God. <verse number="6" style="v"/>That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is born of the Spirit is spirit. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Marvel not that I said unto thee, Ye must be born <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">from above</char>. See <ref loc="JHN 3:31">verse 31</ref>; <ref loc="JHN 19:11">19:11</ref>; <ref loc="JAS 1:17">Jas. 1:17</ref>; <ref loc="JAS 3:15">3:15</ref>, <ref loc="JAS 3:17">17</ref>.</char></note>anew. <verse number="8" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">The Spirit breatheth</char></char></note>The wind bloweth where it will, and thou hearest the voice thereof, but knowest not whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the Spirit. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Nicodemus answered and said unto him, How can these things be? <verse number="10" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto him, Art thou the teacher of Israel, and understandest not these things? <verse number="11" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto thee, We speak that which we know, and bear witness of that which we have seen; and ye receive not our witness. <verse number="12" style="v"/>If I told you earthly things and ye believe not, how shall ye believe if I tell you heavenly things? <verse number="13" style="v"/>And no one hath ascended into heaven, but he that descended out of heaven, <char style="add">even</char> the Son of man, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Man ancient authorities omit <char style="it">who is in heaven</char>.</char></note>who is in heaven. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, even so must the Son of man be lifted up; <verse number="15" style="v"/>that whosoever <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">believeth in him may have</char></char></note>believeth may in him have eternal life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth on him should not perish, but have eternal life. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For God sent not the Son into the world to judge the world; but that the world should be saved through him. <verse number="18" style="v"/>He that believeth on him is not judged: he that believeth not hath been judged already, because he hath not believed on the name of the only begotten Son of God. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And this is the judgment, that the light is come into the world, and men loved the darkness rather than the light; for their works were evil. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For every one that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">practiseth</char></char></note>doeth evil hateth the light, and cometh not to the light, lest his works should be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">convicted</char></char></note>reproved. <verse number="21" style="v"/>But he that doeth the truth cometh to the light, that his works may be made manifest, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">because</char></char></note>that they have been wrought in God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>After these things came Jesus and his disciples into the land of Judaea; and there he tarried with them, and baptized. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And John also was baptizing in Aenon near to Salim, because there <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">were many waters</char>.</char></note>was much water there: and they came, and were baptized. <verse number="24" style="v"/>For John was not yet cast into prison. <verse number="25" style="v"/>There arose therefore a questioning on the part of John&#8217;s disciples with a Jew about purifying. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And they came unto John, and said to him, Rabbi, he that was with thee beyond the Jordan, to whom thou hast borne witness, behold, the same baptizeth, and all men come to him. <verse number="27" style="v"/>John answered and said, A man can receive nothing, except it have been given him from heaven. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Ye yourselves bear me witness, that I said, I am not the Christ, but, that I am sent before him. <verse number="29" style="v"/>He that hath the bride is the bridegroom: but the friend of the bridegroom, that standeth and heareth him, rejoiceth greatly because of the bridegroom&#8217;s voice: this my joy therefore is made full. <verse number="30" style="v"/>He must increase, but I must decrease.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>He that cometh from above is above all: he that is of the earth is of the earth, and of the earth he speaketh: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">he that cometh from heaven beareth witness of what he hath seen and heard</char>.</char></note>he that cometh from heaven is above all. <verse number="32" style="v"/>What he hath seen and heard, of that he beareth witness; and no man receiveth his witness. <verse number="33" style="v"/>He that hath received his witness hath set his seal to <char style="add">this</char>, that God is true. <verse number="34" style="v"/>For he whom God hath sent speaketh the words of God: for he giveth not the Spirit by measure. <verse number="35" style="v"/>The Father loveth the Son, and hath given all things into his hand. <verse number="36" style="v"/>He that believeth on the Son hath eternal life; but he that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">believeth not</char></char></note>obeyeth not the Son shall not see life, but the wrath of God abideth on him.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>When therefore the Lord knew that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus was making and baptizing more disciples than John <verse number="2" style="v"/>(although Jesus himself baptized not, but his disciples), <verse number="3" style="v"/>he left Judaea, and departed again into Galilee. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And he must needs pass through Samaria. <verse number="5" style="v"/>So he cometh to a city of Samaria, called Sychar, near to the parcel of ground that Jacob gave to his son Joseph: <verse number="6" style="v"/>and Jacob&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">spring</char>: and so in <ref loc="JHN 4:14">verse 14</ref>; but not in verses <ref loc="JHN 4:11">11</ref>, <ref loc="JHN 4:12">12</ref>.</char></note>well was there. Jesus therefore, being wearied with his journey, sat <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">as he was</char>. Compare <ref loc="JHN 13:25">13:25</ref>.</char></note>thus by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">spring</char>: and so in <ref loc="JHN 4:14">verse 14</ref>; but not in verses <ref loc="JHN 4:11">11</ref>, <ref loc="JHN 4:12">12</ref>.</char></note>well. It was about the sixth hour. <verse number="7" style="v"/>There cometh a woman of Samaria to draw water: Jesus saith unto her, Give me to drink. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For his disciples were gone away into the city to buy food. <verse number="9" style="v"/>The Samaritan woman therefore saith unto him, How is it that thou, being a Jew, askest drink of me, who am a Samaritan woman? <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">For the Jews have no dealings with Samaritans</char>.</char></note>(For Jews have no dealings with Samaritans.) <verse number="10" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto her, If thou knewest the gift of God, and who it is that saith to thee, Give me to drink; thou wouldest have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water. <verse number="11" style="v"/>The woman saith unto him, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Lord</char></char></note>Sir, thou hast nothing to draw with, and the well is deep: whence then hast thou that living water? <verse number="12" style="v"/>Art thou greater than our father Jacob, who gave us the well, and drank thereof himself, and his sons, and his cattle? <verse number="13" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto her, Every one that drinketh of this water shall thirst again: <verse number="14" style="v"/>but whosoever drinketh of the water that I shall give him shall never thirst; but the water that I shall give him shall become in him a well of water springing up unto eternal life. <verse number="15" style="v"/>The woman saith unto him, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Lord</char></char></note>Sir, give me this water, that I thirst not, neither come all the way hither to draw. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto her, Go, call thy husband, and come hither. <verse number="17" style="v"/>The woman answered and said unto him, I have no husband. Jesus saith unto her, Thou saidst well, I have no husband: <verse number="18" style="v"/>for thou hast had five husbands; and he whom thou now hast is not thy husband: this hast thou said truly. <verse number="19" style="v"/>The woman saith unto him, Sir, I perceive that thou art a prophet. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Our fathers worshipped in this mountain; and ye say, that in Jerusalem is the place where men ought to worship. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto her, Woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when neither in this mountain, nor in Jerusalem, shall ye worship the Father. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Ye worship that which ye know not: we worship that which we know; for salvation is from the Jews. <verse number="23" style="v"/>But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worshippers shall worship the Father in spirit and truth: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for such the Father also seeketh</char></char></note>for such doth the Father seek to be his worshippers. <verse number="24" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">God is spirit</char></char></note>God is a Spirit: and they that worship him must worship in spirit and truth. <verse number="25" style="v"/>The woman saith unto him, I know that Messiah cometh (he that is called Christ): when he is come, he will declare unto us all things. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto her, I that speak unto thee am <char style="add">he</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v"/>And upon this came his disciples; and they marvelled that he was speaking with a woman; yet no man said, What seekest thou? or, Why speakest thou with her? <verse number="28" style="v"/>So the woman left her waterpot, and went away into the city, and saith to the people, <verse number="29" style="v"/>Come, see a man, who told me all things that <char style="add">ever</char> I did: can this be the Christ? <verse number="30" style="v"/>They went out of the city, and were coming to him. <verse number="31" style="v"/>In the mean while the disciples prayed him, saying, Rabbi, eat. <verse number="32" style="v"/>But he said unto them, I have meat to eat that ye know not. <verse number="33" style="v"/>The disciples therefore said one to another, Hath any man brought him <char style="add">aught</char> to eat? <verse number="34" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto them, My meat is to do the will of him that sent me, and to accomplish his work. <verse number="35" style="v"/>Say not ye, There are yet four months, and <char style="add">then</char> cometh the harvest? behold, I say unto you, Lift up your eyes, and look on the fields, that they are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">white unto harvest. Already he that reapeth etc.</char></char></note>white already unto harvest. <verse number="36" style="v"/>He that reapeth receiveth wages, and gathereth fruit unto life eternal; that he that soweth and he that reapeth may rejoice together. <verse number="37" style="v"/>For herein is the saying true, One soweth, and another reapeth. <verse number="38" style="v"/>I sent you to reap that whereon ye have not labored: others have labored, and ye are entered into their labor.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v"/>And from that city many of the Samaritans believed on him because of the word of the woman, who testified, He told me all things that <char style="add">ever</char> I did. <verse number="40" style="v"/>So when the Samaritans came unto him, they besought him to abide with them: and he abode there two days. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And many more believed because of his word; <verse number="42" style="v"/>and they said to the woman, Now we believe, not because of thy speaking: for we have heard for ourselves, and know that this is indeed the Saviour of the world.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v"/>And after the two days he went forth from thence into Galilee. <verse number="44" style="v"/>For Jesus himself testified, that a prophet hath no honor in his own country. <verse number="45" style="v"/>So when he came into Galilee, the Galilaeans received him, having seen all the things that he did in Jerusalem at the feast: for they also went unto the feast.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v"/>He came therefore again unto Cana of Galilee, where he made the water wine. And there was a certain <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">king&#8217;s officer</char></char></note>nobleman, whose son was sick at Capernaum. <verse number="47" style="v"/>When he heard that Jesus was come out of Judaea into Galilee, he went unto him, and besought <char style="add">him</char> that he would come down, and heal his son; for he was at the point of death. <verse number="48" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said unto him, Except ye see signs and wonders, ye will in no wise believe. <verse number="49" style="v"/>The <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">king&#8217;s officer</char></char></note>nobleman saith unto him, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Lord</char></char></note>Sir, come down ere my child die. <verse number="50" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto him, Go thy way; thy son liveth. The man believed the word that Jesus spake unto him, and he went his way. <verse number="51" style="v"/>And as he was now going down, his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants met him, saying, that his son lived. <verse number="52" style="v"/>So he inquired of them the hour when he began to amend. They said therefore unto him, Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him. <verse number="53" style="v"/>So the father knew that <char style="add">it was</char> at that hour in which Jesus said unto him, Thy son liveth: and himself believed, and his whole house. <verse number="54" style="v"/>This is again the second sign that Jesus did, having come out of Judaea into Galilee.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After these things there was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">the feast</char> (Compare <ref loc="JHN 2:13">2:13</ref>?).</char></note>a feast of the Jews; and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>Now there is in Jerusalem by the sheep <char style="add">gate</char> a pool, which is called in Hebrew <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">Bethsaida</char>, others <char style="it">Bethzatha</char></char></note>Bethesda, having five porches. <verse number="3" style="v"/>In these lay a multitude of them that were sick, blind, halt, withered<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities insert, wholly or in part, <char style="it">waiting for the moving of the water:</char> <char style="fv">4</char><char style="it">for an angel of the Lord went down at certain seasons into the pool, and troubled the water: whosoever then first after the troubling of the water stepped in was made whole, with whatsoever disease he was holden</char>.</char></note>. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And a certain man was there, who had been thirty and eight years in his infirmity. <verse number="6" style="v"/>When Jesus saw him lying, and knew that he had been now a long time <char style="add">in that case</char>, he saith unto him, Wouldest thou be made whole? <verse number="7" style="v"/>The sick man answered him, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Lord</char></char></note>Sir, I have no man, when the water is troubled, to put me into the pool: but while I am coming, another steppeth down before me. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto him, Arise, take up thy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pallet</char></char></note>bed, and walk. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And straightway the man was made whole, and took up his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pallet</char></char></note>bed and walked.</para>
	<para style="p">Now it was the sabbath on that day. <verse number="10" style="v"/>So the Jews said unto him that was cured, It is the sabbath, and it is not lawful for thee to take up thy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pallet</char></char></note>bed. <verse number="11" style="v"/>But he answered them, He that made me whole, the same said unto me, Take up thy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pallet</char></char></note>bed, and walk. <verse number="12" style="v"/>They asked him, Who is the man that said unto thee, Take up <char style="add">thy</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pallet</char></char></note><char style="add">bed</char>, and walk? <verse number="13" style="v"/>But he that was healed knew not who it was; for Jesus had conveyed himself away, a multitude being in the place. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Afterward Jesus findeth him in the temple, and said unto him, Behold, thou art made whole: sin no more, lest a worse thing befall thee. <verse number="15" style="v"/>The man went away, and told the Jews that it was Jesus who had made him whole. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And for this cause the Jews persecuted Jesus, because he did these things on the sabbath. <verse number="17" style="v"/>But Jesus answered them, My Father worketh even until now, and I work. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For this cause therefore the Jews sought the more to kill him, because he not only brake the sabbath, but also called God his own Father, making himself equal with God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>Jesus therefore answered and said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, The Son can do nothing of himself, but what he seeth the Father doing: for what things soever he doeth, these the Son also doeth in like manner. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For the Father loveth the Son, and showeth him all things that himself doeth: and greater works than these will he show him, that ye may marvel. <verse number="21" style="v"/>For as the Father raiseth the dead and giveth them life, even so the Son also giveth life to whom he will. <verse number="22" style="v"/>For neither doth the Father judge any man, but he hath given all judgment unto the Son; <verse number="23" style="v"/>that all may honor the Son, even as they honor the Father. He that honoreth not the Son honoreth not the Father that sent him. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that heareth my word, and believeth him that sent me, hath eternal life, and cometh not into judgment, but hath passed out of death into life. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, The hour cometh, and now is, when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God; and they that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hearken</char></char></note>hear shall live. <verse number="26" style="v"/>For as the Father hath life in himself, even so gave he to the Son also to have life in himself: <verse number="27" style="v"/>and he gave him authority to execute judgment, because he is a son of man. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Marvel not at this: for the hour cometh, in which all that are in the tombs shall hear his voice, <verse number="29" style="v"/>and shall come forth; they that have done good, unto the resurrection of life; and they that have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">practised</char></char></note>done evil, unto the resurrection of judgment.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>I can of myself do nothing: as I hear, I judge: and my judgment is righteous; because I seek not mine own will, but the will of him that sent me. <verse number="31" style="v"/>If I bear witness of myself, my witness is not true. <verse number="32" style="v"/>It is another that beareth witness of me; and I know that the witness which he witnesseth of me is true. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Ye have sent unto John, and he hath borne witness unto the truth. <verse number="34" style="v"/>But the witness which I receive is not from man: howbeit I say these things, that ye may be saved. <verse number="35" style="v"/>He was the lamp that burneth and shineth; and ye were willing to rejoice for a season in his light. <verse number="36" style="v"/>But the witness which I have is greater than <char style="add">that of</char> John; for the works which the Father hath given me to accomplish, the very works that I do, bear witness of me, that the Father hath sent me. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And the Father that sent me, he hath borne witness of me. Ye have neither heard his voice at any time, nor seen his form. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And ye have not his word abiding in you: for whom he sent, him ye believe not. <verse number="39" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Search the scriptures</char></char></note>Ye search the scriptures, because ye think that in them ye have eternal life; and these are they which bear witness of me; <verse number="40" style="v"/>and ye will not come to me, that ye may have life. <verse number="41" style="v"/>I receive not glory from men. <verse number="42" style="v"/>But I know you, that ye have not the love of God in yourselves. <verse number="43" style="v"/>I am come in my Father&#8217;s name, and ye receive me not: if another shall come in his own name, him ye will receive. <verse number="44" style="v"/>How can ye believe, who receive glory one of another, and the glory that <char style="add">cometh</char> from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">the only</char> one.</char></note>the only God ye seek not? <verse number="45" style="v"/>Think not that I will accuse you to the Father: there is one that accuseth you, <char style="add">even</char> Moses, on whom ye have set your hope. <verse number="46" style="v"/>For if ye believed Moses, ye would believe me; for he wrote of me. <verse number="47" style="v"/>But if ye believe not his writings, how shall ye believe my words?</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After these things Jesus went away to the other side of the sea of Galilee, which is <char style="add">the sea</char> of Tiberias. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And a great multitude followed him, because they beheld the signs which he did on them that were sick. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And Jesus went up into the mountain, and there he sat with his disciples. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Now the passover, the feast of the Jews, was at hand. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Jesus therefore lifting up his eyes, and seeing that a great multitude cometh unto him, saith unto Philip, Whence are we to buy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">loaves</char>.</char></note>bread, that these may eat? <verse number="6" style="v"/>And this he said to prove him: for he himself knew what he would do. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Philip answered him, Two hundred <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The word in the Greek denotes a coin worth about eight pence halfpenny, or nearly seventeen cents.</char></note>shillings&#8217; worth of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">loaves</char>.</char></note>bread is not sufficient for them, that every one may take a little. <verse number="8" style="v"/>One of his disciples, Andrew, Simon Peter&#8217;s brother, saith unto him, <verse number="9" style="v"/>There is a lad here, who hath five barley loaves, and two fishes: but what are these among so many? <verse number="10" style="v"/>Jesus said, Make the people sit down. Now there was much grass in the place. So the men sat down, in number about five thousand. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Jesus therefore took the loaves; and having given thanks, he distributed to them that were set down; likewise also of the fishes as much as they would. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And when they were filled, he saith unto his disciples, Gather up the broken pieces which remain over, that nothing be lost. <verse number="13" style="v"/>So they gathered them up, and filled twelve baskets with broken pieces from the five barley loaves, which remained over unto them that had eaten. <verse number="14" style="v"/>When therefore the people saw the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">signs</char>.</char></note>sign which he did, they said, This is of a truth the prophet that cometh into the world.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>Jesus therefore perceiving that they were about to come and take him by force, to make him king, withdrew again into the mountain himself alone.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And when evening came, his disciples went down unto the sea; <verse number="17" style="v"/>and they entered into a boat, and were going over the sea unto Capernaum. And it was now dark, and Jesus had not yet come to them. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the sea was rising by reason of a great wind that blew. <verse number="19" style="v"/>When therefore they had rowed about five and twenty or thirty furlongs, they behold Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing nigh unto the boat: and they were afraid. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But he saith unto them, It is I; be not afraid. <verse number="21" style="v"/>They were willing therefore to receive him into the boat: and straightway the boat was at the land whither they were going.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>On the morrow the multitude that stood on the other side of the sea saw that there was no other <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">little boat</char>.</char></note>boat there, save one, and that Jesus entered not with his disciples into the boat, but <char style="add">that</char> his disciples went away alone <verse number="23" style="v"/>(howbeit there came <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">little boats</char>.</char></note>boats from Tiberias nigh unto the place where they ate the bread after the Lord had given thanks): <verse number="24" style="v"/>when the multitude therefore saw that Jesus was not there, neither his disciples, they themselves got into the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">little boats</char>.</char></note>boats, and came to Capernaum, seeking Jesus. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And when they found him on the other side of the sea, they said unto him, Rabbi, when camest thou hither? <verse number="26" style="v"/>Jesus answered them and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Ye seek me, not because ye saw signs, but because ye ate of the loaves, and were filled. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Work not for the food which perisheth, but for the food which abideth unto eternal life, which the Son of man shall give unto you: for him the Father, <char style="add">even</char> God, hath sealed. <verse number="28" style="v"/>They said therefore unto him, What must we do, that we may work the works of God? <verse number="29" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto them, This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">he sent</char></char></note>he hath sent. <verse number="30" style="v"/>They said therefore unto him, What then doest thou for a sign, that we may see, and believe thee? what workest thou? <verse number="31" style="v"/>Our fathers ate the manna in the wilderness; as it is written, He <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="NEH 9:15">Neh. 9:15</ref>; <ref loc="EXO 16:4">Ex. 16:4</ref>, <ref loc="EXO 16:15">15</ref>; <ref loc="PSA 78:24">Ps. 78:24</ref>; <ref loc="PSA 105:40">105:40</ref>.</char></note>gave them bread out of heaven to eat. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, It was not Moses that gave you the bread out of heaven; but my Father giveth you the true bread out of heaven. <verse number="33" style="v"/>For the bread of God is that which cometh down out of heaven, and giveth life unto the world. <verse number="34" style="v"/>They said therefore unto him, Lord, evermore give us this bread. <verse number="35" style="v"/>Jesus said unto them, I am the bread of life: he that cometh to me shall not hunger, and he that believeth on me shall never thirst. <verse number="36" style="v"/>But I said unto you, that ye have seen me, and yet believe not. <verse number="37" style="v"/>All that which the Father giveth me shall come unto me; and him that cometh to me I will in no wise cast out. <verse number="38" style="v"/>For I am come down from heaven, not to do mine own will, but the will of him that sent me. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And this is the will of him that sent me, that of all that which he hath given me I should lose nothing, but should raise it up at the last day. <verse number="40" style="v"/>For this is the will of my Father, that every one that beholdeth the Son, and believeth on him, should have eternal life; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that I should raise him up</char></char></note>I will raise him up at the last day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v"/>The Jews therefore murmured concerning him, because he said, I am the bread which came down out of heaven. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And they said, Is not this Jesus, the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? how doth he now say, I am come down out of heaven? <verse number="43" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto them, Murmur not among yourselves. <verse number="44" style="v"/>No man can come to me, except the Father that sent me draw him: and I will raise him up in the last day. <verse number="45" style="v"/>It is written in the prophets, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 54:13">Isa. 54:13</ref>; (<ref loc="JER 31:34">Jer. 31:34</ref>?).</char></note>And they shall all be taught of God. Every one that hath heard from the Father, and hath learned, cometh unto me. <verse number="46" style="v"/>Not that any man hath seen the Father, save he that is from God, he hath seen the Father. <verse number="47" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that believeth hath eternal life. <verse number="48" style="v"/>I am the bread of life. <verse number="49" style="v"/>Your fathers ate the manna in the wilderness, and they died. <verse number="50" style="v"/>This is the bread which cometh down out of heaven, that a man may eat thereof, and not die. <verse number="51" style="v"/>I am the living bread which came down out of heaven: if any man eat of this bread, he shall live for ever: yea and the bread which I will give is my flesh, for the life of the world.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="52" style="v"/>The Jews therefore strove one with another, saying, How can this man give us his flesh to eat? <verse number="53" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except ye eat the flesh of the Son of man and drink his blood, ye have not life in yourselves. <verse number="54" style="v"/>He that eateth my flesh and drinketh my blood hath eternal life; and I will raise him up at the last day. <verse number="55" style="v"/>For my flesh is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">true meat</char>.</char></note>meat indeed, and my blood is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">true drink</char>.</char></note>drink indeed. <verse number="56" style="v"/>He that eateth my flesh and drinketh my blood abideth in me, and I in him. <verse number="57" style="v"/>As the living Father sent me, and I live because of the Father; so he that eateth me, he also shall live because of me. <verse number="58" style="v"/>This is the bread which came down out of heaven: not as the fathers ate, and died; he that eateth this bread shall live for ever. <verse number="59" style="v"/>These things said he in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a synagogue</char></char></note>the synagogue, as he taught in Capernaum.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="60" style="v"/>Many therefore of his disciples, when they heard <char style="add">this</char>, said, This is a hard saying; who can hear <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">him</char></char></note>it? <verse number="61" style="v"/>But Jesus knowing in himself that his disciples murmured at this, said unto them, Doth this cause you to stumble? <verse number="62" style="v"/><char style="add">What</char> then if ye should behold the Son of man ascending where he was before? <verse number="63" style="v"/>It is the spirit that giveth life; the flesh profiteth nothing: the words that I have spoken unto you are spirit, and are life. <verse number="64" style="v"/>But there are some of you that believe not. For Jesus knew from the beginning who they were that believed not, and who it was that should <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">deliver him up</char></char></note>betray him. <verse number="65" style="v"/>And he said, For this cause have I said unto you, that no man can come unto me, except it be given unto him of the Father.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="66" style="v"/>Upon this many of his disciples went back, and walked no more with him. <verse number="67" style="v"/>Jesus said therefore unto the twelve, Would ye also go away? <verse number="68" style="v"/>Simon Peter answered him, Lord, to whom shall we go? thou <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hast words</char></char></note>hast the words of eternal life. <verse number="69" style="v"/>And we have believed and know that thou art the Holy One of God. <verse number="70" style="v"/>Jesus answered them, Did not I choose you the twelve, and one of you is a devil? <verse number="71" style="v"/>Now he spake of Judas <char style="add">the son</char> of Simon Iscariot, for he it was that should <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">deliver him up</char></char></note>betray him, <char style="add">being</char> one of the twelve.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And after these things Jesus walked in Galilee: for he would not walk in Judaea, because the Jews sought to kill him. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Now the feast of the Jews, the feast of tabernacles, was at hand. <verse number="3" style="v"/>His brethren therefore said unto him, Depart hence, and go into Judaea, that thy disciples also may behold thy works which thou doest. <verse number="4" style="v"/>For no man doeth anything in secret, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">and seeketh it to be known openly</char>.</char></note>and himself seeketh to be known openly. If thou doest these things, manifest thyself to the world. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For even his brethren did not believe on him. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Jesus therefore saith unto them, My time is not yet come; but your time is always ready. <verse number="7" style="v"/>The world cannot hate you; but me it hateth, because I testify of it, that its works are evil. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Go ye up unto the feast: I go not up <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities add <char style="it">yet</char>.</char></note>unto this feast; because my time is not yet fulfilled. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And having said these things unto them, he abode <char style="add">still</char> in Galilee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>But when his brethren were gone up unto the feast, then went he also up, not publicly, but as it were in secret. <verse number="11" style="v"/>The Jews therefore sought him at the feast, and said, Where is he? <verse number="12" style="v"/>And there was much murmuring among the multitudes concerning him: some said, He is a good man; others said, Not so, but he leadeth the multitude astray. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Yet no man spake openly of him for fear of the Jews.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>But when it was now the midst of the feast Jesus went up into the temple, and taught. <verse number="15" style="v"/>The Jews therefore marvelled, saying, How knoweth this man letters, having never learned? <verse number="16" style="v"/>Jesus therefore answered them, and said, My teaching is not mine, but his that sent me. <verse number="17" style="v"/>If any man willeth to do his will, he shall know of the teaching, whether it is of God, or <char style="add">whether</char> I speak from myself. <verse number="18" style="v"/>He that speaketh from himself seeketh his own glory: but he that seeketh the glory of him that sent him, the same is true, and no unrighteousness is in him. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Did not Moses give you the law, and <char style="add">yet</char> none of you doeth the law? Why seek ye to kill me? <verse number="20" style="v"/>The multitude answered, Thou hast a demon: who seeketh to kill thee? <verse number="21" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto them, I did one work, and ye all marvel because thereof. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Moses hath given you circumcision (not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers); and on the sabbath ye circumcise a man. <verse number="23" style="v"/>If a man receiveth circumcision on the sabbath, that the law of Moses may not be broken; are ye wroth with me, because I made <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">a whole man sound</char>.</char></note>a man every whit whole on the sabbath? <verse number="24" style="v"/>Judge not according to appearance, but judge righteous judgment.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>Some therefore of them of Jerusalem said, Is not this he whom they seek to kill? <verse number="26" style="v"/>And lo, he speaketh openly, and they say nothing unto him. Can it be that the rulers indeed know that this is the Christ? <verse number="27" style="v"/>Howbeit we know this man whence he is: but when the Christ cometh, no one knoweth whence he is. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Jesus therefore cried in the temple, teaching and saying, Ye both know me, and know whence I am; and I am not come of myself, but he that sent me is true, whom ye know not. <verse number="29" style="v"/>I know him; because I am from him, and he sent me. <verse number="30" style="v"/>They sought therefore to take him: and no man laid his hand on him, because his hour was not yet come. <verse number="31" style="v"/>But of the multitude many believed on him; and they said, When the Christ shall come, will he do more signs than those which this man hath done? <verse number="32" style="v"/>The Pharisees heard the multitude murmuring these things concerning him; and the chief priests and the Pharisees sent officers to take him. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said, Yet a little while am I with you, and I go unto him that sent me. <verse number="34" style="v"/>Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me: and where I am, ye cannot come. <verse number="35" style="v"/>The Jews therefore said among themselves, Whither will this man go that we shall not find him? will he go unto the Dispersion <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">of</char>.</char></note>among the Greeks, and teach the Greeks? <verse number="36" style="v"/>What is this word that he said, Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me; and where I am, ye cannot come?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v"/>Now on the last day, the great <char style="add">day</char> of the feast, Jesus stood and cried, saying, If any man thirst, let him come unto me and drink. <verse number="38" style="v"/>He that believeth on me, as the scripture hath said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">out of his belly</char>.</char></note>from within him shall flow rivers of living water. <verse number="39" style="v"/>But this spake he of the Spirit, which they that believed on him were to receive: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">for the Holy Spirit was not yet given</char>.</char></note>for the Spirit was not yet <char style="add">given</char>; because Jesus was not yet glorified. <verse number="40" style="v"/><char style="add">Some</char> of the multitude therefore, when they heard these words, said, This is of a truth the prophet. <verse number="41" style="v"/>Others said, This is the Christ. But some said, What, doth the Christ come out of Galilee? <verse number="42" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="2SA 7:12-7:29">2 Sam. 7:12ff</ref>; <ref loc="MIC 5:2">Mic. 5:2</ref>.</char></note>Hath not the scripture said that the Christ cometh of the seed of David, and from Bethlehem, the village where David was? <verse number="43" style="v"/>So there arose a division in the multitude because of him. <verse number="44" style="v"/>And some of them would have taken him; but no man laid hands on him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v"/>The officers therefore came to the chief priests and Pharisees; and they said unto them, Why did ye not bring him? <verse number="46" style="v"/>The officers answered, Never man so spake. <verse number="47" style="v"/>The Pharisees therefore answered them, Are ye also led astray? <verse number="48" style="v"/>Hath any of the rulers believed on him, or of the Pharisees? <verse number="49" style="v"/>But this multitude that knoweth not the law are accursed. <verse number="50" style="v"/>Nicodemus saith unto them (he that came to him before, being one of them), <verse number="51" style="v"/>Doth our law judge a man, except it first hear from himself and know what he doeth? <verse number="52" style="v"/>They answered and said unto him, Art thou also of Galilee? Search, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">see: for out of Galilee etc.</char></char></note>see that out of Galilee ariseth no prophet.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="53" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Most of the ancient authorities omit <ref loc="JHN 7:53-8:11">7:53&#8211;8:11</ref>. Those which contain it vary much from each other.</char></note>[And they went every man unto his own house:</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c"/>
	<para style="nb"><verse number="1" style="v"/>but Jesus went unto the mount of Olives. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And early in the morning he came again into the temple, and all the people came unto him; and he sat down, and taught them. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And the scribes and the Pharisees bring a woman taken in adultery; and having set her in the midst, <verse number="4" style="v"/>they say unto him, Teacher, this woman hath been taken in adultery, in the very act. <verse number="5" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="LEV 20:10">Lev. 20:10</ref>; <ref loc="DEU 22:22-22:30">Dt. 22:22f</ref>.</char></note>Now in the law Moses commanded us to stone such: what then sayest thou of her? <verse number="6" style="v"/>And this they said, trying him, that they might have <char style="add">whereof</char> to accuse him. But Jesus stooped down, and with his finger wrote on the ground. <verse number="7" style="v"/>But when they continued asking him, he lifted up himself, and said unto them, He that is without sin among you, let him first cast a stone at her. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And again he stooped down, and with his finger wrote on the ground. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And they, when they heard it, went out one by one, beginning from the eldest, <char style="add">even</char> unto the last: and Jesus was left alone, and the woman, where she was, in the midst. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Jesus lifted up himself, and said unto her, Woman, where are they? did no man condemn thee? <verse number="11" style="v"/>And she said, No man, Lord. And Jesus said, Neither do I condemn thee: go thy way; from henceforth sin no more.]</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Again therefore Jesus spake unto them, saying, I am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in the darkness, but shall have the light of life. <verse number="13" style="v"/>The Pharisees therefore said unto him, Thou bearest witness of thyself; thy witness is not true. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto them, Even if I bear witness of myself, my witness is true; for I know whence I came, and whither I go; but ye know not whence I come, or whither I go. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Ye judge after the flesh; I judge no man. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Yea and if I judge, my judgment is true; for I am not alone, but I and the Father that sent me. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Yea and in your law it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Compare <ref loc="DEU 19:15">Dt. 19:15</ref>; <ref loc="DEU 17:6">17:6</ref>.</char></note>that the witness of two men is true. <verse number="18" style="v"/>I am he that beareth witness of myself, and the Father that sent me beareth witness of me. <verse number="19" style="v"/>They said therefore unto him, Where is thy Father? Jesus answered, Ye know neither me, nor my Father: if ye knew me, ye would know my Father also. <verse number="20" style="v"/>These words spake he in the treasury, as he taught in the temple: and no man took him; because his hour was not yet come.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>He said therefore again unto them, I go away, and ye shall seek me, and shall die in your sin: whither I go, ye cannot come. <verse number="22" style="v"/>The Jews therefore said, Will he kill himself, that he saith, Whither I go, ye cannot come? <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he said unto them, Ye are from beneath; I am from above: ye are of this world; I am not of this world. <verse number="24" style="v"/>I said therefore unto you, that ye shall die in your sins: for except ye believe that I am <char style="add">he</char>, ye shall die in your sins. <verse number="25" style="v"/>They said therefore unto him, Who art thou? Jesus said unto them, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Altogether that which I also speak unto you</char></char></note>Even that which I have also spoken unto you from the beginning. <verse number="26" style="v"/>I have many things to speak and to judge concerning you: howbeit he that sent me is true; and the things which I heard from him, these speak I unto the world. <verse number="27" style="v"/>They perceived not that he spake to them of the Father. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said, When ye have lifted up the Son of man, then shall ye know that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">I am</char> he: <char style="it">and I do</char></char></note>I am <char style="add">he</char>, and <char style="add">that</char> I do nothing of myself, but as the Father taught me, I speak these things. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And he that sent me is with me; he hath not left me alone; for I do always the things that are pleasing to him. <verse number="30" style="v"/>As he spake these things, many believed on him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said to those Jews that had believed him, If ye abide in my word, <char style="add">then</char> are ye truly my disciples; <verse number="32" style="v"/>and ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free. <verse number="33" style="v"/>They answered unto him, We are Abraham&#8217;s seed, and have never yet been in bondage to any man: how sayest thou, Ye shall be made free? <verse number="34" style="v"/>Jesus answered them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Every one that committeth sin is the bondservant of sin. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And the bondservant abideth not in the house for ever: the son abideth for ever. <verse number="36" style="v"/>If therefore the Son shall make you free, ye shall be free indeed. <verse number="37" style="v"/>I know that ye are Abraham&#8217;s seed; yet ye seek to kill me, because my word <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hath no place in you</char></char></note>hath not free course in you. <verse number="38" style="v"/>I speak the things which I have seen with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the Father: do ye also therefore the things which ye heard from the Father</char>.</char></note><char style="add">my</char> Father: and ye also do the things which ye heard from <char style="add">your</char> father. <verse number="39" style="v"/>They answered and said unto him, Our father is Abraham. Jesus saith unto them, If ye <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">are</char>.</char></note>were Abraham&#8217;s children, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">ye do the works of Abraham</char>.</char></note>ye would do the works of Abraham. <verse number="40" style="v"/>But now ye seek to kill me, a man that hath told you the truth, which I heard from God: this did not Abraham. <verse number="41" style="v"/>Ye do the works of your father. They said unto him, We were not born of fornication; we have one Father, <char style="add">even</char> God. <verse number="42" style="v"/>Jesus said unto them, If God were your Father, ye would love me: for I came forth and am come from God; for neither have I come of myself, but he sent me. <verse number="43" style="v"/>Why do ye not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">know</char></char></note>understand my speech? <char style="add">Even</char> because ye cannot hear my word. <verse number="44" style="v"/>Ye are of <char style="add">your</char> father the devil, and the lusts of your father it is your will to do. He was a murderer from the beginning, and standeth not in the truth, because there is no truth in him. <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">When</char> one <char style="it">speaketh a lie, he speaketh of his own: for his father also is a liar</char>.</char></note>When he speaketh a lie, he speaketh of his own: for he is a liar, and the father thereof. <verse number="45" style="v"/>But because I say the truth, ye believe me not. <verse number="46" style="v"/>Which of you convicteth me of sin? If I say truth, why do ye not believe me? <verse number="47" style="v"/>He that is of God heareth the words of God: for this cause ye hear <char style="add">them</char> not, because ye are not of God. <verse number="48" style="v"/>The Jews answered and said unto him, Say we not well that thou art a Samaritan, and hast a demon? <verse number="49" style="v"/>Jesus answered, I have not a demon; but I honor my Father, and ye dishonor me. <verse number="50" style="v"/>But I seek not mine own glory: there is one that seeketh and judgeth. <verse number="51" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, If a man keep my word, he shall never see death. <verse number="52" style="v"/>The Jews said unto him, Now we know that thou hast a demon. Abraham died, and the prophets; and thou sayest, If a man keep my word, he shall never taste of death. <verse number="53" style="v"/>Art thou greater than our father Abraham, who died? and the prophets died: whom makest thou thyself? <verse number="54" style="v"/>Jesus answered, If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing: it is my Father that glorifieth me; of whom ye say, that he is your God; <verse number="55" style="v"/>and ye have not known him: but I know him; and if I should say, I know him not, I shall be like unto you, a liar: but I know him, and keep his word. <verse number="56" style="v"/>Your father Abraham rejoiced <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that he should see</char></char></note>to see my day; and he saw it, and was glad. <verse number="57" style="v"/>The Jews therefore said unto him, Thou art not yet fifty years old, and hast thou seen Abraham? <verse number="58" style="v"/>Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Before Abraham was born, I am. <verse number="59" style="v"/>They took up stones therefore to cast at him: but Jesus <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was hidden, and went etc.</char></char></note>hid himself, and went out of the temple<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities add <char style="it">and going through the midst of them went his way and so passed by</char>.</char></note>.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And as he passed by, he saw a man blind from his birth. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And his disciples asked him, saying, Rabbi, who sinned, this man, or his parents, that he should be born blind? <verse number="3" style="v"/>Jesus answered, Neither did this man sin, nor his parents: but that the works of God should be made manifest in him. <verse number="4" style="v"/>We must work the works of him that sent me, while it is day: the night cometh, when no man can work. <verse number="5" style="v"/>When I am in the world, I am the light of the world. <verse number="6" style="v"/>When he had thus spoken, he spat on the ground, and made clay of the spittle, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and with the clay thereof anointed</char> his <char style="it">eyes</char></char></note>and anointed his eyes with the clay, <verse number="7" style="v"/>and said unto him, Go, wash in the pool of Siloam (which is by interpretation, Sent). He went away therefore, and washed, and came seeing. <verse number="8" style="v"/>The neighbors therefore, and they that saw him aforetime, that he was a beggar, said, Is not this he that sat and begged? <verse number="9" style="v"/>Others said, It is he: others said, No, but he is like him. He said, I am <char style="add">he</char>. <verse number="10" style="v"/>They said therefore unto him, How then were thine eyes opened? <verse number="11" style="v"/>He answered, The man that is called Jesus made clay, and anointed mine eyes, and said unto me, Go to Siloam, and wash: so I went away and washed, and I received sight. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And they said unto him, Where is he? He saith, I know not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>They bring to the Pharisees him that aforetime was blind. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Now it was the sabbath on the day when Jesus made the clay, and opened his eyes. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Again therefore the Pharisees also asked him how he received his sight. And he said unto them, He put clay upon mine eyes, and I washed, and I see. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Some therefore of the Pharisees said, This man is not from God, because he keepeth not the sabbath. But others said, How can a man that is a sinner do such signs? And there was a division among them. <verse number="17" style="v"/>They say therefore unto the blind man again, What sayest thou of him, in that he opened thine eyes? And he said, He is a prophet. <verse number="18" style="v"/>The Jews therefore did not believe concerning him, that he had been blind, and had received his sight, until they called the parents of him that had received his sight, <verse number="19" style="v"/>and asked them, saying, Is this your son, who ye say was born blind? how then doth he now see? <verse number="20" style="v"/>His parents answered and said, We know that this is our son, and that he was born blind: <verse number="21" style="v"/>but how he now seeth, we know not; or who opened his eyes, we know not: ask him; he is of age; he shall speak for himself. <verse number="22" style="v"/>These things said his parents, because they feared the Jews: for the Jews had agreed already, that if any man should confess him <char style="add">to be</char> Christ, he should be put out of the synagogue. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Therefore said his parents, He is of age; ask him. <verse number="24" style="v"/>So they called a second time the man that was blind, and said unto him, Give glory to God: we know that this man is a sinner. <verse number="25" style="v"/>He therefore answered, Whether he is a sinner, I know not: one thing I know, that, whereas I was blind, now I see. <verse number="26" style="v"/>They said therefore unto him, What did he to thee? how opened he thine eyes? <verse number="27" style="v"/>He answered them, I told you even now, and ye did not hear; wherefore would ye hear it again? would ye also become his disciples? <verse number="28" style="v"/>And they reviled him, and said, Thou art his disciple; but we are disciples of Moses. <verse number="29" style="v"/>We know that God hath spoken unto Moses: but as for this man, we know not whence he is. <verse number="30" style="v"/>The man answered and said unto them, Why, herein is the marvel, that ye know not whence he is, and <char style="add">yet</char> he opened mine eyes. <verse number="31" style="v"/>We know that God heareth not sinners: but if any man be a worshipper of God, and do his will, him he heareth. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Since the world began it was never heard that any one opened the eyes of a man born blind. <verse number="33" style="v"/>If this man were not from God, he could do nothing. <verse number="34" style="v"/>They answered and said unto him, Thou wast altogether born in sins, and dost thou teach us? And they cast him out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v"/>Jesus heard that they had cast him out; and finding him, he said, Dost thou believe on <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">the Son of Man</char>.</char></note>the Son of God? <verse number="36" style="v"/>He answered and said, And who is he, Lord, that I may believe on him? <verse number="37" style="v"/>Jesus said unto him, Thou hast both seen him, and he it is that speaketh with thee. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And he said, Lord, I believe. And he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The Greek word denotes an act of reverence, whether paid to a creature (as here) or to the Creator (see <ref loc="JHN 4:20">4:20</ref>).</char></note>worshipped him. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And Jesus said, For judgment came I into this world, that they that see not may see; and that they that see may become blind. <verse number="40" style="v"/>Those of the Pharisees who were with him heard these things, and said unto him, Are we also blind? <verse number="41" style="v"/>Jesus said unto them, If ye were blind, ye would have no sin: but now ye say, We see: your sin remaineth.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that entereth not by the door into the fold of the sheep, but climbeth up some other way, the same is a thief and a robber. <verse number="2" style="v"/>But he that entereth in by the door is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a shepherd</char></char></note>the shepherd of the sheep. <verse number="3" style="v"/>To him the porter openeth; and the sheep hear his voice: and he calleth his own sheep by name, and leadeth them out. <verse number="4" style="v"/>When he hath put forth all his own, he goeth before them, and the sheep follow him: for they know his voice. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And a stranger will they not follow, but will flee from him: for they know not the voice of strangers. <verse number="6" style="v"/>This <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">proverb</char></char></note>parable spake Jesus unto them: but they understood not what things they were which he spake unto them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said unto them again, Verily, verily, I say unto you, I am the door of the sheep. <verse number="8" style="v"/>All that came <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">before me</char>.</char></note>before me are thieves and robbers: but the sheep did not hear them. <verse number="9" style="v"/>I am the door; by me if any man enter in, he shall be saved, and shall go in and go out, and shall find pasture. <verse number="10" style="v"/>The thief cometh not, but that he may steal, and kill, and destroy: I came that they may have life, and may <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">have abundance</char></char></note>have <char style="add">it</char> abundantly. <verse number="11" style="v"/>I am the good shepherd: the good shepherd layeth down his life for the sheep. <verse number="12" style="v"/>He that is a hireling, and not a shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, beholdeth the wolf coming, and leaveth the sheep, and fleeth, and the wolf snatcheth them, and scattereth <char style="add">them</char>: <verse number="13" style="v"/><char style="add">he fleeth</char> because he is a hireling, and careth not for the sheep. <verse number="14" style="v"/>I am the good shepherd; and I know mine own, and mine own know me, <verse number="15" style="v"/>even as the Father knoweth me, and I know the Father; and I lay down my life for the sheep. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And other sheep I have, which are not of this fold: them also I must <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lead</char></char></note>bring, and they shall hear my voice; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">there shall be one flock</char></char></note>they shall become one flock, one shepherd. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Therefore doth the Father love me, because I lay down my life, that I may take it again. <verse number="18" style="v"/>No one <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">took it away</char>.</char></note>taketh it away from me, but I lay it down of myself. I have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">right</char></char></note>power to lay it down, and I have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">right</char></char></note>power to take it again. This commandment received I from my Father.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>There arose a division again among the Jews because of these words. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And many of them said, He hath a demon, and is mad; why hear ye him? <verse number="21" style="v"/>Others said, These are not the sayings of one possessed with a demon. Can a demon open the eyes of the blind?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">At that time was the feast</char>.</char></note>And it was the feast of the dedication at Jerusalem: <verse number="23" style="v"/>it was winter; and Jesus was walking in the temple in Solomon&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">portico</char></char></note>porch. <verse number="24" style="v"/>The Jews therefore came round about him, and said unto him, How long dost thou hold us in suspense? If thou art the Christ, tell us plainly. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Jesus answered them, I told you, and ye believe not: the works that I do in my Father&#8217;s name, these bear witness of me. <verse number="26" style="v"/>But ye believe not, because ye are not of my sheep. <verse number="27" style="v"/>My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me: <verse number="28" style="v"/>and I give unto them eternal life; and they shall never perish, and no one shall snatch them out of my hand. <verse number="29" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">That which my Father hath given unto me</char>.</char></note>My Father, who hath given <char style="add">them</char> unto me, is greater than all; and no one is able to snatch <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, aught</char></note><char style="add">them</char> out of the Father&#8217;s hand. <verse number="30" style="v"/>I and the Father are one. <verse number="31" style="v"/>The Jews took up stones again to stone him. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Jesus answered them, Many good works have I showed you from the Father; for which of those works do ye stone me? <verse number="33" style="v"/>The Jews answered him, For a good work we stone thee not, but for blasphemy; and because that thou, being a man, makest thyself God. <verse number="34" style="v"/>Jesus answered them, Is it not written in your law, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 82:6">Ps. 82:6</ref>.</char></note>I said, Ye are gods? <verse number="35" style="v"/>If he called them gods, unto whom the word of God came (and the scripture cannot be broken), <verse number="36" style="v"/>say ye of him, whom the Father <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">consecrated</char></char></note>sanctified and sent into the world, Thou blasphemest; because I said, I am <char style="add">the</char> Son of God? <verse number="37" style="v"/>If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not. <verse number="38" style="v"/>But if I do them, though ye believe not me, believe the works: that ye may know and understand that the Father is in me, and I in the Father. <verse number="39" style="v"/>They sought again to take him: and he went forth out of their hand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v"/>And he went away again beyond the Jordan into the place where John was at the first baptizing; and there he abode. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And many came unto him; and they said, John indeed did no sign: but all things whatsoever John spake of this man were true. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And many believed on him there.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now a certain man was sick, Lazarus of Bethany, of the village of Mary and her sister Martha. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And it was that Mary who anointed the Lord with ointment, and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick. <verse number="3" style="v"/>The sisters therefore sent unto him, saying, Lord, behold, he whom thou lovest is sick. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But when Jesus heard it, he said, This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, that the Son of God may be glorified thereby. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus. <verse number="6" style="v"/>When therefore he heard that he was sick, he abode at that time two days in the place where he was. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Then after this he saith to the disciples, Let us go into Judaea again. <verse number="8" style="v"/>The disciples say unto him, Rabbi, the Jews were but now seeking to stone thee; and goest thou thither again? <verse number="9" style="v"/>Jesus answered, Are there not twelve hours in the day? If a man walk in the day, he stumbleth not, because he seeth the light of this world. <verse number="10" style="v"/>But if a man walk in the night, he stumbleth, because the light is not in him. <verse number="11" style="v"/>These things spake he: and after this he saith unto them, Our friend Lazarus is fallen asleep; but I go, that I may awake him out of sleep. <verse number="12" style="v"/>The disciples therefore said unto him, Lord, if he is fallen asleep, he will <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">be saved</char>.</char></note>recover. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Now Jesus had spoken of his death: but they thought that he spake of taking rest in sleep. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Then Jesus therefore said unto them plainly, Lazarus is dead. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And I am glad for your sakes that I was not there, to the intent ye may believe; nevertheless let us go unto him. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Thomas therefore, who is called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Twin</char>.</char></note>Didymus, said unto his fellow-disciples, Let us also go, that we may die with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>So when Jesus came, he found that he had been in the tomb four days already. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Now Bethany was nigh unto Jerusalem, about fifteen furlongs off; <verse number="19" style="v"/>and many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary, to console them concerning their brother. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Martha therefore, when she heard that Jesus was coming, went and met him: but Mary still sat in the house. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Martha therefore said unto Jesus, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And even now I know that, whatsoever thou shalt ask of God, God will give thee. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto her, Thy brother shall rise again. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Martha saith unto him, I know that he shall rise again in the resurrection at the last day. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Jesus said unto her, I am the resurrection, and the life: he that believeth on me, though he die, yet shall he live; <verse number="26" style="v"/>and whosoever liveth and believeth on me shall never die. Believest thou this? <verse number="27" style="v"/>She saith unto him, Yea, Lord: I have believed that thou art the Christ, the Son of God, <char style="add">even</char> he that cometh into the world. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And when she had said this, she went away, and called Mary <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">her sister, saying secretly</char></char></note>her sister secretly, saying, The Teacher is here, and calleth thee. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And she, when she heard it, arose quickly, and went unto him. <verse number="30" style="v"/>(Now Jesus was not yet come into the village, but was still in the place where Martha met him.) <verse number="31" style="v"/>The Jews then who were with her in the house, and were consoling her, when they saw Mary, that she rose up quickly and went out, followed her, supposing that she was going unto the tomb to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">wail</char>.</char></note>weep there. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Mary therefore, when she came where Jesus was, and saw him, fell down at his feet, saying unto him, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died. <verse number="33" style="v"/>When Jesus therefore saw her <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">wailing</char>.</char></note>weeping, and the Jews <char style="add">also</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">wailing</char>.</char></note>weeping who came with her, he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was moved with indignation in the spirit</char></char></note>groaned in the spirit, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">troubled himself</char>.</char></note>was troubled, <verse number="34" style="v"/>and said, Where have ye laid him? They say unto him, Lord, come and see. <verse number="35" style="v"/>Jesus wept. <verse number="36" style="v"/>The Jews therefore said, Behold how he loved him! <verse number="37" style="v"/>But some of them said, Could not this man, who opened the eyes of him that was blind, have caused that this man also should not die? <verse number="38" style="v"/>Jesus therefore again <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">being moved with indignation in himself</char></char></note>groaning in himself cometh to the tomb. Now it was a cave, and a stone lay <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">upon</char></char></note>against it. <verse number="39" style="v"/>Jesus saith, Take ye away the stone. Martha, the sister of him that was dead, saith unto him, Lord, by this time <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">he stinketh</char>.</char></note>the body decayeth; for he hath been <char style="add">dead</char> four days. <verse number="40" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto her, Said I not unto thee, that, if thou believedst, thou shouldest see the glory of God? <verse number="41" style="v"/>So they took away the stone. And Jesus lifted up his eyes, and said, Father, I thank thee that thou heardest me. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And I knew that thou hearest me always: but because of the multitude that standeth around I said it, that they may believe that thou didst send me. <verse number="43" style="v"/>And when he had thus spoken, he cried with a loud voice, Lazarus, come forth. <verse number="44" style="v"/>He that was dead came forth, bound hand and foot with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">grave-bands</char></char></note>grave-clothes; and his face was bound about with a napkin. Jesus saith unto them, Loose him, and let him go.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v"/>Many therefore of the Jews, who came to Mary and beheld <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">the things which he did</char>.</char></note>that which he did, believed on him. <verse number="46" style="v"/>But some of them went away to the Pharisees, and told them the things which Jesus had done.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v"/>The chief priests therefore and the Pharisees gathered a council, and said, What do we? for this man doeth many signs. <verse number="48" style="v"/>If we let him thus alone, all men will believe on him: and the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation. <verse number="49" style="v"/>But a certain one of them, Caiaphas, being high priest that year, said unto them, Ye know nothing at all, <verse number="50" style="v"/>nor do ye take account that it is expedient for you that one man should die for the people, and that the whole nation perish not. <verse number="51" style="v"/>Now this he said not of himself: but being high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus should die for the nation; <verse number="52" style="v"/>and not for the nation only, but that he might also gather together into one the children of God that are scattered abroad. <verse number="53" style="v"/>So from that day forth they took counsel that they might put him to death.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v"/>Jesus therefore walked no more openly among the Jews, but departed thence into the country near to the wilderness, into a city called Ephraim; and there he tarried with the disciples. <verse number="55" style="v"/>Now the passover of the Jews was at hand: and many went up to Jerusalem out of the country before the passover, to purify themselves. <verse number="56" style="v"/>They sought therefore for Jesus, and spake one with another, as they stood in the temple, What think ye? That he will not come to the feast? <verse number="57" style="v"/>Now the chief priests and the Pharisees had given commandment, that, if any man knew where he was, he should show it, that they might take him.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Jesus therefore six days before the passover came to Bethany, where Lazarus was, whom Jesus raised from the dead. <verse number="2" style="v"/>So they made him a supper there: and Martha served; but Lazarus was one of them that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">reclined</char>.</char></note>sat at meat with him. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Mary therefore took a pound of ointment of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">liquid nard</char></char></note>pure nard, very precious, and anointed the feet of Jesus, and wiped his feet with her hair: and the house was filled with the odor of the ointment. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But Judas Iscariot, one of his disciples, that should <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">deliver him up</char></char></note>betray him, saith, <verse number="5" style="v"/>Why was not this ointment sold for three hundred <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="JHN 6:7">6:7</ref>.</char></note>shillings, and given to the poor? <verse number="6" style="v"/>Now this he said, not because he cared for the poor; but because he was a thief, and having the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">box</char></char></note>bag <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">carried what was put therein</char></char></note>took away what was put therein. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Let her alone:</char> it was <char style="it">that she might keep it</char></char></note>Suffer her to keep it against the day of my burying. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For the poor ye have always with you; but me ye have not always.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>The common people therefore of the Jews learned that he was there: and they came, not for Jesus&#8217; sake only, but that they might see Lazarus also, whom he had raised from the dead. <verse number="10" style="v"/>But the chief priests took counsel that they might put Lazarus also to death; <verse number="11" style="v"/>because that by reason of him many of the Jews went away, and believed on Jesus.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>On the morrow <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">the common people</char>. See <ref loc="JHN 12:9">verse 9</ref>.</char></note>a great multitude that had come to the feast, when they heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem, <verse number="13" style="v"/>took the branches of the palm trees, and went forth to meet him, and cried out, Hosanna: Blessed <char style="add">is</char> he that cometh in the name of the Lord, even the King of Israel. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Jesus, having found a young ass, sat thereon; as it is written, <verse number="15" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ZEC 9:9">Zech. 9:9</ref>.</char></note>Fear not, daughter of Zion: behold, thy King cometh, sitting on an ass&#8217;s colt. <verse number="16" style="v"/>These things understood not his disciples at the first: but when Jesus was glorified, then remembered they that these things were written of him, and that they had done these things unto him. <verse number="17" style="v"/>The multitude therefore that was with him when he called Lazarus out of the tomb, and raised him from the dead, bare witness. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For this cause also the multitude went and met him, for that they heard that he had done this sign. <verse number="19" style="v"/>The Pharisees therefore said among themselves, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Ye behold</char></char></note>Behold how ye prevail nothing; lo, the world is gone after him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>Now there were certain Greeks among those that went up to worship at the feast: <verse number="21" style="v"/>these therefore came to Philip, who was of Bethsaida of Galilee, and asked him, saying, Sir, we would see Jesus. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Philip cometh and telleth Andrew: Andrew cometh, and Philip, and they tell Jesus. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And Jesus answereth them, saying, The hour is come, that the Son of man should be glorified. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except a grain of wheat fall into the earth and die, it abideth by itself alone; but if it die, it beareth much fruit. <verse number="25" style="v"/>He that loveth his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">life</char> in these places represents two different Greek words.</char></note>life loseth it; and he that hateth his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">life</char> in these places represents two different Greek words.</char></note>life in this world shall keep it unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">life</char> in these places represents two different Greek words.</char></note>life eternal. <verse number="26" style="v"/>If any man serve me, let him follow me; and where I am, there shall also my servant be: if any man serve me, him will the Father honor. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Now is my soul troubled; and what shall I say? Father, save me from this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hour?</char></char></note>hour. But for this cause came I unto this hour. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Father, glorify thy name. There came therefore a voice out of heaven, <char style="add">saying</char>, I have both glorified it, and will glorify it again. <verse number="29" style="v"/>The multitude therefore, that stood by, and heard it, said that it had thundered: others said, An angel hath spoken to him. <verse number="30" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said, This voice hath not come for my sake, but for your sakes. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Now is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a judgment</char></char></note>the judgment of this world: now shall the prince of this world be cast out. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And I, if I be lifted up <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">out of</char></char></note>from the earth, will draw all men unto myself. <verse number="33" style="v"/>But this he said, signifying by what manner of death he should die. <verse number="34" style="v"/>The multitude therefore answered him, We have heard out of the law that the Christ abideth for ever: and how sayest thou, The Son of man must be lifted up? who is this Son of man? <verse number="35" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said unto them, Yet a little while is the light <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char></char></note>among you. Walk while ye have the light, that darkness overtake you not: and he that walketh in the darkness knoweth not whither he goeth. <verse number="36" style="v"/>While ye have the light, believe on the light, that ye may become sons of light.</para>
	<para style="p">These things spake Jesus, and he departed and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was hidden from them</char></char></note>hid himself from them. <verse number="37" style="v"/>But though he had done so many signs before them, yet they believed not on him: <verse number="38" style="v"/>that the word of Isaiah the prophet might be fulfilled, which he spake,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 53:1">Isa. 53:1</ref>.</char></note>Lord, who hath believed our report?</para>
	<para style="q1">And to whom hath the arm of the Lord been revealed?</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="39" style="v"/>For this cause they could not believe, for that Isaiah said again,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="40" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 6:10">Isa. 6:10</ref>.</char></note>He hath blinded their eyes, and he hardened their heart;</para>
	<para style="q1">Lest they should see with their eyes, and perceive with their heart,</para>
	<para style="q1">And should turn,</para>
	<para style="q1">And I should heal them.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="41" style="v"/>These things said Isaiah, because he saw his glory; and he spake of him. <verse number="42" style="v"/>Nevertheless even of the rulers many believed on him; but because of the Pharisees they did not confess <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, him</char></note><char style="add">it</char>, lest they should be put out of the synagogue: <verse number="43" style="v"/>for they loved the glory <char style="add">that is</char> of men more than the glory <char style="add">that is</char> of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v"/>And Jesus cried and said, He that believeth on me, believeth not on me, but on him that sent me. <verse number="45" style="v"/>And he that beholdeth me beholdeth him that sent me. <verse number="46" style="v"/>I am come a light into the world, that whosoever believeth on me may not abide in the darkness. <verse number="47" style="v"/>And if any man hear my sayings, and keep them not, I judge him not: for I came not to judge the world, but to save the world. <verse number="48" style="v"/>He that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my sayings, hath one that judgeth him: the word that I spake, the same shall judge him in the last day. <verse number="49" style="v"/>For I spake not from myself; but the Father that sent me, he hath given me a commandment, what I should say, and what I should speak. <verse number="50" style="v"/>And I know that his commandment is life eternal; the things therefore which I speak, even as the Father hath said unto me, so I speak.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now before the feast of the passover, Jesus knowing that his hour was come that he should depart out of this world unto the Father, having loved his own that were in the world, he loved them <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to the uttermost</char></char></note>unto the end. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And during supper, the devil having already put into the heart of Judas Iscariot, Simon&#8217;s <char style="add">son</char>, to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">deliver him up</char></char></note>betray him, <verse number="3" style="v"/><char style="add">Jesus</char>, knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands, and that he came forth from God, and goeth unto God, <verse number="4" style="v"/>riseth from supper, and layeth aside his garments; and he took a towel, and girded himself. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Then he poureth water into the basin, and began to wash the disciples&#8217; feet, and to wipe them with the towel wherewith he was girded. <verse number="6" style="v"/>So he cometh to Simon Peter. He saith unto him, Lord, dost thou wash my feet? <verse number="7" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto him, What I do thou knowest not now; but thou shalt understand hereafter. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Peter saith unto him, Thou shalt never wash my feet. Jesus answered him, If I wash thee not, thou hast no part with me. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Simon Peter saith unto him, Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Jesus saith to him, He that is bathed needeth not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">save</char>, and <char style="it">his feet</char>.</char></note>save to wash his feet, but is clean every whit: and ye are clean, but not all. <verse number="11" style="v"/>For he knew him that should <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">deliver him up</char></char></note>betray him; therefore said he, Ye are not all clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>So when he had washed their feet, and taken his garments, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">reclined</char>.</char></note>sat down again, he said unto them, Know ye what I have done to you? <verse number="13" style="v"/>Ye call me, Teacher, and, Lord: and ye say well; for so I am. <verse number="14" style="v"/>If I then, the Lord and the Teacher, have washed your feet, ye also ought to wash one another&#8217;s feet. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For I have given you an example, that ye also should do as I have done to you. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, A <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant is not greater than his lord; neither <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">an apostle</char>.</char></note>one that is sent greater than he that sent him. <verse number="17" style="v"/>If ye know these things, blessed are ye if ye do them. <verse number="18" style="v"/>I speak not of you all: I know whom I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">chose</char></char></note>have chosen: but that the scripture may be fulfilled, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 41:9">Ps. 41:9</ref>.</char></note>He that eateth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">his bread with me</char>.</char></note>my bread lifted up his heel against me. <verse number="19" style="v"/>From henceforth I tell you before it come to pass, that, when it is come to pass, ye may believe that I am <char style="add">he</char>. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that receiveth whomsoever I send receiveth me; and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>When Jesus had thus said, he was troubled in the spirit, and testified, and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, that one of you shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">deliver me up</char></char></note>betray me. <verse number="22" style="v"/>The disciples looked one on another, doubting of whom he spake. <verse number="23" style="v"/>There was at the table reclining in Jesus&#8217; bosom one of his disciples, whom Jesus loved. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Simon Peter therefore beckoneth to him, and saith unto him, Tell <char style="add">us</char> who it is of whom he speaketh. <verse number="25" style="v"/>He leaning back, as he was, on Jesus&#8217; breast saith unto him, Lord, who is it? <verse number="26" style="v"/>Jesus therefore answereth, He it is, for whom I shall dip the sop, and give it him. So when he had dipped the sop, he taketh and giveth it to Judas, <char style="add">the son</char> of Simon Iscariot. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And after the sop, then entered Satan into him. Jesus therefore saith unto him, What thou doest, do quickly. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Now no man at the table knew for what intent he spake this unto him. <verse number="29" style="v"/>For some thought, because Judas had the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">box</char></char></note>bag, that Jesus said unto him, Buy what things we have need of for the feast; or, that he should give something to the poor. <verse number="30" style="v"/>He then having received the sop went out straightway: and it was night.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>When therefore he was gone out, Jesus saith, Now <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was</char></char></note>is the Son of man glorified, and God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was</char></char></note>is glorified in him; <verse number="32" style="v"/>and God shall glorify him in himself, and straightway shall he glorify him. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Little children, yet a little while I am with you. Ye shall seek me: and as I said unto the Jews, Whither I go, ye cannot come; so now I say unto you. <verse number="34" style="v"/>A new commandment I give unto you, that ye love one another; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">even as I loved you, that ye also may love one another</char>.</char></note>even as I have loved you, that ye also love one another. <verse number="35" style="v"/>By this shall all men know that ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v"/>Simon Peter saith unto him, Lord, whither goest thou? Jesus answered, Whither I go, thou canst not follow me now; but thou shalt follow afterwards. <verse number="37" style="v"/>Peter saith unto him, Lord, why cannot I follow thee even now? I will lay down my life for thee. <verse number="38" style="v"/>Jesus answereth, Wilt thou lay down thy life for me? Verily, verily, I say unto thee, The cock shall not crow, till thou hast denied me thrice.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Let not your heart be troubled: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">ye believe in God</char></char></note>believe in God, believe also in me. <verse number="2" style="v"/>In my Father&#8217;s house are many <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">abiding-places</char></char></note>mansions; if it were not so, I would have told you; for I go to prepare a place for you. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And if I go and prepare a place for you, I come again, and will receive you unto myself; that where I am, <char style="add">there</char> ye may be also. <verse number="4" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">And whither I go ye know, and the way ye know</char>.</char></note>And whither I go, ye know the way. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Thomas saith unto him, Lord, we know not whither thou goest; how know we the way? <verse number="6" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, and the truth, and the life: no one cometh unto the Father, but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">through</char></char></note>by me. <verse number="7" style="v"/>If ye had known me, ye would have known my Father also: from henceforth ye know him, and have seen him. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Philip saith unto him, Lord, show us the Father, and it sufficeth us. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto him, Have I been so long time with you, and dost thou not know me, Philip? he that hath seen me hath seen the Father; how sayest thou, Show us the Father? <verse number="10" style="v"/>Believest thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? the words that I say unto you I speak not from myself: but the Father abiding in me doeth his works. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Believe me that I am in the Father, and the Father in me: or else believe me for the very works&#8217; sake. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that believeth on me, the works that I do shall he do also; and greater <char style="add">works</char> than these shall he do; because I go unto the Father. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And whatsoever ye shall ask in my name, that will I do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son. <verse number="14" style="v"/>If ye shall ask <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities add <char style="it">me</char>.</char></note>anything in my name, that will I do. <verse number="15" style="v"/>If ye love me, ye will keep my commandments. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And I will <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">make request of</char>.</char></note>pray the Father, and he shall give you another <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Advocate</char>. Or, <char style="it">Helper</char>. Greek <char style="it">Paraclete</char>.</char></note>Comforter, that he may be with you for ever, <verse number="17" style="v"/><char style="add">even</char> the Spirit of truth: whom the world cannot receive; for it beholdeth him not, neither knoweth him: ye know him; for he abideth with you, and shall be in you. <verse number="18" style="v"/>I will not leave you <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">orphans</char></char></note>desolate: I come unto you. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Yet a little while, and the world beholdeth me no more; but ye behold me: because I live, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and ye shall live</char>.</char></note>ye shall live also. <verse number="20" style="v"/>In that day ye shall know that I am in my Father, and ye in me, and I in you. <verse number="21" style="v"/>He that hath my commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me: and he that loveth me shall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifest myself unto him. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Judas (not Iscariot) saith unto him, Lord, what is come to pass that thou wilt manifest thyself unto us, and not unto the world? <verse number="23" style="v"/>Jesus answered and said unto him, If a man love me, he will keep my word: and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him. <verse number="24" style="v"/>He that loveth me not keepeth not my words: and the word which ye hear is not mine, but the Father&#8217;s who sent me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>These things have I spoken unto you, while <char style="add">yet</char> abiding with you. <verse number="26" style="v"/>But the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Advocate</char>. Or, <char style="it">Helper</char>. Greek <char style="it">Paraclete</char>.</char></note>Comforter, <char style="add">even</char> the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and bring to your remembrance all that I said unto you. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Peace I leave with you; my peace I give unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto you. Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be fearful. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Ye heard how I said to you, I go away, and I come unto you. If ye loved me, ye would have rejoiced, because I go unto the Father: for the Father is greater than I. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And now I have told you before it come to pass, that, when it is come to pass, ye may believe. <verse number="30" style="v"/>I will no more speak much with you, for the prince of the world cometh: and he hath nothing <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in me. But that etc.&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. I do, arise etc.</char></char></note>in me; <verse number="31" style="v"/>but that the world may know that I love the Father, and as the Father gave me commandment, even so I do. Arise, let us go hence.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>I am the true vine, and my Father is the husbandman. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Every branch in me that beareth not fruit, he taketh it away: and every <char style="add">branch</char> that beareth fruit, he cleanseth it, that it may bear more fruit. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Already ye are clean because of the word which I have spoken unto you. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Abide in me, and I in you. As the branch cannot bear fruit of itself, except it abide in the vine; so neither can ye, except ye abide in me. <verse number="5" style="v"/>I am the vine, ye are the branches: He that abideth in me, and I in him, the same beareth much fruit: for apart from me ye can do nothing. <verse number="6" style="v"/>If a man abide not in me, he is cast forth as a branch, and is withered; and they gather them, and cast them into the fire, and they are burned. <verse number="7" style="v"/>If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ask whatsoever ye will, and it shall be done unto you. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Herein <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was</char></char></note>is my Father glorified, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">that ye bear much fruit, and be my disciples</char>.</char></note>that ye bear much fruit; and <char style="add">so</char> shall ye be my disciples. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Even as the Father hath loved me, I also have loved you: abide ye in my love. <verse number="10" style="v"/>If ye keep my commandments, ye shall abide in my love; even as I have kept my Father&#8217;s commandments, and abide in his love. <verse number="11" style="v"/>These things have I spoken unto you, that my joy may be in you, and <char style="add">that</char> your joy may be made full. <verse number="12" style="v"/>This is my commandment, that ye love one another, even as I have loved you. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Greater love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Ye are my friends, if ye do the things which I command you. <verse number="15" style="v"/>No longer do I call you <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants; for the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant knoweth not what his lord doeth: but I have called you friends; for all things that I heard from my Father I have made known unto you. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Ye did not choose me, but I chose you, and appointed you, that ye should go and bear fruit, and <char style="add">that</char> your fruit should abide: that whatsoever ye shall ask of the Father in my name, he may give it you. <verse number="17" style="v"/>These things I command you, that ye may love one another. <verse number="18" style="v"/>If the world hateth you, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">know ye</char></char></note>ye know that it hath hated me before <char style="add">it hated</char> you. <verse number="19" style="v"/>If ye were of the world, the world would love its own: but because ye are not of the world, but I chose you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Remember the word that I said unto you, A <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant is not greater than his lord. If they persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they kept my word, they will keep yours also. <verse number="21" style="v"/>But all these things will they do unto you for my name&#8217;s sake, because they know not him that sent me. <verse number="22" style="v"/>If I had not come and spoken unto them, they had not had sin: but now they have no excuse for their sin. <verse number="23" style="v"/>He that hateth me hateth my Father also. <verse number="24" style="v"/>If I had not done among them the works which none other did, they had not had sin: but now have they both seen and hated both me and my Father. <verse number="25" style="v"/>But <char style="add">this cometh to pass</char>, that the word may be fulfilled that is written in their law, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 35:19">Ps. 35:19</ref>; <ref loc="PSA 69:4">69:4</ref>.</char></note>They hated me without a cause. <verse number="26" style="v"/>But when the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Advocate</char>. Or, <char style="it">Helper</char>. Greek <char style="it">Paraclete</char>.</char></note>Comforter is come, whom I will send unto you from the Father, <char style="add">even</char> the Spirit of truth, which <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">goeth forth from</char></char></note>proceedeth from the Father, he shall bear witness of me: <verse number="27" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and bear ye also witness</char></char></note>and ye also bear witness, because ye have been with me from the beginning.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>These things have I spoken unto you, that ye should not be caused to stumble. <verse number="2" style="v"/>They shall put you out of the synagogues: yea, the hour cometh, that whosoever killeth you shall think that he offereth service unto God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And these things will they do, because they have not known the Father, nor me. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But these things have I spoken unto you, that when their hour is come, ye may remember them, how that I told you. And these things I said not unto you from the beginning, because I was with you. <verse number="5" style="v"/>But now I go unto him that sent me; and none of you asketh me, Whither goest thou? <verse number="6" style="v"/>But because I have spoken these things unto you, sorrow hath filled your heart. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Nevertheless I tell you the truth: It is expedient for you that I go away; for if I go not away, the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Advocate</char>. Or, <char style="it">Helper</char>. Greek <char style="it">Paraclete</char>.</char></note>Comforter will not come unto you; but if I go, I will send him unto you. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he, when he is come, will convict the world in respect of sin, and of righteousness, and of judgment: <verse number="9" style="v"/>of sin, because they believe not on me; <verse number="10" style="v"/>of righteousness, because I go to the Father, and ye behold me no more; <verse number="11" style="v"/>of judgment, because the prince of this world hath been judged. <verse number="12" style="v"/>I have yet many things to say unto you, but ye cannot bear them now. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Howbeit when he, the Spirit of truth, is come, he shall guide you into all the truth: for he shall not speak from himself; but what things soever he shall hear, <char style="add">these</char> shall he speak: and he shall declare unto you the things that are to come. <verse number="14" style="v"/>He shall glorify me: for he shall take of mine, and shall declare <char style="add">it</char> unto you. <verse number="15" style="v"/>All things whatsoever the Father hath are mine: therefore said I, that he taketh of mine, and shall declare <char style="add">it</char> unto you. <verse number="16" style="v"/>A little while, and ye behold me no more; and again a little while, and ye shall see me. <verse number="17" style="v"/><char style="add">Some</char> of his disciples therefore said one to another, What is this that he saith unto us, A little while, and ye behold me not; and again a little while, and ye shall see me: and, Because I go to the Father? <verse number="18" style="v"/>They said therefore, What is this that he saith, A little while? We know not what he saith. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Jesus perceived that they were desirous to ask him, and he said unto them, Do ye inquire among yourselves concerning this, that I said, A little while, and ye behold me not, and again a little while, and ye shall see me? <verse number="20" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto you, that ye shall weep and lament, but the world shall rejoice: ye shall be sorrowful, but your sorrow shall be turned into joy. <verse number="21" style="v"/>A woman when she is in travail hath sorrow, because her hour is come: but when she is delivered of the child, she remembereth no more the anguish, for the joy that a man is born into the world. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And ye therefore now have sorrow: but I will see you again, and your heart shall rejoice, and your joy no one taketh away from you. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And in that day ye shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">ask me nothing</char>. Compare <ref loc="JHN 16:26">verse 26</ref>; <ref loc="JHN 14:13">14:13</ref>, <ref loc="JHN 14:20">20</ref>.</char></note>ask me no question. Verily, verily, I say unto you, If ye shall ask anything of the Father, he will give it you in my name. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Hitherto have ye asked nothing in my name: ask, and ye shall receive, that your joy may be made full.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>These things have I spoken unto you in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">parables</char></char></note>dark sayings: the hour cometh, when I shall no more speak unto you in dark sayings, but shall tell you plainly of the Father. <verse number="26" style="v"/>In that day ye shall ask in my name: and I say not unto you, that I will <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">make request of</char>.</char></note>pray the Father for you; <verse number="27" style="v"/>for the Father himself loveth you, because ye have loved me, and have believed that I came forth from the Father. <verse number="28" style="v"/>I came out from the Father, and am come into the world: again, I leave the world, and go unto the Father. <verse number="29" style="v"/>His disciples say, Lo, now speakest thou plainly, and speakest no <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">parable</char></char></note>dark saying. <verse number="30" style="v"/>Now know we that thou knowest all things, and needest not that any man should ask thee: by this we believe that thou camest forth from God. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Jesus answered them, Do ye now believe? <verse number="32" style="v"/>Behold, the hour cometh, yea, is come, that ye shall be scattered, every man to his own, and shall leave me alone: and <char style="add">yet</char> I am not alone, because the Father is with me. <verse number="33" style="v"/>These things have I spoken unto you, that in me ye may have peace. In the world ye have tribulation: but be of good cheer; I have overcome the world.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>These things spake Jesus; and lifting up his eyes to heaven, he said, Father, the hour is come; glorify thy Son, that the Son may glorify thee: <verse number="2" style="v"/>even as thou gavest him authority over all flesh, that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">whatsoever thou hast given him, to them he etc.</char></char></note>to all whom thou hast given him, he should give eternal life. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And this is life eternal, that they should know thee the only true God, and him whom thou didst send, <char style="add">even</char> Jesus Christ. <verse number="4" style="v"/>I glorified thee on the earth, having accomplished the work which thou hast given me to do. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And now, Father, glorify thou me with thine own self with the glory which I had with thee before the world was. <verse number="6" style="v"/>I manifested thy name unto the men whom thou gavest me out of the world: thine they were, and thou gavest them to me; and they have kept thy word. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Now they know that all things whatsoever thou hast given me are from thee: <verse number="8" style="v"/>for the words which thou gavest me I have given unto them; and they received <char style="add">them</char>, and knew of a truth that I came forth from thee, and they believed that thou didst send me. <verse number="9" style="v"/>I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">make request</char>.</char></note>pray for them: I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">make request</char>.</char></note>pray not for the world, but for those whom thou hast given me; for they are thine: <verse number="10" style="v"/>and all things that are mine are thine, and thine are mine: and I am glorified in them. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And I am no more in the world, and these are in the world, and I come to thee. Holy Father, keep them in thy name which thou hast given me, that they may be one, even as we <char style="add">are</char>. <verse number="12" style="v"/>While I was with them, I kept them in thy name which thou hast given me: and I guarded them, and not one of them perished, but the son of perdition; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 41:9">Ps. 41:9</ref>?</char></note>that the scripture might be fulfilled. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But now I come to thee; and these things I speak in the world, that they may have my joy made full in themselves. <verse number="14" style="v"/>I have given them thy word; and the world hated them, because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world. <verse number="15" style="v"/>I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">make request</char>.</char></note>pray not that thou shouldest take them <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">out of</char>.</char></note>from the world, but that thou shouldest keep them <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">out of</char>.</char></note>from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">evil</char></char></note>the evil <char style="add">one</char>. <verse number="16" style="v"/>They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world. <verse number="17" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Consecrate</char></char></note>Sanctify them in the truth: thy word is truth. <verse number="18" style="v"/>As thou didst send me into the world, even so sent I them into the world. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And for their sakes I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">consecrate</char></char></note>sanctify myself, that they themselves also may be sanctified in truth. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Neither for these only do I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">make request</char>.</char></note>pray, but for them also that believe on me through their word; <verse number="21" style="v"/>that they may all be one; even as thou, Father, <char style="add">art</char> in me, and I in thee, that they also may be in us: that the world may believe that thou didst send me. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the glory which thou hast given me I have given unto them; that they may be one, even as we <char style="add">are</char> one; <verse number="23" style="v"/>I in them, and thou in me, that they may be perfected into one; that the world may know that thou didst send me, and lovedst them, even as thou lovedst me. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Father, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">that which thou hast given me, I desire that where I am, they also may be with me, that etc.</char></char></note>I desire that they also whom thou hast given me be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory, which thou hast given me: for thou lovedst me before the foundation of the world. <verse number="25" style="v"/>O righteous Father, the world knew thee not, but I knew thee; and these knew that thou didst send me; <verse number="26" style="v"/>and I made known unto them thy name, and will make it known; that the love wherewith thou lovedst me may be in them, and I in them.</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>When Jesus had spoken these words, he went forth with his disciples over the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">ravine</char>. Greek <char style="it">winter-torrent</char>.</char></note>brook <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of the Cedars</char></char></note>Kidron, where was a garden, into which he entered, himself and his disciples. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Now Judas also, who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">delivered him up</char></char></note>betrayed him, knew the place: for Jesus oft-times resorted thither with his disciples. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Judas then, having received the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cohort</char></char></note>band <char style="add">of soldiers</char>, and officers from the chief priests and the Pharisees, cometh thither with lanterns and torches and weapons. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Jesus therefore, knowing all the things that were coming upon him, went forth, and saith unto them, Whom seek ye? <verse number="5" style="v"/>They answered him, Jesus of Nazareth. Jesus saith unto them, I am <char style="add">he</char>. And Judas also, who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">delivered him up</char></char></note>betrayed him, was standing with them. <verse number="6" style="v"/>When therefore he said unto them, I am <char style="add">he</char>, they went backward, and fell to the ground. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Again therefore he asked them, Whom seek ye? And they said, Jesus of Nazareth. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Jesus answered, I told you that I am <char style="add">he</char>; if therefore ye seek me, let these go their way: <verse number="9" style="v"/>that the word might be fulfilled which he spake, Of those whom thou hast given me I lost not one. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Simon Peter therefore having a sword drew it, and struck the high priest&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant, and cut off his right ear. Now the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant&#8217;s name was Malchus. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said unto Peter, Put up the sword into the sheath: the cup which the Father hath given me, shall I not drink it?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>So the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cohort</char></char></note>band and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain, and the officers of the Jews, seized Jesus and bound him, <verse number="13" style="v"/>and led him to Annas first; for he was father in law to Caiaphas, who was high priest that year. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Now Caiaphas was he that gave counsel to the Jews, that it was expedient that one man should die for the people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And Simon Peter followed Jesus, and <char style="add">so did</char> another disciple. Now that disciple was known unto the high priest, and entered in with Jesus into the court of the high priest; <verse number="16" style="v"/>but Peter was standing at the door without. So the other disciple, who was known unto the high priest, went out and spake unto her that kept the door, and brought in Peter. <verse number="17" style="v"/>The maid therefore that kept the door saith unto Peter, Art thou also <char style="add">one</char> of this man&#8217;s disciples? He saith, I am not. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Now the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants and the officers were standing <char style="add">there</char>, having made <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">a fire of charcoal</char>.</char></note>a fire of coals; for it was cold; and they were warming themselves: and Peter also was with them, standing and warming himself.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>The high priest therefore asked Jesus of his disciples, and of his teaching. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Jesus answered him, I have spoken openly to the world; I ever taught in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">synagogue</char>.</char></note>synagogues, and in the temple, where all the Jews come together; and in secret spake I nothing. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Why askest thou me? ask them that have heard <char style="add">me</char>, what I spake unto them: behold, these know the things which I said. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And when he had said this, one of the officers standing by struck Jesus <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with a rod</char></char></note>with his hand, saying, Answerest thou the high priest so? <verse number="23" style="v"/>Jesus answered him, If I have spoken evil, bear witness of the evil: but if well, why smitest thou me? <verse number="24" style="v"/>Annas therefore sent him bound unto Caiaphas the high priest.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>Now Simon Peter was standing and warming himself. They said therefore unto him, Art thou also <char style="add">one</char> of his disciples? He denied, and said, I am not. <verse number="26" style="v"/>One of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants of the high priest, being a kinsman of him whose ear Peter cut off, saith, Did not I see thee in the garden with him? <verse number="27" style="v"/>Peter therefore denied again: and straightway the cock crew.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>They lead Jesus therefore from Caiaphas into the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">palace</char></char></note>Praetorium: and it was early; and they themselves entered not into the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">palace</char></char></note>Praetorium, that they might not be defiled, but might eat the passover. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Pilate therefore went out unto them, and saith, What accusation bring ye against this man? <verse number="30" style="v"/>They answered and said unto him, If this man were not an evil-doer, we should not have delivered him up unto thee. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Pilate therefore said unto them, Take him yourselves, and judge him according to your law. The Jews said unto him, It is not lawful for us to put any man to death: <verse number="32" style="v"/>that the word of Jesus might be fulfilled, which he spake, signifying by what manner of death he should die.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v"/>Pilate therefore entered again into the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">palace</char></char></note>Praetorium, and called Jesus, and said unto him, Art thou the King of the Jews? <verse number="34" style="v"/>Jesus answered, Sayest thou this of thyself, or did others tell it thee concerning me? <verse number="35" style="v"/>Pilate answered, Am I a Jew? Thine own nation and the chief priests delivered thee unto me: what hast thou done? <verse number="36" style="v"/>Jesus answered, My kingdom is not of this world: if my kingdom were of this world, then would my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">officers</char>: as in verses <ref loc="JHN 18:3">3</ref>, <ref loc="JHN 18:12">12</ref>, <ref loc="JHN 18:18">18</ref>, <ref loc="JHN 18:22">22</ref>.</char></note>servants fight, that I should not be delivered to the Jews: but now is my kingdom not from hence. <verse number="37" style="v"/>Pilate therefore said unto him, Art thou a king then? Jesus answered, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Thou sayest</char> it, <char style="it">because I am a king</char>.</char></note>Thou sayest that I am a king. To this end have I been born, and to this end am I come into the world, that I should bear witness unto the truth. Every one that is of the truth heareth my voice. <verse number="38" style="v"/>Pilate saith unto him, What is truth?</para>
	<para style="p">And when he had said this, he went out again unto the Jews, and saith unto them, I find no crime in him. <verse number="39" style="v"/>But ye have a custom, that I should release unto you one at the passover: will ye therefore that I release unto you the King of the Jews? <verse number="40" style="v"/>They cried out therefore again, saying, Not this man, but Barabbas. Now Barabbas was a robber.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Then Pilate therefore took Jesus, and scourged him. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the soldiers platted a crown of thorns, and put it on his head, and arrayed him in a purple garment; <verse number="3" style="v"/>and they came unto him, and said, Hail, King of the Jews! and they struck him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with rods</char></char></note>with their hands. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Pilate went out again, and saith unto them, Behold, I bring him out to you, that ye may know that I find no crime in him. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Jesus therefore came out, wearing the crown of thorns and the purple garment. And <char style="add">Pilate</char> saith unto them, Behold, the man! <verse number="6" style="v"/>When therefore the chief priests and the officers saw him, they cried out, saying, Crucify <char style="add">him</char>, crucify <char style="add">him</char>! Pilate saith unto them, Take him yourselves, and crucify him: for I find no crime in him. <verse number="7" style="v"/>The Jews answered him, We have a law, and by that law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God. <verse number="8" style="v"/>When Pilate therefore heard this saying, he was the more afraid; <verse number="9" style="v"/>and he entered into the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">palace</char></char></note>Praetorium again, and saith unto Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus gave him no answer. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Pilate therefore saith unto him, Speakest thou not unto me? knowest thou not that I have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">authority</char></char></note>power to release thee, and have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">authority</char></char></note>power to crucify thee? <verse number="11" style="v"/>Jesus answered him, Thou wouldest have no <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">authority</char></char></note>power against me, except it were given thee from above: therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath greater sin. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Upon this Pilate sought to release him: but the Jews cried out, saying, If thou release this man, thou art not Caesar&#8217;s friend: every one that maketh himself a king <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">opposeth Caesar</char></char></note>speaketh against Caesar. <verse number="13" style="v"/>When Pilate therefore heard these words, he brought Jesus out, and sat down on the judgment-seat at a place called The Pavement, but in Hebrew, Gabbatha. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Now it was the Preparation of the passover: it was about the sixth hour. And he saith unto the Jews, Behold, your King! <verse number="15" style="v"/>They therefore cried out, Away with <char style="add">him</char>, away with <char style="add">him</char>, crucify him! Pilate saith unto them, Shall I crucify your King? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Caesar. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Then therefore he delivered him unto them to be crucified.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>They took Jesus therefore: and he went out, bearing the cross for himself, unto the place called The place of a skull, which is called in Hebrew Golgotha: <verse number="18" style="v"/>where they crucified him, and with him two others, on either side one, and Jesus in the midst. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And Pilate wrote a title also, and put it on the cross. And there was written, <char style="sc">Jesus of Nazareth, the King of the Jews</char>. <verse number="20" style="v"/>This title therefore read many of the Jews, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for the place of the city where Jesus was crucified was nigh at hand</char></char></note>for the place where Jesus was crucified was nigh to the city; and it was written in Hebrew, <char style="add">and</char> in Latin, <char style="add">and</char> in Greek. <verse number="21" style="v"/>The chief priests of the Jews therefore said to Pilate, Write not, The King of the Jews; but, that he said, I am King of the Jews. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Pilate answered, What I have written I have written.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>The soldiers therefore, when they had crucified Jesus, took his garments and made four parts, to every soldier a part; and also the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">tunic</char></char></note>coat: now the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">tunic</char></char></note>coat was without seam, woven from the top throughout. <verse number="24" style="v"/>They said therefore one to another, Let us not rend it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be: that the scripture might be fulfilled, which saith,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 22:18">Ps. 22:18</ref>.</char></note>They parted my garments among them,</para>
	<para style="q1">And upon my vesture did they cast lots.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="25" style="v"/>These things therefore the soldiers did. But there were standing by the cross of Jesus his mother, and his mother&#8217;s sister, Mary the <char style="add">wife</char> of Clopas, and Mary Magdalene. <verse number="26" style="v"/>When Jesus therefore saw his mother, and the disciple standing by whom he loved, he saith unto his mother, Woman, behold, thy son! <verse number="27" style="v"/>Then saith he to the disciple, Behold, thy mother! And from that hour the disciple took her unto his own <char style="add">home</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>After this Jesus, knowing that all things are now finished, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 69:21">Ps. 69:21</ref>.</char></note>that the scripture might be accomplished, saith, I thirst. <verse number="29" style="v"/>There was set there a vessel full of vinegar: so they put a sponge full of the vinegar upon hyssop, and brought it to his mouth. <verse number="30" style="v"/>When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up his spirit.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>The Jews therefore, because it was the Preparation, that the bodies should not remain on the cross upon the sabbath (for the day of that sabbath was a high <char style="add">day</char>), asked of Pilate that their legs might be broken, and <char style="add">that</char> they might be taken away. <verse number="32" style="v"/>The soldiers therefore came, and brake the legs of the first, and of the other that was crucified with him: <verse number="33" style="v"/>but when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already, they brake not his legs: <verse number="34" style="v"/>howbeit one of the soldiers with a spear pierced his side, and straightway there came out blood and water. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And he that hath seen hath borne witness, and his witness is true: and he knoweth that he saith true, that ye also may believe. <verse number="36" style="v"/>For these things came to pass, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="EXO 12:46">Ex. 12:46</ref>; <ref loc="NUM 9:12">Num. 9:12</ref>; <ref loc="PSA 34:20">Ps. 34:20</ref>.</char></note>that the scripture might be fulfilled, A bone of him shall not be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">crushed</char></char></note>broken. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And again another scripture saith, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ZEC 12:10">Zech. 12:10</ref>.</char></note>They shall look on him whom they pierced.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v"/>And after these things Joseph of Arimathaea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly for fear of the Jews, asked of Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus: and Pilate gave <char style="add">him</char> leave. He came therefore, and took away his body. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And there came also Nicodemus, he who at the first came to him by night, bringing a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">roll</char>.</char></note>mixture of myrrh and aloes, about a hundred pounds. <verse number="40" style="v"/>So they took the body of Jesus, and bound it in linen cloths with the spices, as the custom of the Jews is to bury. <verse number="41" style="v"/>Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden; and in the garden a new tomb wherein was never man yet laid. <verse number="42" style="v"/>There then because of the Jews&#8217; Preparation (for the tomb was nigh at hand) they laid Jesus.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now on the first <char style="add">day</char> of the week cometh Mary Magdalene early, while it was yet dark, unto the tomb, and seeth the stone taken away from the tomb. <verse number="2" style="v"/>She runneth therefore, and cometh to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple whom Jesus loved, and saith unto them, They have taken away the Lord out of the tomb, and we know not where they have laid him. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Peter therefore went forth, and the other disciple, and they went toward the tomb. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And they ran both together: and the other disciple outran Peter, and came first to the tomb; <verse number="5" style="v"/>and stooping and looking in, he seeth the linen cloths lying; yet entered he not in. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Simon Peter therefore also cometh, following him, and entered into the tomb; and he beholdeth the linen cloths lying, <verse number="7" style="v"/>and the napkin, that was upon his head, not lying with the linen cloths, but rolled up in a place by itself. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Then entered in therefore the other disciple also, who came first to the tomb, and he saw, and believed. <verse number="9" style="v"/>For as yet they knew not the scripture, that he must rise again from the dead. <verse number="10" style="v"/>So the disciples went away again unto their own home.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>But Mary was standing without at the tomb weeping: so, as she wept, she stooped and looked into the tomb; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and she beholdeth two angels in white sitting, one at the head, and one at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And they say unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? She saith unto them, Because they have taken away my Lord, and I know not where they have laid him. <verse number="14" style="v"/>When she had thus said, she turned herself back, and beholdeth Jesus standing, and knew not that it was Jesus. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? whom seekest thou? She, supposing him to be the gardener, saith unto him, Sir, if thou hast borne him hence, tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will take him away. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto her, Mary. She turneth herself, and saith unto him in Hebrew, Rabboni; which is to say, Teacher. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Jesus saith to her, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Take not hold on me</char></char></note>Touch me not; for I am not yet ascended unto the Father: but go unto my brethren, and say to them, I ascend unto my Father and your Father, and my God and your God. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Mary Magdalene cometh and telleth the disciples, I have seen the Lord; and <char style="add">that</char> he had said these things unto her.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>When therefore it was evening, on that day, the first <char style="add">day</char> of the week, and when the doors were shut where the disciples were, for fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in the midst, and saith unto them, Peace <char style="add">be</char> unto you. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And when he had said this, he showed unto them his hands and his side. The disciples therefore were glad, when they saw the Lord. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Jesus therefore said to them again, Peace <char style="add">be</char> unto you: as the Father hath sent me, even so send I you. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Spirit: <verse number="23" style="v"/>whose soever sins ye forgive, they are forgiven unto them; whose soever <char style="add">sins</char> ye retain, they are retained.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>But Thomas, one of the twelve, called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Twin</char>.</char></note>Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came. <verse number="25" style="v"/>The other disciples therefore said unto him, We have seen the Lord. But he said unto them, Except I shall see in his hands the print of the nails, and put my finger into the print of the nails, and put my hand into his side, I will not believe.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>And after eight days again his disciples were within, and Thomas with them. Jesus cometh, the doors being shut, and stood in the midst, and said, Peace <char style="add">be</char> unto you. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Then saith he to Thomas, Reach hither thy finger, and see my hands; and reach <char style="add">hither</char> thy hand, and put it into my side: and be not faithless, but believing. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Thomas answered and said unto him, My Lord and my God. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto him, Because thou hast seen me, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hast thou believed?</char></char></note>thou hast believed: blessed <char style="add">are</char> they that have not seen, and <char style="add">yet</char> have believed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>Many other signs therefore did Jesus in the presence of the disciples, which are not written in this book: <verse number="31" style="v"/>but these are written, that ye may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God; and that believing ye may have life in his name.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After these things Jesus manifested himself again to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias; and he manifested <char style="add">himself</char> on this wise. <verse number="2" style="v"/>There were together Simon Peter, and Thomas called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Twin</char>.</char></note>Didymus, and Nathanael of Cana in Galilee, and the <char style="add">sons</char> of Zebedee, and two other of his disciples. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Simon Peter saith unto them, I go a fishing. They say unto him, We also come with thee. They went forth, and entered into the boat; and that night they took nothing. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But when day was now breaking, Jesus stood on the beach: yet the disciples knew not that it was Jesus. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Jesus therefore saith unto them, Children, have ye aught to eat? They answered him, No. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he said unto them, Cast the net on the right side of the boat, and ye shall find. They cast therefore, and now they were not able to draw it for the multitude of fishes. <verse number="7" style="v"/>That disciple therefore whom Jesus loved saith unto Peter, It is the Lord. So when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he girt his coat about him (for he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">had on his undergarment only</char>. Compare <ref loc="JHN 13:4">13:4</ref>; <ref loc="ISA 20:2">Isa. 20:2</ref>; <ref loc="MIC 1:8">Mic. 1:8</ref>, <ref loc="MIC 1:11">11</ref>.</char></note>was naked), and cast himself into the sea. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But the other disciples came in the little boat (for they were not far from the land, but about two hundred cubits off), dragging the net <char style="add">full</char> of fishes. <verse number="9" style="v"/>So when they got out upon the land, they see <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">a fire of charcoal</char>.</char></note>a fire of coals there, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a fish</char></char></note>fish laid thereon, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a loaf</char></char></note>bread. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto them, Bring of the fish which ye have now taken. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Simon Peter therefore went <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">aboard</char></char></note>up, and drew the net to land, full of great fishes, a hundred and fifty and three: and for all there were so many, the net was not rent. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto them, Come <char style="add">and</char> break your fast. And none of the disciples durst inquire of him, Who art thou? knowing that it was the Lord. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Jesus cometh, and taketh the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">loaf</char></char></note>bread, and giveth them, and the fish likewise. <verse number="14" style="v"/>This is now the third time that Jesus was manifested to the disciples, after that he was risen from the dead.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>So when they had broken their fast, Jesus saith to Simon Peter, Simon, <char style="add">son</char> of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Joanes</char>. See <ref loc="JHN 1:42">1:42</ref> margin.</char></note>John, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">Love</char> in these places represents two different Greek words</char></note>lovest thou me more than these? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">Love</char> in these places represents two different Greek words</char></note>love thee. He saith unto him, Feed my lambs. <verse number="16" style="v"/>He saith to him again a second time, Simon, <char style="add">son</char> of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Joanes</char>. See <ref loc="JHN 1:42">1:42</ref> margin.</char></note>John, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">Love</char> in these places represents two different Greek words</char></note>lovest thou me? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">Love</char> in these places represents two different Greek words</char></note>love thee. He saith unto him, Tend my sheep. <verse number="17" style="v"/>He saith unto him the third time, Simon, <char style="add">son</char> of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Joanes</char>. See <ref loc="JHN 1:42">1:42</ref> margin.</char></note>John, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">Love</char> in these places represents two different Greek words</char></note>lovest thou me? Peter was grieved because he said unto him the third time, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">Love</char> in these places represents two different Greek words</char></note>Lovest thou me? And he said unto him, Lord, thou knowest all things; thou <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">perceivest</char></char></note>knowest that I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><char style="it">Love</char> in these places represents two different Greek words</char></note>love thee. Jesus saith unto him, Feed my sheep. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Verily, verily, I say unto thee, When thou wast young, thou girdedst thyself, and walkedst whither thou wouldest: but when thou shalt be old, thou shalt stretch forth thy hands, and another shall gird thee, and carry thee whither thou wouldest not. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Now this he spake, signifying by what manner of death he should glorify God. And when he had spoken this, he saith unto him, Follow me. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Peter, turning about, seeth the disciple whom Jesus loved following; who also leaned back on his breast at the supper, and said, Lord, who is he that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">delivereth thee up</char></char></note>betrayeth thee? <verse number="21" style="v"/>Peter therefore seeing him saith to Jesus, Lord, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">and this man, what?</char></char></note>and what shall this man do? <verse number="22" style="v"/>Jesus saith unto him, If I will that he tarry till I come, what <char style="add">is that</char> to thee? follow thou me. <verse number="23" style="v"/>This saying therefore went forth among the brethren, that that disciple should not die: yet Jesus said not unto him, that he should not die; but, If I will that he tarry till I come, what <char style="add">is that</char> to thee?</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>This is the disciple that beareth witness of these things, and wrote these things: and we know that his witness is true.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And there are also many other things which Jesus did, the which if they should be written every one, I suppose that even the world itself would not contain the books that should be written.</para>
</usx>