<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="ACT" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>The <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">first</char>.</char></note>former treatise I made, O Theophilus, concerning all that Jesus began both to do and to teach, <verse number="2" style="v"/>until the day in which he was received up, after that he had given commandment through the Holy Spirit unto the apostles whom he had chosen: <verse number="3" style="v"/>to whom he also <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">presented</char>.</char></note>showed himself alive after his passion by many proofs, appearing unto them by the space of forty days, and speaking the things concerning the kingdom of God: <verse number="4" style="v"/>and, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">eating with them</char></char></note>being assembled together with them, he charged them not to depart from Jerusalem, but to wait for the promise of the Father, which, <char style="add">said he</char>, ye heard from me: <verse number="5" style="v"/>for John indeed baptized with water; but ye shall be baptized <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with</char></char></note>in the Holy Spirit not many days hence.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>They therefore, when they were come together, asked him, saying, Lord, dost thou at this time restore the kingdom to Israel? <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he said unto them, It is not for you to know times or seasons, which the Father hath <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">appointed by</char></char></note>set within his own authority. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But ye shall receive power, when the Holy Spirit is come upon you: and ye shall be my witnesses both in Jerusalem, and in all Judaea and Samaria, and unto the uttermost part of the earth. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And when he had said these things, as they were looking, he was taken up; and a cloud received him out of their sight. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And while they were looking stedfastly into heaven as he went, behold two men stood by them in white apparel; <verse number="11" style="v"/>who also said, Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye looking into heaven? this Jesus, who was received up from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye beheld him going into heaven.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Then returned they unto Jerusalem from the mount called Olivet, which is nigh unto Jerusalem, a sabbath day&#8217;s journey off. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And when they were come in, they went up into the upper chamber, where they were abiding; both Peter and John and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Jacob</char></char></note>James and Andrew, Philip and Thomas, Bartholomew and Matthew, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Jacob</char></char></note>James <char style="add">the son</char> of Alphaeus, and Simon the Zealot, and Judas <char style="add">the</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, brother. See <ref loc="JUD 1:1">Jude 1</ref>.</char></note><char style="add">son</char> of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Jacob</char></char></note>James. <verse number="14" style="v"/>These all with one accord continued stedfastly in prayer, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with</char> certain <char style="it">women</char></char></note>with the women, and Mary the mother of Jesus, and with his brethren.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And in these days Peter stood up in the midst of the brethren, and said (and there was a multitude of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">names</char>. See <ref loc="REV 3:4">Rev. 3:4</ref>.</char></note>persons <char style="add">gathered</char> together, about a hundred and twenty), <verse number="16" style="v"/>Brethren, it was needful that the scripture should be fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit spake before by the mouth of David concerning Judas, who was guide to them that took Jesus. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For he was numbered among us, and received his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lot</char></char></note>portion in this ministry. <verse number="18" style="v"/>(Now this man obtained a field with the reward of his iniquity; and falling headlong, he burst asunder in the midst, and all his bowels gushed out. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And it became known to all the dwellers at Jerusalem; insomuch that in their language that field was called Akeldama, that is, The field of blood.) <verse number="20" style="v"/>For it is written in the book of Psalms,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 69:25">Ps. 69:25</ref>.</char></note>Let his habitation be made desolate,</para>
	<para style="q1">And let no man dwell therein:</para>
	<para style="p">and,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 109:8">Ps. 109:8</ref>.</char></note>His <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">overseership</char>.</char></note>office let another take.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="21" style="v"/>Of the men therefore that have companied with us all the time that the Lord Jesus went in and went out <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">over</char></char></note>among us, <verse number="22" style="v"/>beginning from the baptism of John, unto the day that he was received up from us, of these must one become a witness with us of his resurrection. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And they put forward two, Joseph called Barsabbas, who was surnamed Justus, and Matthias. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And they prayed, and said, Thou, Lord, who knowest the hearts of all men, show of these two the one whom thou hast chosen, <verse number="25" style="v"/>to take the place in this ministry and apostleship from which Judas fell away, that he might go to his own place. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And they gave lots <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">unto</char></char></note>for them; and the lot fell upon Matthias; and he was numbered with the eleven apostles.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And when the day of Pentecost <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">was being fulfilled</char>.</char></note>was now come, they were all together in one place. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And suddenly there came from heaven a sound as of the rushing of a mighty wind, and it filled all the house where they were sitting. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And there appeared unto them tongues <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">parting among them</char>. Or, <char style="it">distributing themselves</char></char></note>parting asunder, like as of fire; and it sat upon each one of them. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and began to speak with other tongues, as the Spirit gave them utterance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>Now there were dwelling at Jerusalem Jews, devout men, from every nation under heaven. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And when this sound was heard, the multitude came together, and were confounded, because that every man heard them speaking in his own language. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And they were all amazed and marvelled, saying, Behold, are not all these that speak Galilaeans? <verse number="8" style="v"/>And how hear we, every man in our own language wherein we were born? <verse number="9" style="v"/>Parthians and Medes and Elamites, and the dwellers in Mesopotamia, in Judaea and Cappadocia, in Pontus and Asia, <verse number="10" style="v"/>in Phrygia and Pamphylia, in Egypt and the parts of Libya about Cyrene, and sojourners from Rome, both Jews and proselytes, <verse number="11" style="v"/>Cretans and Arabians, we hear them speaking in our tongues the mighty works of God. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And they were all amazed, and were perplexed, saying one to another, What meaneth this? <verse number="13" style="v"/>But others mocking said, They are filled with new wine.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>But Peter, standing up with the eleven, lifted up his voice, and spake forth unto them, <char style="add">saying</char>, Ye men of Judaea, and all ye that dwell at Jerusalem, be this known unto you, and give ear unto my words. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For these are not drunken, as ye suppose; seeing it is <char style="add">but</char> the third hour of the day; <verse number="16" style="v"/>but this is that which hath been spoken through the prophet Joel:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="17" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="JOL 2:28-2:32">Joel 2:28ff</ref>.</char></note>And it shall be in the last days, saith God,</para>
	<para style="q1">I will pour forth of my Spirit upon all flesh:</para>
	<para style="q1">And your sons and your daughters shall prophesy,</para>
	<para style="q1">And your young men shall see visions,</para>
	<para style="q1">And your old men shall dream dreams:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="18" style="v"/>Yea and on my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondmen</char>.</char></note>servants and on my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondmaidens</char>.</char></note>handmaidens in those days</para>
	<para style="q1">Will I pour forth of my Spirit; and they shall prophesy.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="19" style="v"/>And I will show wonders in the heaven above,</para>
	<para style="q1">And signs on the earth beneath;</para>
	<para style="q1">Blood, and fire, and vapor of smoke:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="20" style="v"/>The sun shall be turned into darkness,</para>
	<para style="q1">And the moon into blood,</para>
	<para style="q1">Before the day of the Lord come,</para>
	<para style="q1">That great and notable <char style="add">day</char>:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="21" style="v"/>And it shall be, that whosoever shall call on the name of the Lord shall be saved.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="22" style="v"/>Ye men of Israel, hear these words: Jesus of Nazareth, a man approved of God unto you by <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">powers</char>.</char></note>mighty works and wonders and signs which God did by him in the midst of you, even as ye yourselves know; <verse number="23" style="v"/>him, being delivered up by the determinate counsel and foreknowledge of God, ye by the hand of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">men without the law</char>. See <ref loc="ROM 2:12">Rom. 2:12</ref>.</char></note>lawless men did crucify and slay: <verse number="24" style="v"/>whom God raised up, having loosed the pangs of death: because it was not possible that he should be holden of it. <verse number="25" style="v"/>For David saith concerning him,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 16:8-16:11">Ps. 16:8ff</ref>.</char></note>I beheld the Lord always before my face;</para>
	<para style="q1">For he is on my right hand, that I should not be moved:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="26" style="v"/>Therefore my heart was glad, and my tongue rejoiced;</para>
	<para style="q1">Moreover my flesh also shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">tabernacle</char></char></note>dwell in hope:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="27" style="v"/>Because thou wilt not leave my soul unto Hades,</para>
	<para style="q1">Neither wilt thou give thy Holy One to see corruption.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="28" style="v"/>Thou madest known unto me the ways of life;</para>
	<para style="q1">Thou shalt make me full of gladness <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in thy presence</char></char></note>with thy countenance.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="29" style="v"/>Brethren, I may say unto you freely of the patriarch David, that he both died and was buried, and his tomb is with us unto this day. <verse number="30" style="v"/>Being therefore a prophet, and knowing that God had sworn with an oath to him, that of the fruit of his loins <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, one <char style="it">should sit</char></char></note>he would set <char style="add">one</char> upon his throne; <verse number="31" style="v"/>he foreseeing <char style="add">this</char> spake of the resurrection of the Christ, that neither was he left unto Hades, nor did his flesh see corruption. <verse number="32" style="v"/>This Jesus did God raise up, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of whom</char></char></note>whereof we all are witnesses. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Being therefore <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">at</char></char></note>by the right hand of God exalted, and having received of the Father the promise of the Holy Spirit, he hath poured forth this, which ye see and hear. <verse number="34" style="v"/>For David ascended not into the heavens: but he saith himself,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 110:1">Ps. 110:1</ref>.</char></note>The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="35" style="v"/>Till I make thine enemies the footstool of thy feet.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="36" style="v"/>Let <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">every house</char></char></note>all the house of Israel therefore know assuredly, that God hath made him both Lord and Christ, this Jesus whom ye crucified.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v"/>Now when they heard <char style="add">this</char>, they were pricked in their heart, and said unto Peter and the rest of the apostles, Brethren, what shall we do? <verse number="38" style="v"/>And Peter <char style="add">said</char> unto them, Repent ye, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ unto the remission of your sins; and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Spirit. <verse number="39" style="v"/>For to you is the promise, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, <char style="add">even</char> as many as the Lord our God shall call unto him. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And with many other words he testified, and exhorted them, saying, Save yourselves from this crooked generation. <verse number="41" style="v"/>They then <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">having received</char></char></note>that received his word were baptized: and there were added <char style="add">unto them</char> in that day about three thousand souls. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And they continued stedfastly in the apostles&#8217; teaching and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in fellowship</char></char></note>fellowship, in the breaking of bread and the prayers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v"/>And fear came upon every soul: and many wonders and signs were done through the apostles<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities add <char style="it">in Jerusalem; and great fear was upon all</char></char></note>. <verse number="44" style="v"/>And all that believed were together, and had all things common; <verse number="45" style="v"/>and they sold their possessions and goods, and parted them to all, according as any man had need. <verse number="46" style="v"/>And day by day, continuing stedfastly with one accord in the temple, and breaking bread at home, they took their food with gladness and singleness of heart, <verse number="47" style="v"/>praising God, and having favor with all the people. And the Lord added <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">together</char>.</char></note>to them day by day those that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">were being saved</char></char></note>were saved.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now Peter and John were going up into the temple at the hour of prayer, <char style="add">being</char> the ninth <char style="add">hour</char>. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And a certain man that was lame from his mother&#8217;s womb was carried, whom they laid daily at the door of the temple which is called Beautiful, to ask alms of them that entered into the temple; <verse number="3" style="v"/>who seeing Peter and John about to go into the temple, asked to receive an alms. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Peter, fastening his eyes upon him, with John, said, Look on us. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And he gave heed unto them, expecting to receive something from them. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But Peter said, Silver and gold have I none; but what I have, that give I thee. In the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, walk. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he took him by the right hand, and raised him up: and immediately his feet and his ankle-bones received strength. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And leaping up, he stood, and began to walk; and he entered with them into the temple, walking, and leaping, and praising God. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And all the people saw him walking and praising God: <verse number="10" style="v"/>and they took knowledge of him, that it was he that sat for alms at the Beautiful Gate of the temple; and they were filled with wonder and amazement at that which had happened unto him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And as he held Peter and John, all the people ran together unto them in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">portico</char></char></note>porch that is called Solomon&#8217;s, greatly wondering. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And when Peter saw it, he answered unto the people, Ye men of Israel, why marvel ye at this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">thing</char></char></note>man? or why fasten ye your eyes on us, as though by our own power or godliness we had made him to walk? <verse number="13" style="v"/>The God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob, the God of our fathers, hath glorified his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Child</char>. See <ref loc="MAT 12:18">Mt. 12:18</ref>; <ref loc="ISA 42:1">Isa. 42:1</ref>; <ref loc="ISA 52:13">52:13</ref>; <ref loc="ISA 53:11">53:11</ref>.</char></note>Servant Jesus; whom ye delivered up, and denied before the face of Pilate, when he had determined to release him. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But ye denied the Holy and Righteous One, and asked for a murderer to be granted unto you, <verse number="15" style="v"/>and killed the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Author</char></char></note>Prince of life; whom God raised from the dead; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of whom</char></char></note>whereof we are witnesses. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">on the ground of</char></char></note>by faith in his name hath his name made this man strong, whom ye behold and know: yea, the faith which is through him hath given him this perfect soundness in the presence of you all. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And now, brethren, I know that in ignorance ye did it, as did also your rulers. <verse number="18" style="v"/>But the things which God foreshowed by the mouth of all the prophets, that his Christ should suffer, he thus fulfilled. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Repent ye therefore, and turn again, that your sins may be blotted out, that so there may come seasons of refreshing from the presence of the Lord; <verse number="20" style="v"/>and that he may send the Christ who hath been appointed for you, <char style="add">even</char> Jesus: <verse number="21" style="v"/>whom the heaven must receive until the times of restoration of all things, whereof God spake by the mouth of his holy prophets that have been from of old. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Moses indeed said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 18:15">Dt. 18:15</ref>.</char></note>A prophet shall the Lord God raise up unto you from among your brethren, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">as</char> he raised up <char style="it">me</char></char></note>like unto me; to him shall ye hearken in all things whatsoever he shall speak unto you. <verse number="23" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 18:19">Dt. 18:19</ref>.</char></note>And it shall be, that every soul that shall not hearken to that prophet, shall be utterly destroyed from among the people. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Yea and all the prophets from Samuel and them that followed after, as many as have spoken, they also told of these days. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Ye are the sons of the prophets, and of the covenant which God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">covenanted</char>.</char></note>made with your fathers, saying unto Abraham, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 12:3">Gen. 12:3</ref>; <ref loc="GEN 22:18">22:18</ref>; <ref loc="GEN 26:4">26:4</ref>; <ref loc="GEN 28:14">28:14</ref>.</char></note>And in thy seed shall all the families of the earth be blessed. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Unto you first God, having raised up his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Child</char>. See <ref loc="MAT 12:18">Mt. 12:18</ref>; <ref loc="ISA 42:1">Isa. 42:1</ref>; <ref loc="ISA 52:13">52:13</ref>; <ref loc="ISA 53:11">53:11</ref>.</char></note>Servant, sent him to bless you, in turning away every one of you from your iniquities.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And as they spake unto the people, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">the chief priests</char>.</char></note>the priests and the captain of the temple and the Sadducees came upon them, <verse number="2" style="v"/>being sore troubled because they taught the people, and proclaimed in Jesus the resurrection from the dead. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And they laid hands on them, and put them in ward unto the morrow: for it was now eventide. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But many of them that heard the word believed; and the number of the men came to be about five thousand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>And it came to pass on the morrow, that their rulers and elders and scribes were gathered together in Jerusalem; <verse number="6" style="v"/>and Annas the high priest <char style="add">was there</char>, and Caiaphas, and John, and Alexander, and as many as were of the kindred of the high priest. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And when they had set them in the midst, they inquired, By what power, or in what name, have ye done this? <verse number="8" style="v"/>Then Peter, filled with the Holy Spirit, said unto them, Ye rulers of the people, and elders, <verse number="9" style="v"/>if we this day are examined concerning a good deed done to an impotent man, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in whom</char></char></note>by what means this man is made whole; <verse number="10" style="v"/>be it known unto you all, and to all the people of Israel, that in the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, whom ye crucified, whom God raised from the dead, <char style="add">even</char> in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">this</char> name</char></note>him doth this man stand here before you whole. <verse number="11" style="v"/>He is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 118:22">Ps. 118:22</ref>.</char></note>the stone which was set at nought of you the builders, which was made the head of the corner. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And in none other is there salvation: for neither is there any other name under heaven, that is given among men, wherein we must be saved.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>Now when they beheld the boldness of Peter and John, and had perceived that they were unlearned and ignorant men, they marvelled; and they took knowledge of them, that they had been with Jesus. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And seeing the man that was healed standing with them, they could say nothing against it. <verse number="15" style="v"/>But when they had commanded them to go aside out of the council, they conferred among themselves, <verse number="16" style="v"/>saying, What shall we do to these men? for that indeed a notable <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sign</char>.</char></note>miracle hath been wrought through them, is manifest to all that dwell in Jerusalem; and we cannot deny it. <verse number="17" style="v"/>But that it spread no further among the people, let us threaten them, that they speak henceforth to no man in this name. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And they called them, and charged them not to speak at all nor teach in the name of Jesus. <verse number="19" style="v"/>But Peter and John answered and said unto them, Whether it is right in the sight of God to hearken unto you rather than unto God, judge ye: <verse number="20" style="v"/>for we cannot but speak the things which we saw and heard. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And they, when they had further threatened them, let them go, finding nothing how they might punish them, because of the people; for all men glorified God for that which was done. <verse number="22" style="v"/>For the man was more than forty years old, on whom this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sign</char>.</char></note>miracle of healing was wrought.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>And being let go, they came to their own company, and reported all that the chief priests and the elders had said unto them. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And they, when they heard it, lifted up their voice to God with one accord, and said, O <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Master</char>.</char></note>Lord, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">thou</char> art <char style="it">he that did make</char></char></note>thou that didst make the heaven and the earth and the sea, and all that in them is: <verse number="25" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The Greek text in this clause is somewhat uncertain.</char></note>who by the Holy Spirit, <char style="add">by</char> the mouth of our father David thy servant, didst say,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 2:1">Ps. 2:1</ref>, <ref loc="PSA 2:2">2</ref>.</char></note>Why did the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles rage,</para>
	<para style="q1">And the peoples <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">meditate</char></char></note>imagine vain things?</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="26" style="v"/>The kings of the earth set themselves in array,</para>
	<para style="q1">And the rulers were gathered together,</para>
	<para style="q1">Against the Lord, and against his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Christ</char>.</char></note>Anointed:</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="27" style="v"/>for of a truth in this city against thy holy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Child</char>. See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 3:13">3:13</ref>.</char></note>Servant Jesus, whom thou didst anoint, both Herod and Pontius Pilate, with the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles and the peoples of Israel, were gathered together, <verse number="28" style="v"/>to do whatsoever thy hand and thy council foreordained to come to pass. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And now, Lord, look upon their threatenings: and grant unto thy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants to speak thy word with all boldness, <verse number="30" style="v"/>while thou stretchest forth thy hand to heal; and that signs and wonders may be done through the name of thy holy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Child</char>. See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 3:13">3:13</ref>.</char></note>Servant Jesus. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And when they had prayed, the place was shaken wherein they were gathered together; and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and they spake the word of God with boldness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v"/>And the multitude of them that believed were of one heart and soul: and not one <char style="add">of them</char> said that aught of the things which he possessed was his own; but they had all things common. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And with great power gave the apostles their witness of the resurrection of the Lord Jesus: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities add <char style="it">Christ</char>.</char></note>and great grace was upon them all. <verse number="34" style="v"/>For neither was there among them any that lacked: for as many as were possessors of lands or houses sold them, and brought the prices of the things that were sold, <verse number="35" style="v"/>and laid them at the apostles&#8217; feet: and distribution was made unto each, according as any one had need.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v"/>And Joseph, who by the apostles was surnamed Barnabas (which is, being interpreted, Son of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">consolation</char>. See <ref loc="LUK 2:25">Lk. 2:25</ref>; <ref loc="ACT 9:31">9:31</ref>; <ref loc="ACT 15:31">15:31</ref>; <ref loc="2CO 1:3-1:7">2 Cor. 1:3&#8211;7</ref> in the Greek.</char></note>exhortation), a Levite, a man of Cyprus by race, <verse number="37" style="v"/>having a field, sold it, and brought the money and laid it at the apostles&#8217; feet.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>But a certain man named Ananias, with Sapphira his wife, sold a possession, <verse number="2" style="v"/>and kept back <char style="add">part</char> of the price, his wife also being privy to it, and brought a certain part, and laid it at the apostles&#8217; feet. <verse number="3" style="v"/>But Peter said, Ananias, why hath Satan filled thy heart to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">deceive</char></char></note>lie to the Holy Spirit, and to keep back <char style="add">part</char> of the price of the land? <verse number="4" style="v"/>While it remained, did it not remain thine own? and after it was sold, was it not in thy power? How is it that thou hast conceived this thing in thy heart? thou hast not lied unto men, but unto God. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Ananias hearing these words fell down and gave up the ghost: and great fear came upon all that heard it. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">younger</char>.</char></note>young men arose and wrapped him round, and they carried him out and buried him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And it was about the space of three hours after, when his wife, not knowing what was done, came in. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Peter answered unto her, Tell me whether ye sold the land for so much. And she said, Yea, for so much. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But Peter <char style="add">said</char> unto her, How is it that ye have agreed together to try the Spirit of the Lord? behold, the feet of them that have buried thy husband are at the door, and they shall carry thee out. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And she fell down immediately at his feet, and gave up the ghost: and the young men came in and found her dead, and they carried her out and buried her by her husband. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And great fear came upon the whole church, and upon all that heard these things.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And by the hands of the apostles were many signs and wonders wrought among the people: and they were all with one accord in Solomon&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">portico</char></char></note>porch. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But of the rest durst no man join himself to them: howbeit the people magnified them; <verse number="14" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and there were the more added</char> to them, <char style="it">believing on the Lord</char></char></note>and believers were the more added to the Lord, multitudes both of men and women: <verse number="15" style="v"/>insomuch that they even carried out the sick into the streets, and laid them on beds and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pallets</char></char></note>couches, that, as Peter came by, at the least his shadow might overshadow some one of them. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And there also came together the multitude from the cities round about Jerusalem, bringing sick folk, and them that were vexed with unclean spirits: and they were healed every one.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>But the high priest rose up, and all they that were with him (which is the sect of the Sadducees), and they were filled with jealousy, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and laid hands on the apostles, and put them in public ward. <verse number="19" style="v"/>But an angel of the Lord by night opened the prison doors, and brought them out, and said, <verse number="20" style="v"/>Go ye, and stand and speak in the temple to the people all the words of this Life. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And when they heard <char style="add">this</char>, they entered into the temple about daybreak, and taught. But the high priest came, and they that were with him, and called the council together, and all the senate of the children of Israel, and sent to the prison-house to have them brought. <verse number="22" style="v"/>But the officers that came found them not in the prison; and they returned, and told, <verse number="23" style="v"/>saying, The prison-house we found shut in all safety, and the keepers standing at the doors: but when we had opened, we found no man within. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Now when the captain of the temple and the chief priests heard these words, they were much perplexed concerning them whereunto this would grow. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And there came one and told them, Behold, the men whom ye put in the prison are in the temple standing and teaching the people. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Then went the captain with the officers, and brought them, <char style="add">but</char> without violence; for they feared the people, lest they should be stoned. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And when they had brought them, they set them before the council. And the high priest asked them, <verse number="28" style="v"/>saying, We strictly charged you not to teach in this name: and behold, ye have filled Jerusalem with your teaching, and intend to bring this man&#8217;s blood upon us. <verse number="29" style="v"/>But Peter and the apostles answered and said, We must obey God rather than men. <verse number="30" style="v"/>The God of our fathers raised up Jesus, whom ye slew, hanging him on a tree. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Him did God exalt <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">at</char></char></note>with his right hand <char style="add">to be</char> a Prince and a Saviour, to give repentance to Israel, and remission of sins. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And we are witnesses <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities add <char style="it">in him</char>.</char></note>of these <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sayings</char>.</char></note>things; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">and God hath given the Holy Spirit to them that obey him</char>.</char></note>and <char style="add">so is</char> the Holy Spirit, whom God hath given to them that obey him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v"/>But they, when they heard this, were cut to the heart, and were minded to slay them. <verse number="34" style="v"/>But there stood up one in the council, a Pharisee, named Gamaliel, a doctor of the law, had in honor of all the people, and commanded to put the men forth a little while. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And he said unto them, Ye men of Israel, take heed to yourselves as touching these men, what ye are about to do. <verse number="36" style="v"/>For before these days rose up Theudas, giving himself out to be somebody; to whom a number of men, about four hundred, joined themselves: who was slain; and all, as many as obeyed him, were dispersed, and came to nought. <verse number="37" style="v"/>After this man rose up Judas of Galilee in the days of the enrolment, and drew away <char style="add">some of the</char> people after him: he also perished; and all, as many as obeyed him, were scattered abroad. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And now I say unto you, Refrain from these men, and let them alone: for if this counsel or this work be of men, it will be overthrown: <verse number="39" style="v"/>but if it is of God, ye will not be able to overthrow them; lest haply ye be found even to be fighting against God. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And to him they agreed: and when they had called the apostles unto them, they beat them and charged them not to speak in the name of Jesus, and let them go. <verse number="41" style="v"/>They therefore departed from the presence of the council, rejoicing that they were counted worthy to suffer dishonor for the Name. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And every day, in the temple and at home, they ceased not to teach and to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bring good tidings of</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 13:32">13:32</ref>; <ref loc="ACT 14:15">14:15</ref>.</char></note>preach Jesus <char style="add">as</char> the Christ.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now in these days, when the number of the disciples was multiplying, there arose a murmuring of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Hellenists</char>.</char></note>Grecian Jews against the Hebrews, because their widows were neglected in the daily ministration. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the twelve called the multitude of the disciples unto them, and said, It is not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">pleasing</char>.</char></note>fit that we should forsake the word of God, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">minister to tables</char></char></note>serve tables. <verse number="3" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">But, brethren, look ye out from among you</char>.</char></note>Look ye out therefore, brethren, from among you seven men of good report, full of the Spirit and of wisdom, whom we may appoint over this business. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But we will continue stedfastly in prayer, and in the ministry of the word. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the saying pleased the whole multitude: and they chose Stephen, a man full of faith and of the Holy Spirit, and Philip, and Prochorus, and Nicanor, and Timon, and Parmenas, and Nicolaus a proselyte of Antioch; <verse number="6" style="v"/>whom they set before the apostles: and when they had prayed, they laid their hands upon them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And the word of God increased; and the number of the disciples multiplied in Jerusalem exceedingly; and a great company of the priests were obedient to the faith.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And Stephen, full of grace and power, wrought great wonders and signs among the people. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But there arose certain of them that were of the synagogue called <char style="add">the synagogue</char> of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Freedmen</char></char></note>Libertines, and of the Cyrenians, and of the Alexandrians, and of them of Cilicia and Asia, disputing with Stephen. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And they were not able to withstand the wisdom and the Spirit by which he spake. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Then they suborned men, who said, We have heard him speak blasphemous words against Moses, and <char style="add">against</char> God. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And they stirred up the people, and the elders, and the scribes, and came upon him, and seized him, and brought him into the council, <verse number="13" style="v"/>and set up false witnesses, who said, This man ceaseth not to speak words against this holy place, and the law: <verse number="14" style="v"/>for we have heard him say, that this Jesus of Nazareth shall destroy this place, and shall change the customs which Moses delivered unto us. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And all that sat in the council, fastening their eyes on him, saw his face as it had been the face of an angel.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the high priest said, Are these things so? <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he said,</para>
	<para style="p">Brethren and fathers, hearken: The God of glory appeared unto our father Abraham, when he was in Mesopotamia, before he dwelt in Haran, <verse number="3" style="v"/>and said unto him, Get thee out of thy land, and from thy kindred, and come into the land which I shall show thee. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Then came he out of the land of the Chaldaeans, and dwelt in Haran: and from thence, when his father was dead, <char style="add">God</char> removed him into this land, wherein ye now dwell: <verse number="5" style="v"/>and he gave him none inheritance in it, no, not so much as to set his foot on: and he promised that he would give it to him in possession, and to his seed after him, when <char style="add">as yet</char> he had no child. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And God spake on this wise, that his seed should sojourn in a strange land, and that they should bring them into bondage, and treat them ill, four hundred years. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the nation to which they shall be in bondage will I judge, said God: and after that shall they come forth, and serve me in this place. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And he gave him the covenant of circumcision: and so <char style="add">Abraham</char> begat Isaac, and circumcised him the eighth day; and Isaac <char style="add">begat</char> Jacob, and Jacob the twelve patriarchs. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the patriarchs, moved with jealousy against Joseph, sold him into Egypt: and God was with him, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and delivered him out of all his afflictions, and gave him favor and wisdom before Pharaoh king of Egypt; and he made him governor over Egypt and all his house. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Now there came a famine over all Egypt and Canaan, and great affliction: and our fathers found no sustenance. <verse number="12" style="v"/>But when Jacob heard that there was grain in Egypt, he sent forth our fathers the first time. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And at the second time Joseph was made known to his brethren; and Joseph&#8217;s race became manifest unto Pharaoh. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And Joseph sent, and called to him Jacob his father, and all his kindred, threescore and fifteen souls. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And Jacob went down into Egypt; and he died, himself and our fathers; <verse number="16" style="v"/>and they were carried over unto Shechem, and laid in the tomb that Abraham bought for a price in silver of the sons of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Emmor</char>.</char></note>Hamor in Shechem. <verse number="17" style="v"/>But as the time of the promise drew nigh which God vouchsafed unto Abraham, the people grew and multiplied in Egypt, <verse number="18" style="v"/>till there arose another king over Egypt, who knew not Joseph. <verse number="19" style="v"/>The same dealt craftily with our race, and ill-treated our fathers, that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">he</char></char></note>they should cast out their babes to the end they might not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">be preserved alive</char>.</char></note>live. <verse number="20" style="v"/>At which season Moses was born, and was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">fair unto God</char>. Compare <ref loc="2CO 10:4">2 Cor. 10:4</ref>.</char></note>exceeding fair; and he was nourished three months in his father&#8217;s house: <verse number="21" style="v"/>and when he was cast out, Pharaoh&#8217;s daughter took him up, and nourished him for her own son. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians; and he was mighty in his words and works. <verse number="23" style="v"/>But when he was well-nigh forty years old, it came into his heart to visit his brethren the children of Israel. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And seeing one <char style="add">of them</char> suffer wrong, he defended him, and avenged him that was oppressed, smiting the Egyptian: <verse number="25" style="v"/>and he supposed that his brethren understood that God by his hand was giving them <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">salvation</char></char></note>deliverance; but they understood not. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And the day following he appeared unto them as they strove, and would have set them at one again, saying, Sirs, ye are brethren; why do ye wrong one to another? <verse number="27" style="v"/>But he that did his neighbor wrong thrust him away, saying, Who made thee a ruler and a judge over us? <verse number="28" style="v"/>Wouldest thou kill me, as thou killedst the Egyptian yesterday? <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Moses fled at this saying, and became a sojourner in the land of Midian, where he begat two sons. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And when forty years were fulfilled, an angel appeared to him in the wilderness of mount Sinai, in a flame of fire in a bush. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And when Moses saw it, he wondered at the sight: and as he drew near to behold, there came a voice of the Lord, <verse number="32" style="v"/>I am the God of thy fathers, the God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob. And Moses trembled, and durst not behold. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And the Lord said unto him, Loose the shoes from thy feet: for the place whereon thou standest is holy ground. <verse number="34" style="v"/>I have surely seen the affliction of my people that is in Egypt, and have heard their groaning, and I am come down to deliver them: and now come, I will send thee into Egypt. <verse number="35" style="v"/>This Moses whom they refused, saying, Who made thee a ruler and a judge? him hath God sent <char style="add">to be</char> both a ruler and a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">redeemer</char>.</char></note>deliverer with the hand of the angel that appeared to him in the bush. <verse number="36" style="v"/>This man led them forth, having wrought wonders and signs in Egypt, and in the Red sea, and in the wilderness forty years. <verse number="37" style="v"/>This is that Moses, who said unto the children of Israel, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 18:15">Dt. 18:15</ref>.</char></note>A prophet shall God raise up unto you from among your brethren, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">as</char> he raised up <char style="it">me</char></char></note>like unto me. <verse number="38" style="v"/>This is he that was in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">congregation</char></char></note>church in the wilderness with the angel that spake to him in the mount Sinai, and with our fathers: who received living oracles to give unto us: <verse number="39" style="v"/>to whom our fathers would not be obedient, but thrust him from them, and turned back in their hearts unto Egypt, <verse number="40" style="v"/>saying unto Aaron, Make us gods that shall go before us: for as for this Moses, who led us forth out of the land of Egypt, we know not what is become of him. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And they made a calf in those days, and brought a sacrifice unto the idol, and rejoiced in the works of their hands. <verse number="42" style="v"/>But God turned, and gave them up to serve the host of heaven; as it is written in the book of the prophets,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="AMO 5:25-5:27">Am. 5:25ff</ref>.</char></note>Did ye offer unto me slain beasts and sacrifices</para>
	<para style="q1">Forty years in the wilderness, O house of Israel?</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="43" style="v"/>And ye took up the tabernacle of Moloch,</para>
	<para style="q1">And the star of the god Rephan,</para>
	<para style="q1">The figures which ye made to worship them:</para>
	<para style="q1">And I will carry you away beyond Babylon.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="44" style="v"/>Our fathers had the tabernacle of the testimony in the wilderness, even as he appointed who spake unto Moses, that he should make it according to the figure that he had seen. <verse number="45" style="v"/>Which also our fathers, in their turn, brought in with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Jesus</char>. Compare <ref loc="HEB 4:8">Heb. 4:8</ref>.</char></note>Joshua when they entered on the possession of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gentiles</char>. Compare <ref loc="ACT 4:25">4:25</ref>.</char></note>nations, that God thrust out before the face of our fathers, unto the days of David; <verse number="46" style="v"/>who found favor in the sight of God, and asked to find a habitation for the God of Jacob. <verse number="47" style="v"/>But Solomon built him a house. <verse number="48" style="v"/>Howbeit the Most High dwelleth not in <char style="add">houses</char> made with hands; as saith the prophet,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="49" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 66">Isa. 66:1f</ref>.</char></note>The heaven is my throne,</para>
	<para style="q1">And the earth the footstool of my feet:</para>
	<para style="q1">What manner of house will ye build me? saith the Lord:</para>
	<para style="q1">Or what is the place of my rest?</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="50" style="v"/>Did not my hand make all these things?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v"/>Ye stiffnecked and uncircumcised in heart and ears, ye do always resist the Holy Spirit: as your fathers did, so do ye. <verse number="52" style="v"/>Which of the prophets did not your fathers persecute? and they killed them that showed before of the coming of the Righteous One; of whom ye have now become betrayers and murderers; <verse number="53" style="v"/>ye who received the law <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">as the ordinance of angels</char>. Greek <char style="it">unto ordinances of angels</char>.</char></note>as it was ordained by angels, and kept it not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v"/>Now when they heard these things, they were cut to the heart, and they gnashed on him with their teeth. <verse number="55" style="v"/>But he, being full of the Holy Spirit, looked up stedfastly into heaven, and saw the glory of God, and Jesus standing on the right hand of God, <verse number="56" style="v"/>and said, Behold, I see the heavens opened, and the Son of man standing on the right hand of God. <verse number="57" style="v"/>But they cried out with a loud voice, and stopped their ears, and rushed upon him with one accord; <verse number="58" style="v"/>and they cast him out of the city, and stoned him: and the witnesses laid down their garments at the feet of a young man named Saul. <verse number="59" style="v"/>And they stoned Stephen, calling upon <char style="add">the Lord</char>, and saying, Lord Jesus, receive my spirit. <verse number="60" style="v"/>And he kneeled down, and cried with a loud voice, Lord, lay not this sin to their charge. And when he had said this, he fell asleep.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c"/>
	<para style="nb"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Saul was consenting unto his death.</para>
	<para style="p">And there arose on that day a great persecution against the church which was in Jerusalem; and they were all scattered abroad throughout the regions of Judaea and Samaria, except the apostles. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And devout men buried Stephen, and made great lamentation over him. <verse number="3" style="v"/>But Saul laid waste the church, entering into every house, and dragging men and women committed them to prison.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>They therefore that were scattered abroad went about <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Compare marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preaching the word. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Philip went down to the city of Samaria, and proclaimed unto them the Christ. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And the multitudes gave heed with one accord unto the things that were spoken by Philip, when they heard, and saw the signs which he did. <verse number="7" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">For many of those that had unclean spirits that cried with a loud voice came forth</char></char></note>For <char style="add">from</char> many of those that had unclean spirits, they came out, crying with a loud voice: and many that were palsied, and that were lame, were healed. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And there was much joy in that city.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>But there was a certain man, Simon by name, who beforetime in the city used sorcery, and amazed the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nation</char>.</char></note>people of Samaria, giving out that himself was some great one: <verse number="10" style="v"/>to whom they all gave heed, from the least to the greatest, saying, This man is that power of God which is called Great. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And they gave heed to him, because that of long time he had amazed them with his sorceries. <verse number="12" style="v"/>But when they believed Philip preaching good tidings concerning the kingdom of God and the name of Jesus Christ, they were baptized, both men and women. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And Simon also himself believed: and being baptized, he continued with Philip; and beholding signs and great <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">powers</char>.</char></note>miracles wrought, he was amazed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>Now when the apostles that were at Jerusalem heard that Samaria had received the word of God, they sent unto them Peter and John: <verse number="15" style="v"/>who, when they were come down, prayed for them, that they might receive the Holy Spirit: <verse number="16" style="v"/>for as yet it was fallen upon none of them: only they had been baptized into the name of the Lord Jesus. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the Holy Spirit. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Now when Simon saw that through the laying on of the apostles&#8217; hands the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">Holy</char>.</char></note>Holy Spirit was given, he offered them money, <verse number="19" style="v"/>saying, Give me also this power, that on whomsoever I lay my hands, he may receive the Holy Spirit. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But Peter said unto him, Thy silver perish with thee, because thou hast thought to obtain the gift of God with money. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Thou hast neither part nor lot in this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">word</char>.</char></note>matter: for thy heart is not right before God. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Repent therefore of this thy wickedness, and pray the Lord, if perhaps the thought of thy heart shall be forgiven thee. <verse number="23" style="v"/>For I see that thou <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wilt become gall</char> (or <char style="it">a gall root</char>) <char style="it">of bitterness and a bond of iniquity</char>. Compare <ref loc="DEU 29:18">Dt. 29:18</ref>; <ref loc="HEB 12:15">Heb. 12:15</ref>.</char></note>art in the gall of bitterness and in the bond of iniquity. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Simon answered and said, Pray ye for me to the Lord, that none of the things which ye have spoken come upon me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>They therefore, when they had testified and spoken the word of the Lord, returned to Jerusalem, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">brought good tidings</char>. Compare <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preached the gospel to many villages of the Samaritans.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>But an angel of the Lord spake unto Philip, saying, Arise, and go <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">at noon</char>. Compare <ref loc="ACT 22:6">22:6</ref>.</char></note>toward the south unto the way that goeth down from Jerusalem unto Gaza: the same is desert. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And he arose and went: and behold, a man of Ethiopia, a eunuch of great authority under Candace, queen of the Ethiopians, who was over all her treasure, who had come to Jerusalem to worship; <verse number="28" style="v"/>and he was returning and sitting in his chariot, and was reading the prophet Isaiah. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And the Spirit said unto Philip, Go near, and join thyself to this chariot. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And Philip ran to him, and heard him reading Isaiah the prophet, and said, Understandest thou what thou readest? <verse number="31" style="v"/>And he said, How can I, except some one shall guide me? And he besought Philip to come up and sit with him. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Now the passage of the scripture which he was reading was this,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 53:7-53:12">Isa. 53:7f</ref>.</char></note>He was led as a sheep to the slaughter;</para>
	<para style="q1">And as a lamb before his shearer is dumb,</para>
	<para style="q1">So he openeth not his mouth:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="33" style="v"/>In his humiliation his judgment was taken away:</para>
	<para style="q1">His generation who shall declare?</para>
	<para style="q1">For his life is taken from the earth.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="34" style="v"/>And the eunuch answered Philip, and said, I pray thee, of whom speaketh the prophet this? of himself, or of some other? <verse number="35" style="v"/>And Philip opened his mouth, and beginning from this scripture, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preached unto him Jesus. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And as they went on the way, they came unto a certain water; and the eunuch saith, Behold, <char style="add">here is</char> water; what doth hinder me to be baptized?<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities insert, wholly or in part, <ref loc="ACT 8:37">verse 37</ref> <char style="it">And Philip said, If thou believest with all thy heart, thou mayest. And he answered and said, I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God</char>.</char></note> <verse number="38" style="v"/>And he commanded the chariot to stand still: and they both went down into the water, both Philip and the eunuch; and he baptized him. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And when they came up out of the water, the Spirit of the Lord caught away Philip; and the eunuch saw him no more, for he went on his way rejoicing. <verse number="40" style="v"/>But Philip was found at Azotus: and passing through he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preached the gospel to all the cities, till he came to Caesarea.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>But Saul, yet breathing threatening and slaughter against the disciples of the Lord, went unto the high priest, <verse number="2" style="v"/>and asked of him letters to Damascus unto the synagogues, that if he found any that were of the Way, whether men or women, he might bring them bound to Jerusalem. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And as he journeyed, it came to pass that he drew nigh unto Damascus: and suddenly there shone round about him a light out of heaven: <verse number="4" style="v"/>and he fell upon the earth, and heard a voice saying unto him, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? <verse number="5" style="v"/>And he said, Who art thou, Lord? And he <char style="add">said</char>, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest: <verse number="6" style="v"/>but rise, and enter into the city, and it shall be told thee what thou must do. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the men that journeyed with him stood speechless, hearing the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sound</char></char></note>voice, but beholding no man. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Saul arose from the earth; and when his eyes were opened, he saw nothing; and they led him by the hand, and brought him into Damascus. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And he was three days without sight, and did neither eat nor drink.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>Now there was a certain disciple at Damascus, named Ananias; and the Lord said unto him in a vision, Ananias. And he said, Behold, I <char style="add">am here</char>, Lord. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the Lord <char style="add">said</char> unto him, Arise, and go to the street which is called Straight, and inquire in the house of Judas for one named Saul, a man of Tarsus: for behold, he prayeth; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and he hath seen a man named Ananias coming in, and laying his hands on him, that he might receive his sight. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But Ananias answered, Lord, I have heard from many of this man, how much evil he did to thy saints at Jerusalem: <verse number="14" style="v"/>and here he hath authority from the chief priests to bind all that call upon thy name. <verse number="15" style="v"/>But the Lord said unto him, Go thy way: for he is a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">vessel of election</char>.</char></note>chosen vessel unto me, to bear my name before the Gentiles and kings, and the children of Israel: <verse number="16" style="v"/>for I will show him how many things he must suffer for my name&#8217;s sake. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Ananias departed, and entered into the house; and laying his hands on him said, Brother Saul, the Lord, <char style="add">even</char> Jesus, who appeared unto thee in the way which thou camest, hath sent me, that thou mayest receive thy sight, and be filled with the Holy Spirit. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And straightway there fell from his eyes as it were scales, and he received his sight; and he arose and was baptized; <verse number="19" style="v"/>and he took food and was strengthened.</para>
	<para style="p">And he was certain days with the disciples that were at Damascus. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And straightway in the synagogues he proclaimed Jesus, that he is the Son of God. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And all that heard him were amazed, and said, Is not this he that in Jerusalem made havoc of them that called on this name? and he had come hither for this intent, that he might bring them bound before the chief priests. <verse number="22" style="v"/>But Saul increased the more in strength, and confounded the Jews that dwelt at Damascus, proving that this is the Christ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>And when many days were fulfilled, the Jews took counsel together to kill him: <verse number="24" style="v"/>but their plot became known to Saul. And they watched the gates also day and night that they might kill him: <verse number="25" style="v"/>but his disciples took him by night, and let him down through the wall, lowering him in a basket.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>And when he was come to Jerusalem, he assayed to join himself to the disciples: and they were all afraid of him, not believing that he was a disciple. <verse number="27" style="v"/>But Barnabas took him, and brought him to the apostles, and declared unto them how he had seen the Lord in the way, and that he had spoken to him, and how at Damascus he had preached boldly in the name of Jesus. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And he was with them going in and going out at Jerusalem, <verse number="29" style="v"/>preaching boldly in the name of the Lord: and he spake and disputed against the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Hellenists</char>.</char></note>Grecian Jews; but they were seeking to kill him. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And when the brethren knew it, they brought him down to Caesarea, and sent him forth to Tarsus.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>So the church throughout all Judaea and Galilee and Samaria had peace, being <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">builded up</char>.</char></note>edified; and, walking <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by</char></char></note>in the fear of the Lord and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by</char></char></note>in the comfort of the Holy Spirit, was multiplied. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as Peter went throughout all parts, he came down also to the saints that dwelt at Lydda. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And there he found a certain man named Aeneas, who had kept his bed eight years; for he was palsied. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And Peter said unto him, Aeneas, Jesus Christ healeth thee: arise, and make thy bed. And straightway he arose. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And all that dwelt at Lydda and in Sharon saw him, and they turned to the Lord.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v"/>Now there was at Joppa a certain disciple named Tabitha, which by interpretation is called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Gazelle</char>.</char></note>Dorcas: this woman was full of good works and almsdeeds which she did. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And it came to pass in those days, that she fell sick, and died: and when they had washed her, they laid her in an upper chamber. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And as Lydda was nigh unto Joppa, the disciples, hearing that Peter was there, sent two men unto him, entreating him, Delay not to come on unto us. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And Peter arose and went with them. And when he was come, they brought him into the upper chamber: and all the widows stood by him weeping, and showing the coats and garments which Dorcas made, while she was with them. <verse number="40" style="v"/>But Peter put them all forth, and kneeled down, and prayed; and turning to the body, he said, Tabitha, arise. And she opened her eyes; and when she saw Peter, she sat up. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And he gave her his hand, and raised her up; and calling the saints and widows, he presented her alive. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And it became known throughout all Joppa: and many believed on the Lord. <verse number="43" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that he abode many days in Joppa with one Simon a tanner.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now <char style="add">there was</char> a certain man in Caesarea, Cornelius by name, a centurion of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cohort</char></char></note>band called the Italian <char style="add">band</char>, <verse number="2" style="v"/>a devout man, and one that feared God with all his house, who gave much alms to the people, and prayed to God always. <verse number="3" style="v"/>He saw in a vision openly, as it were about the ninth hour of the day, an angel of God coming in unto him, and saying to him, Cornelius. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And he, fastening his eyes upon him, and being affrighted, said, What is it, Lord? And he said unto him, Thy prayers and thine alms are gone up for a memorial before God. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And now send men to Joppa, and fetch one Simon, who is surnamed Peter: <verse number="6" style="v"/>he lodgeth with one Simon a tanner, whose house is by the sea side. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And when the angel that spake unto him was departed, he called two of his household-servants, and a devout soldier of them that waited on him continually; <verse number="8" style="v"/>and having rehearsed all things unto them, he sent them to Joppa.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>Now on the morrow, as they were on their journey, and drew nigh unto the city, Peter went up upon the housetop to pray, about the sixth hour: <verse number="10" style="v"/>and he became hungry, and desired to eat: but while they made ready, he fell into a trance; <verse number="11" style="v"/>and he beholdeth the heaven opened, and a certain vessel descending, as it were a great sheet, let down by four corners upon the earth: <verse number="12" style="v"/>wherein were all manner of fourfooted beasts and creeping things of the earth and birds of the heaven. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And there came a voice to him, Rise, Peter; kill and eat. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But Peter said, Not so, Lord; for I have never eaten anything that is common and unclean. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And a voice <char style="add">came</char> unto him again the second time, What God hath cleansed, make not thou common. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And this was done thrice: and straightway the vessel was received up into heaven.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>Now while Peter was much perplexed in himself what the vision which he had seen might mean, behold, the men that were sent by Cornelius, having made inquiry for Simon&#8217;s house, stood before the gate, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and called and asked whether Simon, who was surnamed Peter, were lodging there. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And while Peter thought on the vision, the Spirit said unto him, Behold, three men seek thee. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But arise, and get thee down, and go with them, nothing doubting: for I have sent them. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And Peter went down to the men, and said, Behold, I am he whom ye seek: what is the cause wherefore ye are come? <verse number="22" style="v"/>And they said, Cornelius a centurion, a righteous man and one that feareth God, and well reported of by all the nation of the Jews, was warned <char style="add">of God</char> by a holy angel to send for thee into his house, and to hear words from thee. <verse number="23" style="v"/>So he called them in and lodged them.</para>
	<para style="p">And on the morrow he arose and went forth with them, and certain of the brethren from Joppa accompanied him. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And on the morrow <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">he</char>.</char></note>they entered into Caesarea. And Cornelius was waiting for them, having called together his kinsmen and his near friends. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And when it came to pass that Peter entered, Cornelius met him, and fell down at his feet, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The Greek word denotes an act of reverence, whether paid to a creature or to the Creator.</char></note>worshipped him. <verse number="26" style="v"/>But Peter raised him up, saying, Stand up; I myself also am a man. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And as he talked with him, he went in, and findeth many come together: <verse number="28" style="v"/>and he said unto them, Ye yourselves know <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">how unlawful it is for a man etc.</char></char></note>how it is an unlawful thing for a man that is a Jew to join himself or come unto one of another nation; and <char style="add">yet</char> unto me hath God showed that I should not call any man common or unclean: <verse number="29" style="v"/>wherefore also I came without gainsaying, when I was sent for. I ask therefore with what intent ye sent for me. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And Cornelius said, Four days ago, until this hour, I was keeping the ninth hour of prayer in my house; and behold, a man stood before me in bright apparel, <verse number="31" style="v"/>and saith, Cornelius, thy prayer is heard, and thine alms are had in remembrance in the sight of God. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Send therefore to Joppa, and call unto thee Simon, who is surnamed Peter; he lodgeth in the house of Simon a tanner, by the sea side. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Forthwith therefore I sent to thee; and thou hast well done that thou art come. Now therefore we are all here present in the sight of God, to hear all things that have been commanded thee of the Lord. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And Peter opened his mouth, and said,</para>
	<para style="p">Of a truth I perceive that God is no respecter of persons: <verse number="35" style="v"/>but in every nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteousness, is acceptable to him. <verse number="36" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">He sent the word unto</char>.</char></note>The word which he sent unto the children of Israel, preaching <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the gospel</char></char></note>good tidings of peace by Jesus Christ (he is Lord of all)&#8212;<verse number="37" style="v"/>that saying ye yourselves know, which was published throughout all Judaea, beginning from Galilee, after the baptism which John preached; <verse number="38" style="v"/><char style="add">even</char> Jesus of Nazareth, how God anointed him with the Holy Spirit and with power: who went about doing good, and healing all that were oppressed of the devil; for God was with him. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And we are witnesses of all things which he did both in the country of the Jews, and in Jerusalem; whom also they slew, hanging him on a tree. <verse number="40" style="v"/>Him God raised up the third day, and gave him to be made manifest, <verse number="41" style="v"/>not to all the people, but unto witnesses that were chosen before of God, <char style="add">even</char> to us, who ate and drank with him after he rose from the dead. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And he charged us to preach unto the people, and to testify that this is he who is ordained of God <char style="add">to be</char> the Judge of the living and the dead. <verse number="43" style="v"/>To him bear all the prophets witness, that through his name every one that believeth on him shall receive remission of sins.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v"/>While Peter yet spake these words, the Holy Spirit fell on all them that heard the word. <verse number="45" style="v"/>And they of the circumcision that believed were amazed, as many as came with Peter, because that on the Gentiles also was poured out the gift of the Holy Spirit. <verse number="46" style="v"/>For they heard them speak with tongues, and magnify God. Then answered Peter, <verse number="47" style="v"/>Can any man forbid the water, that these should not be baptized, who have received the Holy Spirit as well as we? <verse number="48" style="v"/>And he commanded them to be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ. Then prayed they him to tarry certain days.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now the apostles and the brethren that were in Judaea heard that the Gentiles also had received the word of God. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And when Peter was come up to Jerusalem, they that were of the circumcision contended with him, <verse number="3" style="v"/>saying, Thou wentest in to men uncircumcised, and didst eat with them. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But Peter began, and expounded <char style="add">the matter</char> unto them in order, saying, <verse number="5" style="v"/>I was in the city of Joppa praying: and in a trance I saw a vision, a certain vessel descending, as it were a great sheet let down from heaven by four corners; and it came even unto me: <verse number="6" style="v"/>upon which when I had fastened mine eyes, I considered, and saw the fourfooted beasts of the earth and wild beasts and creeping things and birds of the heaven. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And I heard also a voice saying unto me, Rise, Peter; kill and eat. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But I said, Not so, Lord: for nothing common or unclean hath ever entered into my mouth. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But a voice answered the second time out of heaven, What God hath cleansed, make not thou common. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And this was done thrice: and all were drawn up again into heaven. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And behold, forthwith three men stood before the house in which we were, having been sent from Caesarea unto me. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And the Spirit bade me go with them, making no distinction. And these six brethren also accompanied me; and we entered into the man&#8217;s house: <verse number="13" style="v"/>and he told us how he had seen the angel standing in his house, and saying, Send to Joppa, and fetch Simon, whose surname is Peter; <verse number="14" style="v"/>who shall speak unto thee words, whereby thou shalt be saved, thou and all thy house. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And as I began to speak, the Holy Spirit fell on them, even as on us at the beginning. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And I remembered the word of the Lord, how he said, John indeed baptized with water; but ye shall be baptized <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with</char></char></note>in the Holy Spirit. <verse number="17" style="v"/>If then God gave unto them the like gift as <char style="add">he did</char> also unto us, when we believed on the Lord Jesus Christ, who was I, that I could withstand God? <verse number="18" style="v"/>And when they heard these things, they held their peace, and glorified God, saying, Then to the Gentiles also hath God granted repentance unto life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>They therefore that were scattered abroad upon the tribulation that arose about Stephen travelled as far as Phoenicia, and Cyprus, and Antioch, speaking the word to none save only to Jews. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But there were some of them, men of Cyprus and Cyrene, who, when they were come to Antioch, spake unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">Grecian Jews</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 6:1">6:1</ref>.</char></note>Greeks also, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preaching the Lord Jesus. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And the hand of the Lord was with them: and a great number that believed turned unto the Lord. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the report concerning them came to the ears of the church which was in Jerusalem: and they sent forth Barnabas as far as Antioch: <verse number="23" style="v"/>who, when he was come, and had seen the grace of God, was glad; and he exhorted them all, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">that they would cleave unto the purpose of their heart in the Lord</char>.</char></note>that with purpose of heart they would cleave unto the Lord: <verse number="24" style="v"/>for he was a good man, and full of the Holy Spirit and of faith: and much people was added unto the Lord. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And he went forth to Tarsus to seek for Saul; <verse number="26" style="v"/>and when he had found him, he brought him unto Antioch. And it came to pass, that even for a whole year they were gathered together <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in</char>.</char></note>with the church, and taught much people; and that the disciples were called Christians first in Antioch.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v"/>Now in these days there came down prophets from Jerusalem unto Antioch. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And there stood up one of them named Agabus, and signified by the Spirit that there should be a great famine over all <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>the world: which came to pass in the days of Claudius. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And the disciples, every man according to his ability, determined to send <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">for ministry</char>. Compare <ref loc="ACT 6:1">6:1</ref>.</char></note>relief unto the brethren that dwelt in Judaea: <verse number="30" style="v"/>which also they did, sending it to the elders by the hand of Barnabas and Saul.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now about that time Herod the king put forth his hands to afflict certain of the church. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he killed James the brother of John with the sword. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And when he saw that it pleased the Jews, he proceeded to seize Peter also. And <char style="add">those</char> were the days of unleavened bread. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And when he had taken him, he put him in prison, and delivered him to four quaternions of soldiers to guard him; intending after the Passover to bring him forth to the people. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Peter therefore was kept in the prison: but prayer was made earnestly of the church unto God for him. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And when Herod was about to bring him forth, the same night Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, bound with two chains: and guards before the door kept the prison. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And behold, an angel of the Lord stood by him, and a light shined in the cell: and he smote Peter on the side, and awoke him, saying, Rise up quickly. And his chains fell off from his hands. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And the angel said unto him, Gird thyself, and bind on thy sandals. And he did so. And he saith unto him, Cast thy garment about thee, and follow me. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And he went out, and followed; and he knew not that it was true which was done <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">through</char>.</char></note>by the angel, but thought he saw a vision. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And when they were past the first and the second guard, they came unto the iron gate that leadeth into the city; which opened to them of its own accord: and they went out, and passed on through one street; and straightway the angel departed from him. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And when Peter was come to himself, he said, Now I know of a truth, that the Lord hath sent forth his angel and delivered me out of the hand of Herod, and from all the expectation of the people of the Jews. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And when he had considered <char style="add">the thing</char>, he came to the house of Mary the mother of John whose surname was Mark; where many were gathered together and were praying. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And when he knocked at the door of the gate, a maid came to answer, named Rhoda. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And when she knew Peter&#8217;s voice, she opened not the gate for joy, but ran in, and told that Peter stood before the gate. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And they said unto her, Thou art mad. But she confidently affirmed that it was even so. And they said, It is his angel. <verse number="16" style="v"/>But Peter continued knocking: and when they had opened, they saw him, and were amazed. <verse number="17" style="v"/>But he, beckoning unto them with the hand to hold their peace, declared unto them how the Lord had brought him forth out of the prison. And he said, Tell these things unto James, and to the brethren. And he departed, and went to another place. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Now as soon as it was day, there was no small stir among the soldiers, what was become of Peter. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And when Herod had sought for him, and found him not, he examined the guards, and commanded that they should be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">led away to death</char>.</char></note>put to death. And he went down from Judaea to Caesarea, and tarried there.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>Now he was highly displeased with them of Tyre and Sidon: and they came with one accord to him, and, having made Blastus the king&#8217;s chamberlain their friend, they asked for peace, because their country was fed from the king&#8217;s country. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And upon a set day Herod arrayed himself in royal apparel, and sat on the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">judgment-seat</char>. See <ref loc="MAT 27:19">Mt. 27:19</ref>.</char></note>throne, and made an oration unto them. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the people shouted, <char style="add">saying</char>, The voice of a god, and not of a man. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And immediately an angel of the Lord smote him, because he gave not God the glory: and he was eaten of worms, and gave up the ghost.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>But the word of God grew and multiplied.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>And Barnabas and Saul returned <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">to Jerusalem</char>.</char></note>from Jerusalem, when they had fulfilled their ministration, taking with them John whose surname was Mark.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now there were at Antioch, in the church that was <char style="add">there</char>, prophets and teachers, Barnabas, and Symeon that was called Niger, and Lucius of Cyrene, and Manaen the foster-brother of Herod the tetrarch, and Saul. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And as they ministered to the Lord, and fasted, the Holy Spirit said, Separate me Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Then, when they had fasted and prayed and laid their hands on them, they sent them away.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>So they, being sent forth by the Holy Spirit, went down to Seleucia; and from thence they sailed to Cyprus. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And when they were at Salamis, they proclaimed the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews: and they had also John as their attendant. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And when they had gone through the whole island unto Paphos, they found a certain <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Magus</char>: as in <ref loc="MAT 2:1">Mt. 2:1</ref>, <ref loc="MAT 2:7">7</ref>, <ref loc="MAT 2:16">16</ref>.</char></note>sorcerer, a false prophet, a Jew, whose name was Bar-Jesus; <verse number="7" style="v"/>who was with the proconsul, Sergius Paulus, a man of understanding. The same called unto him Barnabas and Saul, and sought to hear the word of God. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But Elymas the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Magus</char>: as in <ref loc="MAT 2:1">Mt. 2:1</ref>, <ref loc="MAT 2:7">7</ref>, <ref loc="MAT 2:16">16</ref>.</char></note>sorcerer (for so is his name by interpretation) withstood them, seeking to turn aside the proconsul from the faith. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But Saul, who is also <char style="add">called</char> Paul, filled with the Holy Spirit, fastened his eyes on him, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and said, O full of all guile and all villany, thou son of the devil, thou enemy of all righteousness, wilt thou not cease to pervert the right ways of the Lord? <verse number="11" style="v"/>And now, behold, the hand of the Lord is upon thee, and thou shalt be blind, not seeing the sun <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">until</char></char></note>for a season. And immediately there fell on him a mist and a darkness; and he went about seeking some to lead him by the hand. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Then the proconsul, when he saw what was done, believed, being astonished at the teaching of the Lord.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>Now Paul and his company set sail from Paphos, and came to Perga in Pamphylia: and John departed from them and returned to Jerusalem. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But they, passing through from Perga, came to Antioch of Pisidia; and they went into the synagogue on the sabbath day, and sat down. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And after the reading of the law and the prophets the rulers of the synagogue sent unto them, saying, Brethren, if ye have any word of exhortation for the people, say on. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And Paul stood up, and beckoning with the hand said,</para>
	<para style="p">Men of Israel, and ye that fear God, hearken: <verse number="17" style="v"/>The God of this people Israel chose our fathers, and exalted the people when they sojourned in the land of Egypt, and with a high arm led he them forth out of it. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And for about the time of forty years <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">suffered he their manners in the wilderness</char>. See <ref loc="DEU 9:7">Dt. 9:7</ref>.</char></note>as a nursing-father bare he them in the wilderness. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And when he had destroyed seven nations in the land of Canaan, he gave <char style="add">them</char> their land for an inheritance, for about four hundred and fifty years: <verse number="20" style="v"/>and after these things he gave <char style="add">them</char> judges until Samuel the prophet. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And afterward they asked for a king: and God gave unto them Saul the son of Kish, a man of the tribe of Benjamin, for the space of forty years. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And when he had removed him, he raised up David to be their king; to whom also he bare witness and said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="1SA 13:14">1 Sam. 13:14</ref>; <ref loc="PSA 89:20">Ps. 89:20</ref>.</char></note>I have found David the son of Jesse, a man after my heart, who shall do all my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">wills</char>.</char></note>will. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Of this man&#8217;s seed hath God according to promise brought unto Israel a Saviour, Jesus; <verse number="24" style="v"/>when John had first preached <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">before the face of his entering in</char>.</char></note>before his coming the baptism of repentance to all the people of Israel. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And as John was fulfilling his course, he said, What suppose ye that I am? I am not <char style="add">he</char>. But behold, there cometh one after me the shoes of whose feet I am not worthy to unloose. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Brethren, children of the stock of Abraham, and those among you that fear God, to us is the word of this salvation sent forth. <verse number="27" style="v"/>For they that dwell in Jerusalem, and their rulers, because they knew him not, nor the voices of the prophets which are read every sabbath, fulfilled <char style="add">them</char> by condemning <char style="add">him</char>. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And though they found no cause of death <char style="add">in him</char>, yet asked they of Pilate that he should be slain. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And when they had fulfilled all things that were written of him, they took him down from the tree, and laid him in a tomb. <verse number="30" style="v"/>But God raised him from the dead: <verse number="31" style="v"/>and he was seen for many days of them that came up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem, who are now his witnesses unto the people. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And we bring you good tidings of the promise made unto the fathers, <verse number="33" style="v"/>that God hath fulfilled the same unto our children, in that he raised up Jesus; as also it is written in the second psalm, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 2:7">Ps. 2:7</ref>.</char></note>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And as concerning that he raised him up from the dead, now no more to return to corruption, he hath spoken on this wise, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 55:3">Isa. 55:3</ref>.</char></note>I will give you the holy and sure <char style="add">blessings</char> of David. <verse number="35" style="v"/>Because he saith also in another <char style="add">psalm</char>, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 16:10">Ps. 16:10</ref>.</char></note>Thou wilt not give thy Holy One to see corruption. <verse number="36" style="v"/>For David, after he had <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">served his own generation by the counsel of God, fell asleep</char>. Or, <char style="it">served his own generation, fell asleep by the counsel of God</char></char></note>in his own generation served the counsel of God, fell asleep, and was laid unto his fathers, and saw corruption: <verse number="37" style="v"/>but he whom God raised up saw no corruption. <verse number="38" style="v"/>Be it known unto you therefore, brethren, that through this man is proclaimed unto you remission of sins: <verse number="39" style="v"/>and by him every one that believeth is justified from all things, from which ye could not be justified by the law of Moses. <verse number="40" style="v"/>Beware therefore, lest that come upon <char style="add">you</char> which is spoken in the prophets:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="41" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="HAB 1:5">Hab. 1:5</ref>.</char></note>Behold, ye despisers, and wonder, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">vanish away</char>. <ref loc="JAS 4:14">Jas. 4:14</ref></char></note>perish;</para>
	<para style="q1">For I work a work in your days,</para>
	<para style="q1">A work which ye shall in no wise believe, if one declare it unto you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v"/>And as they went out, they besought that these words might be spoken to them the next sabbath. <verse number="43" style="v"/>Now when the synagogue broke up, many of the Jews and of the devout proselytes followed Paul and Barnabas; who, speaking to them, urged them to continue in the grace of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v"/>And the next sabbath almost the whole city was gathered together to hear the word of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">the Lord</char>.</char></note>God. <verse number="45" style="v"/>But when the Jews saw the multitudes, they were filled with jealousy, and contradicted the things which were spoken by Paul, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">railed</char></char></note>blasphemed. <verse number="46" style="v"/>And Paul and Barnabas spake out boldly, and said, It was necessary that the word of God should first be spoken to you. Seeing ye thrust it from you, and judge yourselves unworthy of eternal life, lo, we turn to the Gentiles. <verse number="47" style="v"/>For so hath the Lord commanded us, <char style="add">saying</char>,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 49:6">Isa. 49:6</ref>.</char></note>I have set thee for a light of the Gentiles,</para>
	<para style="q1">That thou shouldest be for salvation unto the uttermost part of the earth.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="48" style="v"/>And as the Gentiles heard this, they were glad, and glorified the word of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">the Lord</char>.</char></note>God: and as many as were ordained to eternal life believed. <verse number="49" style="v"/>And the word of the Lord was spread abroad throughout all the region. <verse number="50" style="v"/>But the Jews urged on the devout women of honorable estate, and the chief men of the city, and stirred up a persecution against Paul and Barnabas, and cast them out of their borders. <verse number="51" style="v"/>But they shook off the dust of their feet against them, and came unto Iconium. <verse number="52" style="v"/>And the disciples were filled with joy and with the Holy Spirit.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass in Iconium that they entered together into the synagogue of the Jews, and so spake that a great multitude both of Jews and of Greeks believed. <verse number="2" style="v"/>But the Jews that were disobedient stirred up the souls of the Gentiles, and made them evil affected against the brethren. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Long time therefore they tarried <char style="add">there</char> speaking boldly in the Lord, who bare witness unto the word of his grace, granting signs and wonders to be done by their hands. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But the multitude of the city was divided; and part held with the Jews, and part with the apostles. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And when there was made an onset both of the Gentiles and of the Jews with their rulers, to treat them shamefully and to stone them, <verse number="6" style="v"/>they became aware of it, and fled unto the cities of Lycaonia, Lystra and Derbe, and the region round about: <verse number="7" style="v"/>and there they <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preached the gospel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And at Lystra there sat a certain man, impotent in his feet, a cripple from his mother&#8217;s womb, who never had walked. <verse number="9" style="v"/>The same heard Paul speaking: who, fastening his eyes upon him, and seeing that he had faith to be made whole, <verse number="10" style="v"/>said with a loud voice, Stand upright on thy feet. And he leaped up and walked. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And when the multitude saw what Paul had done, they lifted up their voice, saying in the speech of Lycaonia, The gods are come down to us in the likeness of men. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And they called Barnabas, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Zeus</char>.</char></note>Jupiter; and Paul, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Hermes</char>.</char></note>Mercury, because he was the chief speaker. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And the priest of Jupiter whose <char style="add">temple</char> was before the city, brought oxen and garlands unto the gates, and would have done sacrifice with the multitudes. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But when the apostles, Barnabas and Paul, heard of it, they rent their garments, and sprang forth among the multitude, crying out <verse number="15" style="v"/>and saying, Sirs, why do ye these things? We also are men of like <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">nature</char></char></note>passions with you, and bring you good tidings, that ye should turn from these vain things unto a living God, who made the heaven and the earth and the sea, and all that in them is: <verse number="16" style="v"/>who in the generations gone by suffered all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gentiles</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 4:25">4:25</ref>.</char></note>nations to walk in their own ways. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And yet he left not himself without witness, in that he did good and gave you from heaven rains and fruitful seasons, filling your hearts with food and gladness. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And with these sayings scarce restrained they the multitudes from doing sacrifice unto them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>But there came Jews thither from Antioch and Iconium: and having persuaded the multitudes, they stoned Paul, and dragged him out of the city, supposing that he was dead. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But as the disciples stood round about him, he rose up, and entered into the city: and on the morrow he went forth with Barnabas to Derbe. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And when they had <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">brought the good tidings</char>. Compare <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preached the gospel to that city, and had made many disciples, they returned to Lystra, and to Iconium, and to Antioch, <verse number="22" style="v"/>confirming the souls of the disciples, exhorting them to continue in the faith, and that through many tribulations we must enter into the kingdom of God. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And when they had appointed for them elders in every church, and had prayed with fasting, they commended them to the Lord, on whom they had believed. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And they passed through Pisidia, and came to Pamphylia. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And when they had spoken the word in Perga, they went down to Attalia; <verse number="26" style="v"/>and thence they sailed to Antioch, from whence they had been committed to the grace of God for the work which they had fulfilled. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And when they were come, and had gathered the church together, they rehearsed all things that God had done with them, and that he had opened a door of faith unto the Gentiles. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And they tarried no little time with the disciples.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And certain men came down from Judaea and taught the brethren, <char style="add">saying</char>, Except ye be circumcised after the custom of Moses, ye cannot be saved. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And when Paul and Barnabas had no small dissension and questioning with them, <char style="add">the brethren</char> appointed that Paul and Barnabas, and certain other of them, should go up to Jerusalem unto the apostles and elders about this question. <verse number="3" style="v"/>They therefore, being brought on their way by the church, passed through both Phoenicia and Samaria, declaring the conversion of the Gentiles: and they caused great joy unto all the brethren. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And when they were come to Jerusalem, they were received of the church and the apostles and the elders, and they rehearsed all things that God had done with them. <verse number="5" style="v"/>But there rose up certain of the sect of the Pharisees who believed, saying, It is needful to circumcise them, and to charge them to keep the law of Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And the apostles and the elders were gathered together to consider of this matter. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And when there had been much questioning, Peter rose up, and said unto them,</para>
	<para style="p">Brethren, ye know that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">from early days</char>.</char></note>a good while ago God made choice among you, that by my mouth the Gentiles should hear the word of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">good tidings</char></char></note>gospel, and believe. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And God, who knoweth the heart, bare them witness, giving them the Holy Spirit, even as he did unto us; <verse number="9" style="v"/>and he made no distinction between us and them, cleansing their hearts by faith. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Now therefore why make ye trial of God, that ye should put a yoke upon the neck of the disciples which neither our fathers nor we were able to bear? <verse number="11" style="v"/>But we believe that we shall be saved through the grace of the Lord Jesus, in like manner as they.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And all the multitude kept silence; and they hearkened unto Barnabas and Paul rehearsing what signs and wonders God had wrought among the Gentiles through them. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And after they had held their peace, James answered, saying,</para>
	<para style="p">Brethren, hearken unto me: <verse number="14" style="v"/>Symeon hath rehearsed how first God visited the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 4:25">4:25</ref>.</char></note>Gentiles, to take out of them a people for his name. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And to this agree the words of the prophets; as it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="16" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="AMO 9:11">Am. 9:11</ref>, <ref loc="AMO 9:12">12</ref>.</char></note>After these things I will return,</para>
	<para style="q1">And I will build again the tabernacle of David, which is fallen;</para>
	<para style="q1">And I will build again the ruins thereof,</para>
	<para style="q1">And I will set it up:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="17" style="v"/>That the residue of men may seek after the Lord,</para>
	<para style="q1">And all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 4:25">4:25</ref>.</char></note>Gentiles, upon whom my name is called,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="18" style="v"/>Saith the Lord, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">who doeth these things</char> where were <char style="it">known etc.</char></char></note>who maketh these things known from of old.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="19" style="v"/>Wherefore my judgment is, that we trouble not them that from among the Gentiles turn to God; <verse number="20" style="v"/>but that we <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">enjoin them</char></char></note>write unto them, that they abstain from the pollutions of idols, and from fornication, and from what is strangled, and from blood. <verse number="21" style="v"/>For Moses from generations of old hath in every city them that preach him, being read in the synagogues every sabbath.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>Then it seemed good to the apostles and the elders, with the whole church, to choose men out of their company, and send them to Antioch with Paul and Barnabas; <char style="add">namely</char>, Judas called Barsabbas, and Silas, chief men among the brethren: <verse number="23" style="v"/>and they wrote <char style="add">thus</char> by them, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">The apostles and the elder brethren</char></char></note>The apostles and the elders, brethren, unto the brethren who are of the Gentiles in Antioch and Syria and Cilicia, greeting: <verse number="24" style="v"/>Forasmuch as we have heard that certain <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">who went out</char>.</char></note>who went out from us have troubled you with words, subverting your souls; to whom we gave no commandment; <verse number="25" style="v"/>it seemed good unto us, having come to one accord, to choose out men and send them unto you with our beloved Barnabas and Paul, <verse number="26" style="v"/>men that have hazarded their lives for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse number="27" style="v"/>We have sent therefore Judas and Silas, who themselves also shall tell you the same things by word of mouth. <verse number="28" style="v"/>For it seemed good to the Holy Spirit, and to us, to lay upon you no greater burden than these necessary things: <verse number="29" style="v"/>that ye abstain from things sacrificed to idols, and from blood, and from things strangled, and from fornication; from which if ye keep yourselves, it shall be well with you. Fare ye well.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>So they, when they were dismissed, came down to Antioch; and having gathered the multitude together, they delivered the epistle. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And when they had read it, they rejoiced for the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">exhortation</char></char></note>consolation. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And Judas and Silas, being themselves also prophets, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">comforted</char></char></note>exhorted the brethren with many words, and confirmed them. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And after they had spent some time <char style="add">there</char>, they were dismissed in peace from the brethren unto those that had sent them forth.<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities insert, with variations, <ref loc="ACT 15:34">verse 34</ref> <char style="it">But it seemed good unto Silas to abide there</char>.</char></note> <verse number="35" style="v"/>But Paul and Barnabas tarried in Antioch, teaching and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Compare marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preaching the word of the Lord, with many others also.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v"/>And after some days Paul said unto Barnabas, Let us return now and visit the brethren in every city wherein we proclaimed the word of the Lord, <char style="add">and see</char> how they fare. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And Barnabas was minded to take with them John also, who was called Mark. <verse number="38" style="v"/>But Paul thought not good to take with them him who withdrew from them from Pamphylia, and went not with them to the work. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And there arose a sharp contention, so that they parted asunder one from the other, and Barnabas took Mark with him, and sailed away unto Cyprus: <verse number="40" style="v"/>but Paul chose Silas, and went forth, being commended by the brethren to the grace of the Lord. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And he went through Syria and Cilicia, confirming the churches.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And he came also to Derbe and to Lystra: and behold, a certain disciple was there, named Timothy, the son of a Jewess that believed; but his father was a Greek. <verse number="2" style="v"/>The same was well reported of by the brethren that were at Lystra and Iconium. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Him would Paul have to go forth with him; and he took and circumcised him because of the Jews that were in those parts: for they all knew that his father was a Greek. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And as they went on their way through the cities, they delivered them the decrees to keep which had been ordained of the apostles and elders that were at Jerusalem. <verse number="5" style="v"/>So the churches were strengthened <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in faith</char></char></note>in the faith, and increased in number daily.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And they went through <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Phrygia and the region of Galatia</char></char></note>the region of Phrygia and Galatia, having been forbidden of the Holy Spirit to speak the word in Asia; <verse number="7" style="v"/>and when they were come over against Mysia, they assayed to go into Bithynia; and the Spirit of Jesus suffered them not; <verse number="8" style="v"/>and passing by Mysia, they came down to Troas. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And a vision appeared to Paul in the night: There was a man of Macedonia standing, beseeching him, and saying, Come over into Macedonia, and help us. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And when he had seen the vision, straightway we sought to go forth into Macedonia, concluding that God had called us to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bring the good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preach the gospel unto them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>Setting sail therefore from Troas, we made a straight course to Samothrace, and the day following to Neapolis; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and from thence to Philippi, which is a city of Macedonia, the first of the district, a <char style="add">Roman</char> colony: and we were in this city tarrying certain days. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And on the sabbath day we went forth without the gate by a river side, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many authorities read <char style="it">where was wont to be etc.</char></char></note>where we supposed there was a place of prayer; and we sat down, and spake unto the women that were come together. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And a certain woman named Lydia, a seller of purple, of the city of Thyatira, one that worshipped God, heard us: whose heart the Lord opened to give heed unto the things which were spoken by Paul. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And when she was baptized, and her household, she besought us, saying, If ye have judged me to be faithful to the Lord, come into my house, and abide <char style="add">there</char>. And she constrained us.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And it came to pass, as we were going to the place of prayer, that a certain maid having <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">a spirit, a Python</char>.</char></note>a spirit of divination met us, who brought her masters much gain by soothsaying. <verse number="17" style="v"/>The same following after Paul and us cried out, saying, These men are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants of the Most High God, who proclaim unto you <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a way</char></char></note>the way of salvation. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And this she did for many days. But Paul, being sore troubled, turned and said to the spirit, I charge thee in the name of Jesus Christ to come out of her. And it came out that very hour.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>But when her masters saw that the hope of their gain was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">come out</char>.</char></note>gone, they laid hold on Paul and Silas, and dragged them into the marketplace before the rulers, <verse number="20" style="v"/>and when they had brought them unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">praetors</char>: compare verses <ref loc="ACT 16:22">22</ref>, <ref loc="ACT 16:35">35</ref>, <ref loc="ACT 16:36">36</ref>, <ref loc="ACT 16:38">38</ref>.</char></note>magistrates, they said, These men, being Jews, do exceedingly trouble our city, <verse number="21" style="v"/>and set forth customs which it is not lawful for us to receive, or to observe, being Romans. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the multitude rose up together against them: and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">praetors</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 16:20">verse 20</ref>.</char></note>magistrates rent their garments off them, and commanded to beat them with rods. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And when they had laid many stripes upon them, they cast them into prison, charging the jailor to keep them safely: <verse number="24" style="v"/>who, having received such a charge, cast them into the inner prison, and made their feet fast in the stocks. <verse number="25" style="v"/>But about midnight Paul and Silas were praying and singing hymns unto God, and the prisoners were listening to them; <verse number="26" style="v"/>and suddenly there was a great earthquake, so that the foundations of the prison-house were shaken: and immediately all the doors were opened; and every one&#8217;s bands were loosed. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And the jailor, being roused out of sleep and seeing the prison doors open, drew his sword and was about to kill himself, supposing that the prisoners had escaped. <verse number="28" style="v"/>But Paul cried with a loud voice, saying, Do thyself no harm: for we are all here. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And he called for lights and sprang in, and, trembling for fear, fell down before Paul and Silas, <verse number="30" style="v"/>and brought them out and said, Sirs, what must I do to be saved? <verse number="31" style="v"/>And they said, Believe on the Lord Jesus, and thou shalt be saved, thou and thy house. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And they spake the word of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">God</char>.</char></note>the Lord unto him, with all that were in his house. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And he took them the same hour of the night, and washed their stripes; and was baptized, he and all his, immediately. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And he brought them up into his house, and set <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">a table</char>.</char></note>food before them, and rejoiced greatly, with all his house, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">having believed God</char></char></note>having believed in God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v"/>But when it was day, the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">praetors</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 16:20">verse 20</ref>.</char></note>magistrates sent the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lictors</char>.</char></note>serjeants, saying, Let those men go. <verse number="36" style="v"/>And the jailor reported the words to Paul, <char style="add">saying</char>, The <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">praetors</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 16:20">verse 20</ref>.</char></note>magistrates have sent to let you go: now therefore come forth, and go in peace. <verse number="37" style="v"/>But Paul said unto them, They have beaten us publicly, uncondemned, men that are Romans, and have cast us into prison; and do they now cast us out privily? nay verily; but let them come themselves and bring us out. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lictors</char>.</char></note>serjeants reported these words unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">praetors</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 16:20">verse 20</ref>.</char></note>magistrates: and they feared when they heard that they were Romans; <verse number="39" style="v"/>and they came and besought them; and when they had brought them out, they asked them to go away from the city. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And they went out of the prison, and entered into <char style="add">the house of</char> Lydia: and when they had seen the brethren, they <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">exhorted</char></char></note>comforted them, and departed.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now when they had passed through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they came to Thessalonica, where was a synagogue of the Jews: <verse number="2" style="v"/>and Paul, as his custom was, went in unto them, and for three <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">weeks</char></char></note>sabbath days reasoned with them from the scriptures, <verse number="3" style="v"/>opening and alleging that it behooved the Christ to suffer, and to rise again from the dead; and that this Jesus, whom, <char style="add">said he</char>, I proclaim unto you, is the Christ. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And some of them were persuaded, and consorted with Paul and Silas; and of the devout Greeks a great multitude, and of the chief women not a few. <verse number="5" style="v"/>But the Jews, being moved with jealousy, took unto them certain vile fellows of the rabble, and gathering a crowd, set the city on an uproar; and assaulting the house of Jason, they sought to bring them forth to the people. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And when they found them not, they dragged Jason and certain brethren before the rulers of the city, crying, These that have turned <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>the world upside down are come hither also; <verse number="7" style="v"/>whom Jason hath received: and these all act contrary to the decrees of Caesar, saying that there is another king, <char style="add">one</char> Jesus. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And they troubled the multitude and the rulers of the city, when they heard these things. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And when they had taken security from Jason and the rest, they let them go.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And the brethren immediately sent away Paul and Silas by night unto Beroea: who when they were come thither went into the synagogue of the Jews. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Now these were more noble than those in Thessalonica, in that they received the word with all readiness of mind, examining the scriptures daily, whether these things were so. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Many of them therefore believed; also of the Greek women of honorable estate, and of men, not a few. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But when the Jews of Thessalonica had knowledge that the word of God was proclaimed of Paul at Beroea also, they came thither likewise, stirring up and troubling the multitudes. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And then immediately the brethren sent forth Paul to go as far as to the sea: and Silas and Timothy abode there still. <verse number="15" style="v"/>But they that conducted Paul brought him as far as Athens: and receiving a commandment unto Silas and Timothy that they should come to him with all speed, they departed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>Now while Paul waited for them at Athens, his spirit was provoked within him as he beheld the city full of idols. <verse number="17" style="v"/>So he reasoned in the synagogue with the Jews and the devout persons, and in the marketplace every day with them that met him. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And certain also of the Epicurean and Stoic philosophers encountered him. And some said, What would this babbler say? others, He seemeth to be a setter forth of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">foreign divinities</char></char></note>strange <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">demons</char>.</char></note>gods: because he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ACT 5:42">5:42</ref>.</char></note>preached Jesus and the resurrection. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And they took hold of him, and brought him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">before</char></char></note>unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the hill of Mars</char></char></note>the Areopagus, saying, May we know what this new teaching is, which is spoken by thee? <verse number="20" style="v"/>For thou bringest certain strange things to our ears: we would know therefore what these things mean. <verse number="21" style="v"/>(Now all the Athenians and the strangers sojourning there <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">had leisure for nothing else</char></char></note>spent their time in nothing else, but either to tell or to hear some new thing.) <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Paul stood in the midst of the Areopagus, and said,</para>
	<para style="p">Ye men of Athens, in all things I perceive that ye are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">somewhat superstitious</char></char></note>very religious. <verse number="23" style="v"/>For as I passed along, and observed the objects of your worship, I found also an altar with this inscription, <char style="sc">To an Unknown God</char>. What therefore ye worship in ignorance, this I set forth unto you. <verse number="24" style="v"/>The God that made the world and all things therein, he, being Lord of heaven and earth, dwelleth not in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuaries</char></char></note>temples made with hands; <verse number="25" style="v"/>neither is he served by men&#8217;s hands, as though he needed anything, seeing he himself giveth to all life, and breath, and all things; <verse number="26" style="v"/>and he made of one every nation of men to dwell on all the face of the earth, having determined <char style="add">their</char> appointed seasons, and the bounds of their habitation; <verse number="27" style="v"/>that they should seek God, if haply they might feel after him and find him, though he is not far from each one of us: <verse number="28" style="v"/>for in him we live, and move, and have our being; as certain even of your own poets have said,</para>
	<para style="p">For we are also his offspring. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Being then the offspring of God, we ought not to think that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that which is divine</char></char></note>the Godhead is like unto gold, or silver, or stone, graven by art and device of man. <verse number="30" style="v"/>The times of ignorance therefore God overlooked; but now he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">declareth to men</char>.</char></note>commandeth men that they should all everywhere repent: <verse number="31" style="v"/>inasmuch as he hath appointed a day in which he will judge <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>the world in righteousness <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in</char>.</char></note>by <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a man</char></char></note>the man whom he hath ordained; whereof he hath given assurance unto all men, in that he hath raised him from the dead.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v"/>Now when they heard of the resurrection of the dead, some mocked; but others said, We will hear thee concerning this yet again. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Thus Paul went out from among them. <verse number="34" style="v"/>But certain men clave unto him, and believed: among whom also was Dionysius the Areopagite, and a woman named Damaris, and others with them.</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After these things he departed from Athens, and came to Corinth. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he found a certain Jew named Aquila, a man of Pontus by race, lately come from Italy, with his wife Priscilla, because Claudius had commanded all the Jews to depart from Rome: and he came unto them; <verse number="3" style="v"/>and because he was of the same trade, he abode with them, and they wrought; for by their trade they were tentmakers. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And he reasoned in the synagogue every sabbath, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sought to persuade</char>.</char></note>persuaded Jews and Greeks. <verse number="5" style="v"/>But when Silas and Timothy came down from Macedonia, Paul was constrained by the word, testifying to the Jews that Jesus was the Christ. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And when they opposed themselves and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">railed</char></char></note>blasphemed, he shook out his raiment and said unto them, Your blood <char style="add">be</char> upon your own heads; I am clean: from henceforth I will go unto the Gentiles. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he departed thence, and went into the house of a certain man named Titus Justus, one that worshipped God, whose house joined hard to the synagogue. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And Crispus, the ruler of the synagogue, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">believed the Lord</char>.</char></note>believed in the Lord with all his house; and many of the Corinthians hearing believed, and were baptized. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the Lord said unto Paul in the night by a vision, Be not afraid, but speak and hold not thy peace: <verse number="10" style="v"/>for I am with thee, and no man shall set on thee to harm thee: for I have much people in this city. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And he dwelt <char style="add">there</char> a year and six months, teaching the word of God among them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>But when Gallio was proconsul of Achaia, the Jews with one accord rose up against Paul and brought him before the judgment-seat, <verse number="13" style="v"/>saying, This man persuadeth men to worship God contrary to the law. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But when Paul was about to open his mouth, Gallio said unto the Jews, If indeed it were a matter of wrong or of wicked villany, O ye Jews, reason would that I should bear with you: <verse number="15" style="v"/>but if they are questions about words and names and your own law, look to it yourselves; I am not minded to be a judge of these matters. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he drove them from the judgment-seat. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And they all laid hold on Sosthenes, the ruler of the synagogue, and beat him before the judgment-seat. And Gallio cared for none of these things.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And Paul, having tarried after this yet many days, took his leave of the brethren, and sailed thence for Syria, and with him Priscilla and Aquila: having shorn his head in Cenchreae; for he had a vow. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And they came to Ephesus, and he left them there: but he himself entered into the synagogue, and reasoned with the Jews. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And when they asked him to abide a longer time, he consented not; <verse number="21" style="v"/>but taking his leave of them, and saying, I will return again unto you if God will, he set sail from Ephesus.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And when he had landed at Caesarea, he went up and saluted the church, and went down to Antioch. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And having spent some time <char style="add">there</char>, he departed, and went through the region of Galatia, and Phrygia, in order, establishing all the disciples.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>Now a certain Jew named Apollos, an Alexandrian by race, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a learned man</char></char></note>an eloquent man, came to Ephesus; and he was mighty in the scriptures. <verse number="25" style="v"/>This man had been <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">taught by word of mouth</char>.</char></note>instructed in the way of the Lord; and being fervent in spirit, he spake and taught accurately the things concerning Jesus, knowing only the baptism of John: <verse number="26" style="v"/>and he began to speak boldly in the synagogue. But when Priscilla and Aquila heard him, they took him unto them, and expounded unto him the way of God more accurately. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And when he was minded to pass over into Achaia, the brethren encouraged him, and wrote to the disciples to receive him: and when he was come, he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">helped much through grace them that had believed</char></char></note>helped them much that had believed through grace; <verse number="28" style="v"/>for he powerfully confuted the Jews, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">showing publicly</char></char></note><char style="add">and that</char> publicly, showing by the scriptures that Jesus was the Christ.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that, while Apollos was at Corinth, Paul having passed through the upper country came to Ephesus, and found certain disciples: <verse number="2" style="v"/>and he said unto them, Did ye receive the Holy Spirit when ye believed? And they <char style="add">said</char> unto him, Nay, we did not so much as hear whether <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">there is a Holy Spirit</char></char></note>the Holy Spirit was <char style="add">given</char>. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he said, Into what then were ye baptized? And they said, Into John&#8217;s baptism. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And Paul said, John baptized with the baptism of repentance, saying unto the people that they should believe on him that should come after him, that is, on Jesus. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And when they heard this, they were baptized into the name of the Lord Jesus. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And when Paul had laid his hands upon them, the Holy Spirit came on them; and they spake with tongues, and prophesied. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And they were in all about twelve men.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And he entered into the synagogue, and spake boldly for the space of three months, reasoning and persuading <char style="add">as to</char> the things concerning the kingdom of God. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But when some were hardened and disobedient, speaking evil of the Way before the multitude, he departed from them, and separated the disciples, reasoning daily in the school of Tyrannus. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And this continued for the space of two years; so that all they that dwelt in Asia heard the word of the Lord, both Jews and Greeks. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And God wrought special <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">powers</char>.</char></note>miracles by the hands of Paul: <verse number="12" style="v"/>insomuch that unto the sick were carried away from his body handkerchiefs or aprons, and the diseases departed from them, and the evil spirits went out. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But certain also of the strolling Jews, exorcists, took upon them to name over them that had the evil spirits the name of the Lord Jesus, saying, I adjure you by Jesus whom Paul preacheth. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And there were seven sons of one Sceva, a Jew, a chief priest, who did this. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the evil spirit answered and said unto them, Jesus I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">recognize</char></char></note>know, and Paul I know; but who are ye? <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the man in whom the evil spirit was leaped on them, and mastered both of them, and prevailed against them, so that they fled out of that house naked and wounded. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And this became known to all, both Jews and Greeks, that dwelt at Ephesus; and fear fell upon them all, and the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Many also of them that had believed came, confessing, and declaring their deeds. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And not a few of them that practised magical arts brought their books together and burned them in the sight of all; and they counted the price of them, and found it fifty thousand pieces of silver. <verse number="20" style="v"/>So mightily grew the word of the Lord and prevailed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>Now after these things were ended, Paul purposed in the spirit, when he had passed through Macedonia and Achaia, to go to Jerusalem, saying, After I have been there, I must also see Rome. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And having sent into Macedonia two of them that ministered unto him, Timothy and Erastus, he himself stayed in Asia for a while.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>And about that time there arose no small stir concerning the Way. <verse number="24" style="v"/>For a certain man named Demetrius, a silversmith, who made silver shrines of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Artemis</char>.</char></note>Diana, brought no little business unto the craftsmen; <verse number="25" style="v"/>whom he gathered together, with the workmen of like occupation, and said, Sirs, ye know that by this business we have our wealth. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And ye see and hear, that not alone at Ephesus, but almost throughout all Asia, this Paul hath persuaded and turned away much people, saying that they are no gods, that are made with hands: <verse number="27" style="v"/>and not only is there danger that this our trade come into disrepute; but also that the temple of the great goddess <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Artemis</char>.</char></note>Diana be made of no account, and that she should even be deposed from her magnificence whom all Asia and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>the world worshippeth. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And when they heard this they were filled with wrath, and cried out, saying, Great <char style="add">is</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Artemis</char>.</char></note>Diana of the Ephesians. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And the city was filled with the confusion: and they rushed with one accord into the theatre, having seized Gaius and Aristarchus, men of Macedonia, Paul&#8217;s companions in travel. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And when Paul was minded to enter in unto the people, the disciples suffered him not. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And certain also of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, officers having charge of festivals etc. in the Roman province of Asia.</char></note>Asiarchs, being his friends, sent unto him and besought him not to adventure himself into the theatre. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Some therefore cried one thing, and some another: for the assembly was in confusion; and the more part knew not wherefore they were come together. <verse number="33" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">And</char> some <char style="it">of the multitude instructed Alexander</char></char></note>And they brought Alexander out of the multitude, the Jews putting him forward. And Alexander beckoned with the hand, and would have made a defence unto the people. <verse number="34" style="v"/>But when they perceived that he was a Jew, all with one voice about the space of two hours cried out, Great <char style="add">is</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Artemis</char>.</char></note>Diana of the Ephesians. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And when the townclerk had quieted the multitude, he saith, Ye men of Ephesus, what man is there who knoweth not that the city of the Ephesians is temple-keeper of the great <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Artemis</char>.</char></note>Diana, and of the <char style="add">image</char> which fell down from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">heaven</char></char></note>Jupiter? <verse number="36" style="v"/>Seeing then that these things cannot be gainsaid, ye ought to be quiet, and to do nothing rash. <verse number="37" style="v"/>For ye have brought <char style="add">hither</char> these men, who are neither robbers of temples nor blasphemers of our goddess. <verse number="38" style="v"/>If therefore Demetrius, and the craftsmen that are with him, have a matter against any man, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">court</char> days <char style="it">are kept</char></char></note>the courts are open, and there are proconsuls: let them accuse one another. <verse number="39" style="v"/>But if ye seek anything about other matters, it shall be settled in the regular assembly. <verse number="40" style="v"/>For indeed we are in danger to be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">accused of riot concerning this day</char></char></note>accused concerning this day&#8217;s riot, there being no cause <char style="add">for it</char>: and as touching it we shall not be able to give account of this concourse. <verse number="41" style="v"/>And when he had thus spoken, he dismissed the assembly.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And after the uproar ceased, Paul having sent for the disciples and exhorted them, took leave of them, and departed to go into Macedonia. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And when he had gone through those parts, and had given them much exhortation, he came into Greece. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And when he had spent three months <char style="add">there</char>, and a plot was laid against him by the Jews as he was about to set sail for Syria, he determined to return through Macedonia. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And there accompanied him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities omit <char style="it">as far as Asia</char>.</char></note>as far as Asia, Sopater of Beroea, <char style="add">the son</char> of Pyrrhus; and of the Thessalonians, Aristarchus and Secundus; and Gaius of Derbe, and Timothy; and of Asia, Tychicus and Trophimus. <verse number="5" style="v"/>But these <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">came, and were waiting</char>.</char></note>had gone before, and were waiting for us at Troas. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And we sailed away from Philippi after the days of unleavened bread, and came unto them to Troas in five days; where we tarried seven days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And upon the first day of the week, when we were gathered together to break bread, Paul discoursed with them, intending to depart on the morrow; and prolonged his speech until midnight. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And there were many lights in the upper chamber where we were gathered together. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And there sat in the window a certain young man named Eutychus, borne down with deep sleep; and as Paul discoursed yet longer, being borne down by his sleep he fell down from the third story, and was taken up dead. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And Paul went down, and fell on him, and embracing him said, Make ye no ado; for his life is in him. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And when he was gone up, and had broken the bread, and eaten, and had talked with them a long while, even till break of day, so he departed. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And they brought the lad alive, and were not a little comforted.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>But we, going before to the ship, set sail for Assos, there intending to take in Paul: for so had he appointed, intending himself to go <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">on foot</char></char></note>by land. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And when he met us at Assos, we took him in, and came to Mitylene. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And sailing from thence, we came the following day over against Chios; and the next day we touched at Samos; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities insert <char style="it">having tarried at Trogyllium</char>.</char></note>the day after we came to Miletus. <verse number="16" style="v"/>For Paul had determined to sail past Ephesus, that he might not have to spend time in Asia; for he was hastening, if it were possible for him, to be at Jerusalem the day of Pentecost.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And from Miletus he sent to Ephesus, and called to him the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">presbyters</char></char></note>elders of the church. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And when they were come to him, he said unto them,</para>
	<para style="p">Ye yourselves know, from the first day that I set foot in Asia, after what manner I was with you all the time, <verse number="19" style="v"/>serving the Lord with all lowliness of mind, and with tears, and with trials which befell me by the plots of the Jews; <verse number="20" style="v"/>how I shrank not from declaring unto you anything that was profitable, and teaching you publicly, and from house to house, <verse number="21" style="v"/>testifying both to Jews and to Greeks repentance toward God, and faith toward our Lord Jesus <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities omit <char style="it">Christ</char>.</char></note>Christ. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And now, behold, I go bound in the spirit unto Jerusalem, not knowing the things that shall befall me there: <verse number="23" style="v"/>save that the Holy Spirit testifieth unto me in every city, saying that bonds and afflictions abide me. <verse number="24" style="v"/>But I hold not my life of any account as dear unto myself, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in comparison of accomplishing my course</char></char></note>so that I may accomplish my course, and the ministry which I received from the Lord Jesus, to testify the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">good tidings</char></char></note>gospel of the grace of God. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And now, behold, I know that ye all, among whom I went about preaching the kingdom, shall see my face no more. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Wherefore I testify unto you this day, that I am pure from the blood of all men. <verse number="27" style="v"/>For I shrank not from declaring unto you the whole counsel of God. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Take heed unto yourselves, and to all the flock, in which the Holy Spirit hath made you <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">overseers</char></char></note>bishops, to feed the church of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities, including the two oldest manuscripts, read <char style="it">God</char>.</char></note>the Lord which he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">acquired</char>.</char></note>purchased with his own blood. <verse number="29" style="v"/>I know that after my departing grievous wolves shall enter in among you, not sparing the flock; <verse number="30" style="v"/>and from among your own selves shall men arise, speaking perverse things, to draw away the disciples after them. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Wherefore watch ye, remembering that by the space of three years I ceased not to admonish every one night and day with tears. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And now I commend you to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">the Lord</char>.</char></note>God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build <char style="add">you</char> up, and to give <char style="add">you</char> the inheritance among all them that are sanctified. <verse number="33" style="v"/>I coveted no man&#8217;s silver, or gold, or apparel. <verse number="34" style="v"/>Ye yourselves know that these hands ministered unto my necessities, and to them that were with me. <verse number="35" style="v"/>In all things I gave you an example, that so laboring ye ought to help the weak, and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, that he himself said, It is more blessed to give than to receive.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v"/>And when he had thus spoken, he kneeled down and prayed with them all. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And they all wept sore, and fell on Paul&#8217;s neck and kissed him, <verse number="38" style="v"/>sorrowing most of all for the word which he had spoken, that they should behold his face no more. And they brought him on his way unto the ship.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And when it came to pass that we were parted from them and had set sail, we came with a straight course unto Cos, and the next day unto Rhodes, and from thence unto Patara: <verse number="2" style="v"/>and having found a ship crossing over unto Phoenicia, we went aboard, and set sail. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And when we had come in sight of Cyprus, leaving it on the left hand, we sailed unto Syria, and landed at Tyre; for there the ship was to unlade her burden. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And having found the disciples, we tarried there seven days: and these said to Paul through the Spirit, that he should not set foot in Jerusalem. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And when it came to pass that we had accomplished the days, we departed and went on our journey; and they all, with wives and children, brought us on our way till we were out of the city: and kneeling down on the beach, we prayed, and bade each other farewell; <verse number="6" style="v"/>and we went on board the ship, but they returned home again.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And when we had finished the voyage from Tyre, we arrived at Ptolemais; and we saluted the brethren, and abode with them one day. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And on the morrow we departed, and came unto Caesarea: and entering into the house of Philip the evangelist, who was one of the seven, we abode with him. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Now this man had four virgin daughters, who prophesied. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And as we tarried there some days, there came down from Judaea a certain prophet, named Agabus. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And coming to us, and taking Paul&#8217;s girdle, he bound his own feet and hands, and said, Thus saith the Holy Spirit, So shall the Jews at Jerusalem bind the man that owneth this girdle, and shall deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And when we heard these things, both we and they of that place besought him not to go up to Jerusalem. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Then Paul answered, What do ye, weeping and breaking my heart? for I am ready not to be bound only, but also to die at Jerusalem for the name of the Lord Jesus. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And when he would not be persuaded, we ceased, saying, The will of the Lord be done.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And after these days we <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">made ready</char></char></note>took up our baggage and went up to Jerusalem. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And there went with us also <char style="add">certain</char> of the disciples from Caesarea, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">bringing</char> us to <char style="it">one Mnason etc.</char></char></note>bringing <char style="add">with them</char> one Mnason of Cyprus, an early disciple, with whom we should lodge.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And when we were come to Jerusalem, the brethren received us gladly. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the day following Paul went in with us unto James; and all the elders were present. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And when he had saluted them, he rehearsed one by one the things which God had wrought among the Gentiles through his ministry. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And they, when they heard it, glorified God; and they said unto him, Thou seest, brother, how many <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">myriads</char>.</char></note>thousands there are among the Jews of them that have believed; and they are all zealous for the law: <verse number="21" style="v"/>and they have been informed concerning thee, that thou teachest all the Jews who are among the Gentiles to forsake Moses, telling them not to circumcise their children, neither to walk after the customs. <verse number="22" style="v"/>What is it therefore? they will certainly hear that thou art come. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Do therefore this that we say to thee: We have four men that have a vow on them; <verse number="24" style="v"/>these take, and purify thyself with them, and be at charges for them, that they may shave their heads: and all shall know that there is no truth in the things whereof they have been informed concerning thee; but that thou thyself also walkest orderly, keeping the law. <verse number="25" style="v"/>But as touching the Gentiles that have believed, we <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">enjoined</char>. Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">sent</char>.</char></note>wrote, giving judgment that they should keep themselves from things sacrificed to idols, and from blood, and from what is strangled, and from fornication. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Then Paul <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">took the men the next day, and purifying himself etc.</char></char></note>took the men, and the next day purifying himself with them went into the temple, declaring the fulfilment of the days of purification, until the offering was offered for every one of them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v"/>And when the seven days were almost completed, the Jews from Asia, when they saw him in the temple, stirred up all the multitude and laid hands on him, <verse number="28" style="v"/>crying out, Men of Israel, help: This is the man that teacheth all men everywhere against the people, and the law, and this place; and moreover he brought Greeks also into the temple, and hath defiled this holy place. <verse number="29" style="v"/>For they had before seen with him in the city Trophimus the Ephesian, whom they supposed that Paul had brought into the temple. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And all the city was moved, and the people ran together; and they laid hold on Paul, and dragged him out of the temple: and straightway the doors were shut. <verse number="31" style="v"/>And as they were seeking to kill him, tidings came up to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cohort</char></char></note>band, that all Jerusalem was in confusion. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And forthwith he took soldiers and centurions, and ran down upon them: and they, when they saw the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain and the soldiers, left off beating Paul. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Then the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain came near, and laid hold on him, and commanded him to be bound with two chains; and inquired who he was, and what he had done. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And some shouted one thing, some another, among the crowd: and when he could not know the certainty for the uproar, he commanded him to be brought into the castle. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And when he came upon the stairs, so it was that he was borne of the soldiers for the violence of the crowd; <verse number="36" style="v"/>for the multitude of the people followed after, crying out, Away with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v"/>And as Paul was about to be brought into the castle, he saith unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain, May I say something unto thee? And he said, Dost thou know Greek? <verse number="38" style="v"/>Art thou not then the Egyptian, who before these days stirred up to sedition and led out into the wilderness the four thousand men of the Assassins? <verse number="39" style="v"/>But Paul said, I am a Jew, of Tarsus in Cilicia, a citizen of no mean city: and I beseech thee, give me leave to speak unto the people. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And when he had given him leave, Paul, standing on the stairs, beckoned with the hand unto the people; and when there was made a great silence, he spake unto them in the Hebrew language, saying,</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Brethren and fathers, hear ye the defence which I now make unto you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>And when they heard that he spake unto them in the Hebrew language, they were the more quiet: and he saith,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>I am a Jew, born in Tarsus of Cilicia, but brought up in this city, at the feet of Gamaliel, instructed according to the strict manner of the law of our fathers, being zealous for God, even as ye all are this day: <verse number="4" style="v"/>and I persecuted this Way unto the death, binding and delivering into prisons both men and women. <verse number="5" style="v"/>As also the high priest doth bear me witness, and all the estate of the elders: from whom also I received letters unto the brethren, and journeyed to Damascus to bring them also that were there unto Jerusalem in bonds to be punished. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that, as I made my journey, and drew nigh unto Damascus, about noon, suddenly there shone from heaven a great light round about me. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And I fell unto the ground, and heard a voice saying unto me, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? <verse number="8" style="v"/>And I answered, Who art thou, Lord? And he said unto me, I am Jesus of Nazareth, whom thou persecutest. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And they that were with me beheld indeed the light, but they heard not the voice of him that spake to me. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And I said, What shall I do, Lord? And the Lord said unto me, Arise, and go into Damascus; and there it shall be told thee of all things which are appointed for thee to do. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And when I could not see for the glory of that light, being led by the hand of them that were with me I came into Damascus. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And one Ananias, a devout man according to the law, well reported of by all the Jews that dwelt there, <verse number="13" style="v"/>came unto me, and standing by me said unto me, Brother Saul, receive thy sight. And in that very hour I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">received my sight</char> and looked <char style="it">upon him</char>.</char></note>looked up on him. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And he said, The God of our fathers hath appointed thee to know his will, and to see the Righteous One, and to hear a voice from his mouth. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For thou shalt be a witness for him unto all men of what thou hast seen and heard. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And now why tarriest thou? arise, and be baptized, and wash away thy sins, calling on his name. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that, when I had returned to Jerusalem, and while I prayed in the temple, I fell into a trance, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and saw him saying unto me, Make haste, and get thee quickly out of Jerusalem; because they will not receive of thee testimony concerning me. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And I said, Lord, they themselves know that I imprisoned and beat in every synagogue them that believed on thee: <verse number="20" style="v"/>and when the blood of Stephen thy witness was shed, I also was standing by, and consenting, and keeping the garments of them that slew him. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And he said unto me, Depart: for I will send thee forth far hence unto the Gentiles.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>And they gave him audience unto this word; and they lifted up their voice, and said, Away with such a fellow from the earth: for it is not fit that he should live. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And as they cried out, and threw off their garments, and cast dust into the air, <verse number="24" style="v"/>the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain commanded him to be brought into the castle, bidding that he should be examined by scourging, that he might know for what cause they so shouted against him. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And when they had tied him up <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for</char></char></note>with the thongs, Paul said unto the centurion that stood by, Is it lawful for you to scourge a man that is a Roman, and uncondemned? <verse number="26" style="v"/>And when the centurion heard it, he went to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain and told him, saying, What art thou about to do? for this man is a Roman. <verse number="27" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain came and said unto him, Tell me, art thou a Roman? And he said, Yea. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain answered, With a great sum obtained I this citizenship. And Paul said, But I am <char style="add">a Roman</char> born. <verse number="29" style="v"/>They then that were about to examine him straightway departed from him: and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain also was afraid when he knew that he was a Roman, and because he had bound him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>But on the morrow, desiring to know the certainty wherefore he was accused of the Jews, he loosed him, and commanded the chief priests and all the council to come together, and brought Paul down and set him before them.</para>
	<chapter number="23" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Paul, looking stedfastly on the council, said, Brethren, I have lived before God in all good conscience until this day. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the high priest Ananias commanded them that stood by him to smite him on the mouth. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Then said Paul unto him, God shall smite thee, thou whited wall: and sittest thou to judge me according to the law, and commandest me to be smitten contrary to the law? <verse number="4" style="v"/>And they that stood by said, Revilest thou God&#8217;s high priest? <verse number="5" style="v"/>And Paul said, I knew not, brethren, that he was high priest: for it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="EXO 22:28">Ex. 22:28</ref>.</char></note>Thou shalt not speak evil of a ruler of thy people. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But when Paul perceived that the one part were Sadducees and the other Pharisees, he cried out in the council, Brethren, I am a Pharisee, a son of Pharisees: touching the hope and resurrection of the dead I am called in question. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And when he had so said, there arose a dissension between the Pharisees and Sadducees; and the assembly was divided. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For the Sadducees say that there is no resurrection, neither angel, nor spirit; but the Pharisees confess both. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And there arose a great clamor: and some of the scribes of the Pharisees&#8217; part stood up, and strove, saying, We find no evil in this man: and what if a spirit hath spoken to him, or an angel? <verse number="10" style="v"/>And when there arose a great dissension, the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain, fearing lest Paul should be torn in pieces by them, commanded the soldiers to go down and take him by force from among them, and bring him into the castle.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And the night following the Lord stood by him, and said, Be of good cheer: for as thou hast testified concerning me at Jerusalem, so must thou bear witness also at Rome.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And when it was day, the Jews banded together, and bound themselves under a curse, saying that they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed Paul. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And they were more than forty that made this conspiracy. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And they came to the chief priests and the elders, and said, We have bound ourselves under a great curse, to taste nothing until we have killed Paul. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Now therefore do ye with the council signify to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain that he bring him down unto you, as though ye would judge of his case more exactly: and we, before he comes near, are ready to slay him. <verse number="16" style="v"/>But Paul&#8217;s sister&#8217;s son heard of their lying in wait, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">having come in</char> upon them, <char style="it">and he entered etc.</char></char></note>and he came and entered into the castle and told Paul. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And Paul called unto him one of the centurions, and said, Bring this young man unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain; for he hath something to tell him. <verse number="18" style="v"/>So he took him, and brought him to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain, and saith, Paul the prisoner called me unto him, and asked me to bring this young man unto thee, who hath something to say to thee. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain took him by the hand, and going aside asked him privately, What is it that thou hast to tell me? <verse number="20" style="v"/>And he said, The Jews have agreed to ask thee to bring down Paul to-morrow unto the council, as though thou wouldest inquire somewhat more exactly concerning him. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Do not thou therefore yield unto them: for there lie in wait for him of them more than forty men, who have bound themselves under a curse, neither to eat nor to drink till they have slain him: and now are they ready, looking for the promise from thee. <verse number="22" style="v"/>So the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain let the young man go, charging him, Tell no man that thou hast signified these things to me. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he called unto him two of the centurions, and said, Make ready two hundred soldiers to go as far as Caesarea, and horsemen threescore and ten, and spearmen two hundred, at the third hour of the night: <verse number="24" style="v"/>and <char style="add">he bade them</char> provide beasts, that they might set Paul thereon, and bring him safe unto Felix the governor. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And he wrote a letter after this form:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>Claudius Lysias unto the most excellent governor Felix, greeting. <verse number="27" style="v"/>This man was seized by the Jews, and was about to be slain of them, when I came upon them with the soldiers and rescued him, having learned that he was a Roman. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And desiring to know the cause wherefore they accused him, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">I brought him down unto their council</char>.</char></note>I brought him down unto their council: <verse number="29" style="v"/>whom I found to be accused about questions of their law, but to have nothing laid to his charge worthy of death or of bonds. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And when it was shown to me that there would be a plot <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">against the man on their part, I sent him to thee, charging etc.</char></char></note>against the man, I sent him to thee forthwith, charging his accusers also to speak against him before thee. <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities add <char style="it">Farewell</char>.</char></note></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>So the soldiers, as it was commanded them, took Paul and brought him by night to Antipatris. <verse number="32" style="v"/>But on the morrow they left the horsemen to go with him, and returned to the castle: <verse number="33" style="v"/>and they, when they came to Caesarea and delivered the letter to the governor, presented Paul also before him. <verse number="34" style="v"/>And when he had read it, he asked of what province he was; and when he understood that he was of Cilicia, <verse number="35" style="v"/>I will hear thee fully, said he, when thine accusers also are come: and he commanded him to be kept in Herod&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Praetorium</char>.</char></note>palace.</para>
	<chapter number="24" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And after five days the high priest Ananias came down with certain elders, and <char style="add">with</char> an orator, one Tertullus; and they informed the governor against Paul. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And when he was called, Tertullus began to accuse him, saying,</para>
	<para style="p">Seeing that by thee we enjoy much peace, and that by thy providence evils are corrected for this nation, <verse number="3" style="v"/>we accept it in all ways and in all places, most excellent Felix, with all thankfulness. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But, that I be not further tedious unto thee, I entreat thee to hear us of thy clemency a few words. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For we have found this man a pestilent fellow, and a mover of insurrections among all the Jews throughout <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>the world, and a ringleader of the sect of the Nazarenes: <verse number="6" style="v"/>who moreover assayed to profane the temple: on whom also we laid hold: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities insert <char style="it">and we would have judged him according to our law.</char> <char style="fv">7</char><char style="it">But the chief captain Lysias came, and with great violence took him away out of our hands,</char> <char style="fv">8</char><char style="it">commanding his accusers to come before thee</char>.</char></note> <verse number="8" style="v"/>from whom thou wilt be able, by examining him thyself, to take knowledge of all these things whereof we accuse him. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the Jews also joined in the charge, affirming that these things were so.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And when the governor had beckoned unto him to speak, Paul answered,</para>
	<para style="p">Forasmuch as I know that thou hast been of many years a judge unto this nation, I cheerfully make my defence: <verse number="11" style="v"/>seeing that thou canst take knowledge that it is not more than twelve days since I went up to worship at Jerusalem: <verse number="12" style="v"/>and neither in the temple did they find me disputing with any man or stirring up a crowd, nor in the synagogues, nor in the city. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Neither can they prove to thee the things whereof they now accuse me. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But this I confess unto thee, that after the Way which they call a sect, so serve I the God of our fathers, believing all things which are according to the law, and which are written in the prophets; <verse number="15" style="v"/>having hope toward God, which these also themselves <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">accept</char></char></note>look for, that there shall be a resurrection both of the just and unjust. <verse number="16" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">On this account</char></char></note>Herein I also exercise myself to have a conscience void of offence toward God and men always. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Now after some years I came to bring alms to my nation, and offerings: <verse number="18" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char> presenting <char style="it">which</char></char></note>amidst which they found me purified in the temple, with no crowd, nor yet with tumult: but <char style="add">there were</char> certain Jews from Asia&#8212;<verse number="19" style="v"/>who ought to have been here before thee, and to make accusation, if they had aught against me. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Or else let these men themselves say what wrong-doing they found when I stood before the council, <verse number="21" style="v"/>except it be for this one voice, that I cried standing among them, Touching the resurrection of the dead I am called in question before you this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>But Felix, having more exact knowledge concerning the Way, deferred them, saying, When Lysias the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribune</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarch</char>.</char></note>chief captain shall come down, I will determine your matter. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And he gave order to the centurion that he should be kept in charge, and should have indulgence; and not to forbid any of his friends to minister unto him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>But after certain days, Felix came with Drusilla, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">his own wife</char>.</char></note>his wife, who was a Jewess, and sent for Paul, and heard him concerning the faith in Christ Jesus. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And as he reasoned of righteousness, and self-control, and the judgment to come, Felix was terrified, and answered, Go thy way for this time; and when I have a convenient season, I will call thee unto me. <verse number="26" style="v"/>He hoped withal that money would be given him of Paul: wherefore also he sent for him the oftener, and communed with him. <verse number="27" style="v"/>But when two years were fulfilled, Felix was succeeded by Porcius Festus; and desiring to gain favor with the Jews, Felix left Paul in bonds.</para>
	<chapter number="25" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Festus therefore, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">having entered upon his province</char></char></note>having come into the province, after three days went up to Jerusalem from Caesarea. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the chief priests and the principal men of the Jews informed him against Paul; and they besought him, <verse number="3" style="v"/>asking a favor against him, that he would send for him to Jerusalem; laying a plot to kill him on the way. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Howbeit Festus answered, that Paul was kept in charge at Caesarea, and that he himself was about to depart <char style="add">thither</char> shortly. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Let them therefore, saith he, that are of power among you go down with me, and if there is anything amiss in the man, let them accuse him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And when he had tarried among them not more than eight or ten days, he went down unto Caesarea; and on the morrow he sat on the judgment-seat, and commanded Paul to be brought. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And when he was come, the Jews that had come down from Jerusalem stood round about him, bringing against him many and grievous charges which they could not prove; <verse number="8" style="v"/>while Paul said in his defence, Neither against the law of the Jews, nor against the temple, nor against Caesar, have I sinned at all. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But Festus, desiring to gain favor with the Jews, answered Paul and said, Wilt thou go up to Jerusalem, and there be judged of these things before me? <verse number="10" style="v"/>But Paul said, I am standing before Caesar&#8217;s judgment-seat, where I ought to be judged: to the Jews have I done no wrong, as thou also very well knowest. <verse number="11" style="v"/>If then I am a wrong-doer, and have committed anything worthy of death, I refuse not to die; but if none of those things is <char style="add">true</char> whereof these accuse me, no man can <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">grant me by favor</char>.</char></note>give me up unto them. I appeal unto Caesar. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Then Festus, when he had conferred with the council, answered, Thou hast appealed unto Caesar: unto Caesar shalt thou go.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>Now when certain days were passed, Agrippa the king and Bernice arrived at Caesarea, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">having saluted</char></char></note>and saluted Festus. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And as they tarried there many days, Festus laid Paul&#8217;s case before the king, saying, There is a certain man left a prisoner by Felix; <verse number="15" style="v"/>about whom, when I was at Jerusalem, the chief priests and the elders of the Jews informed <char style="add">me</char>, asking for sentence against him. <verse number="16" style="v"/>To whom I answered, that it is not the custom of the Romans to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">grant me by favor</char>.</char></note>give up any man, before that the accused have the accusers face to face, and have had opportunity to make his defence concerning the matter laid against him. <verse number="17" style="v"/>When therefore they were come together here, I made no delay, but on the next day sat on the judgment-seat, and commanded the man to be brought. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Concerning whom, when the accusers stood up, they brought no charge of such evil things as I supposed; <verse number="19" style="v"/>but had certain questions against him of their own <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">superstition</char></char></note>religion, and of one Jesus, who was dead, whom Paul affirmed to be alive. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And I, being perplexed how to inquire concerning these things, asked whether he would go to Jerusalem and there be judged of these matters. <verse number="21" style="v"/>But when Paul had appealed to be kept for the decision of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the Augustus</char>.</char></note>the emperor, I commanded him to be kept till I should send him to Caesar. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And Agrippa <char style="add">said</char> unto Festus, I also <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">was wishing</char></char></note>could wish to hear the man myself. To-morrow, saith he, thou shalt hear him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>So on the morrow, when Agrippa was come, and Bernice, with great pomp, and they were entered into the place of hearing with the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribunes</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarchs</char>.</char></note>chief captains and the principal men of the city, at the command of Festus Paul was brought in. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And Festus saith, King Agrippa, and all men who are here present with us, ye behold this man, about whom all the multitude of the Jews made suit to me, both at Jerusalem and here, crying that he ought not to live any longer. <verse number="25" style="v"/>But I found that he had committed nothing worthy of death: and as he himself appealed to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the Augustus</char>.</char></note>the emperor I determined to send him. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Of whom I have no certain thing to write unto my lord. Wherefore I have brought him forth before you, and specially before thee, king Agrippa, that, after examination had, I may have somewhat to write. <verse number="27" style="v"/>For it seemeth to me unreasonable, in sending a prisoner, not withal to signify the charges against him.</para>
	<chapter number="26" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And Agrippa said unto Paul, Thou art permitted to speak for thyself. Then Paul stretched forth his hand, and made his defence:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>I think myself happy, king Agrippa, that I am to make my defence before thee this day touching all the things whereof I am accused by the Jews: <verse number="3" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">because thou art especially expert</char></char></note>especially because thou art expert in all customs and questions which are among the Jews: wherefore I beseech thee to hear me patiently. <verse number="4" style="v"/>My manner of life then from my youth up, which was from the beginning among mine own nation and at Jerusalem, know all the Jews; <verse number="5" style="v"/>having knowledge of me from the first, if they be willing to testify, that after the straitest sect of our religion I lived a Pharisee. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And now I stand <char style="add">here</char> to be judged for the hope of the promise made of God unto our fathers; <verse number="7" style="v"/>unto which <char style="add">promise</char> our twelve tribes, earnestly serving <char style="add">God</char> night and day, hope to attain. And concerning this hope I am accused by the Jews, O king! <verse number="8" style="v"/>Why is it judged incredible with you, if God doth raise the dead? <verse number="9" style="v"/>I verily thought with myself that I ought to do many things contrary to the name of Jesus of Nazareth. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And this I also did in Jerusalem: and I both shut up many of the saints in prisons, having received authority from the chief priests, and when they were put to death I gave my vote against them. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And punishing them oftentimes in all the synagogues, I strove to make them blaspheme; and being exceedingly mad against them, I persecuted them even unto foreign cities. <verse number="12" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">On which errand</char></char></note>Whereupon as I journeyed to Damascus with the authority and commission of the chief priests, <verse number="13" style="v"/>at midday, O king, I saw on the way a light from heaven, above the brightness of the sun, shining round about me and them that journeyed with me. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And when we were all fallen to the earth, I heard a voice saying unto me in the Hebrew language, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? it is hard for thee to kick against <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">goads</char>.</char></note>the goad. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And I said, Who art thou, Lord? And the Lord said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest. <verse number="16" style="v"/>But arise, and stand upon thy feet: for to this end have I appeared unto thee, to appoint thee a minister and a witness both of the things <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">which thou hast seen</char>.</char></note>wherein thou hast seen me, and of the things wherein I will appear unto thee; <verse number="17" style="v"/>delivering thee from the people, and from the Gentiles, unto whom I send thee, <verse number="18" style="v"/>to open their eyes, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to turn them</char></char></note>that they may turn from darkness to light and from the power of Satan unto God, that they may receive remission of sins and an inheritance among them that are sanctified by faith in me. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Wherefore, O king Agrippa, I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision: <verse number="20" style="v"/>but declared both to them of Damascus first, and at Jerusalem, and throughout all the country of Judaea, and also to the Gentiles, that they should repent and turn to God, doing works worthy of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">their repentance</char></char></note>repentance. <verse number="21" style="v"/>For this cause the Jews seized me in the temple, and assayed to kill me. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Having therefore obtained the help that is from God, I stand unto this day testifying both to small and great, saying nothing but what the prophets and Moses did say should come; <verse number="23" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">if</char>. Or, <char style="it">whether</char></char></note>how that the Christ <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">is subject to suffering</char></char></note>must suffer, <char style="add">and</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">if</char>. Or, <char style="it">whether</char></char></note>how that he first by the resurrection of the dead should proclaim light both to the people and to the Gentiles.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>And as he thus made his defence, Festus saith with a loud voice, Paul, thou art mad; thy much learning <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">turneth thee to madness</char>.</char></note>is turning thee mad. <verse number="25" style="v"/>But Paul saith, I am not mad, most excellent Festus; but speak forth words of truth and soberness. <verse number="26" style="v"/>For the king knoweth of these things, unto whom also I speak freely: for I am persuaded that none of these things is hidden from him; for this hath not been done in a corner. <verse number="27" style="v"/>King Agrippa, believest thou the prophets? I know that thou believest. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And Agrippa <char style="add">said</char> unto Paul, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">In a little</char> time <char style="it">thou etc.</char></char></note>With but little persuasion thou wouldest fain make me a Christian. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And Paul <char style="add">said</char>, I would to God, that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">both in little and in great</char>, i.e., in all respects</char></note>whether with little or with much, not thou only, but also all that hear me this day, might become such as I am, except these bonds.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>And the king rose up, and the governor, and Bernice, and they that sat with them: <verse number="31" style="v"/>and when they had withdrawn, they spake one to another, saying, This man doeth nothing worthy of death or of bonds. <verse number="32" style="v"/>And Agrippa said unto Festus, This man might have been set at liberty, if he had not appealed unto Caesar.</para>
	<chapter number="27" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And when it was determined that we should sail for Italy, they delivered Paul and certain other prisoners to a centurion named Julius, of the Augustan <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cohort</char></char></note>band. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And embarking in a ship of Adramyttium, which was about to sail unto the places on the coast of Asia, we put to sea, Aristarchus, a Macedonian of Thessalonica, being with us. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And the next day we touched at Sidon: and Julius treated Paul kindly, and gave him leave to go unto his friends and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">receive attention</char>.</char></note>refresh himself. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And putting to sea from thence, we sailed under the lee of Cyprus, because the winds were contrary. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And when we had sailed across the sea which is off Cilicia and Pamphylia, we came to Myra, <char style="add">a city</char> of Lycia. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And there the centurion found a ship of Alexandria sailing for Italy; and he put us therein. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And when we had sailed slowly many days, and were come with difficulty over against Cnidus, the wind not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">suffering us to get there</char></char></note>further suffering us, we sailed under the lee of Crete, over against Salmone; <verse number="8" style="v"/>and with difficulty coasting along it we came unto a certain place called Fair Havens; nigh whereunto was the city of Lasea.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And when much time was spent, and the voyage was now dangerous, because the Fast was now already gone by, Paul admonished them, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and said unto them, Sirs, I perceive that the voyage will be with injury and much loss, not only of the lading and the ship, but also of our lives. <verse number="11" style="v"/>But the centurion gave more heed to the master and to the owner of the ship, than to those things which were spoken by Paul. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And because the haven was not commodious to winter in, the more part advised to put to sea from thence, if by any means they could reach Phoenix, and winter <char style="add">there; which is</char> a haven of Crete, looking <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">down the south-west wind and down the north-west wind</char>.</char></note>north-east and south-east. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And when the south wind blew softly, supposing that they had obtained their purpose, they weighed anchor and sailed along Crete, close in shore. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But after no long time there beat down from it a tempestuous wind, which is called Euraquilo: <verse number="15" style="v"/>and when the ship was caught, and could not face the wind, we gave way <char style="add">to it</char>, and were driven. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And running under the lee of a small island called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">Clauda</char>.</char></note>Cauda, we were able, with difficulty, to secure the boat: <verse number="17" style="v"/>and when they had hoisted it up, they used helps, under-girding the ship; and, fearing lest they should be cast upon the Syrtis, they lowered the gear, and so were driven. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And as we labored exceedingly with the storm, the next day they began to throw <char style="add">the freight</char> overboard; <verse number="19" style="v"/>and the third day they cast out with their own hands the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">furniture</char></char></note>tackling of the ship. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And when neither sun nor stars shone upon <char style="add">us</char> for many days, and no small tempest lay on <char style="add">us</char>, all hope that we should be saved was now taken away. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And when they had been long without food, then Paul stood forth in the midst of them, and said, Sirs, ye should have hearkened unto me, and not have set sail from Crete, and have gotten this injury and loss. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And now I exhort you to be of good cheer; for there shall be no loss of life among you, but <char style="add">only</char> of the ship. <verse number="23" style="v"/>For there stood by me this night an angel of the God whose I am, whom also I serve, <verse number="24" style="v"/>saying, Fear not, Paul; thou must stand before Caesar: and lo, God hath granted thee all them that sail with thee. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Wherefore, sirs, be of good cheer: for I believe God, that it shall be even so as it hath been spoken unto me. <verse number="26" style="v"/>But we must be cast upon a certain island.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v"/>But when the fourteenth night was come, as we were driven to and fro in the <char style="add">sea of</char> Adria, about midnight the sailors surmised that they were drawing near to some country: <verse number="28" style="v"/>and they sounded, and found twenty fathoms; and after a little space, they sounded again, and found fifteen fathoms. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And fearing lest haply we should be cast ashore on rocky ground, they let go four anchors from the stern, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">prayed</char></char></note>wished for the day. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And as the sailors were seeking to flee out of the ship, and had lowered the boat into the sea, under color as though they would lay out anchors from the foreship, <verse number="31" style="v"/>Paul said to the centurion and to the soldiers, Except these abide in the ship, ye cannot be saved. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Then the soldiers cut away the ropes of the boat, and let her fall off. <verse number="33" style="v"/>And while the day was coming on, Paul besought them all to take some food, saying, This day is the fourteenth day that ye wait and continue fasting, having taken nothing. <verse number="34" style="v"/>Wherefore I beseech you to take some food: for this is for your safety: for there shall not a hair perish from the head of any of you. <verse number="35" style="v"/>And when he had said this, and had taken bread, he gave thanks to God in the presence of all; and he brake it, and began to eat. <verse number="36" style="v"/>Then were they all of good cheer, and themselves also took food. <verse number="37" style="v"/>And we were in all in the ship two hundred threescore and sixteen souls. <verse number="38" style="v"/>And when they had eaten enough, they lightened the ship, throwing out the wheat into the sea. <verse number="39" style="v"/>And when it was day, they knew not the land: but they perceived a certain bay with a beach, and they took counsel whether they could <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">bring the ship safe to shore</char>.</char></note>drive the ship upon it. <verse number="40" style="v"/>And casting off the anchors, they left them in the sea, at the same time loosing the bands of the rudders; and hoisting up the foresail to the wind, they made for the beach. <verse number="41" style="v"/>But lighting upon a place where two seas met, they ran the vessel aground; and the foreship struck and remained unmoveable, but the stern began to break up by the violence <char style="add">of the waves</char>. <verse number="42" style="v"/>And the soldiers&#8217; counsel was to kill the prisoners, lest any <char style="add">of them</char> should swim out, and escape. <verse number="43" style="v"/>But the centurion, desiring to save Paul, stayed them from their purpose; and commanded that they who could swim should cast themselves overboard, and get first to the land; <verse number="44" style="v"/>and the rest, some on planks, and some on <char style="add">other</char> things from the ship. And so it came to pass, that they all escaped safe to the land.</para>
	<chapter number="28" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And when we were escaped, then we knew that the island was called <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">Melitene</char>.</char></note>Melita. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the barbarians showed us no common kindness: for they kindled a fire, and received us all, because of the present rain, and because of the cold. <verse number="3" style="v"/>But when Paul had gathered a bundle of sticks and laid them on the fire, a viper came out <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">from the heat</char></char></note>by reason of the heat, and fastened on his hand. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And when the barbarians saw the <char style="add">venomous</char> creature hanging from his hand, they said one to another, No doubt this man is a murderer, whom, though he hath escaped from the sea, yet Justice hath not suffered to live. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Howbeit he shook off the creature into the fire, and took no harm. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But they expected that he would have swollen, or fallen down dead suddenly: but when they were long in expectation and beheld nothing amiss came to him, they changed their minds, and said that he was a god.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>Now in the neighborhood of that place were lands belonging to the chief man of the island, named Publius; who received us, and entertained us three days courteously. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And it was so, that the father of Publius lay sick of fever and dysentery: unto whom Paul entered in, and prayed, and laying his hands on him healed him. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And when this was done, the rest also that had diseases in the island came, and were cured: <verse number="10" style="v"/>who also honored us with many honors; and when we sailed, they put on board such things as we needed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And after three months we set sail in a ship of Alexandria which had wintered in the island, whose sign was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Dioscuri</char>.</char></note>The Twin Brothers. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And touching at Syracuse, we tarried there three days. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And from thence we <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">cast loose</char>.</char></note>made a circuit, and arrived at Rhegium: and after one day a south wind sprang up, and on the second day we came to Puteoli; <verse number="14" style="v"/>where we found brethren, and were entreated to tarry with them seven days: and so we came to Rome. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And from thence the brethren, when they heard of us, came to meet us as far as The Market of Appius and The Three Taverns; whom when Paul saw, he thanked God, and took courage.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And when we entered into Rome, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities insert <char style="it">the centurion delivered the prisoners to the Chief of the camp: but etc.</char></char></note>Paul was suffered to abide by himself with the soldier that guarded him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And it came to pass, that after three days he called together <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">those that were of the Jews first</char></char></note>those that were the chief of the Jews: and when they were come together, he said unto them, I, brethren, though I had done nothing against the people, or the customs of our fathers, yet was delivered prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans: <verse number="18" style="v"/>who, when they had examined me, desired to set me at liberty, because there was no cause of death in me. <verse number="19" style="v"/>But when the Jews spake against it, I was constrained to appeal unto Caesar; not that I had aught whereof to accuse my nation. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For this cause therefore did I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">call for you, to see and to speak with</char> you</char></note>entreat you to see and to speak with <char style="add">me</char>: for because of the hope of Israel I am bound with this chain. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And they said unto him, We neither received letters from Judaea concerning thee, nor did any of the brethren come hither and report or speak any harm of thee. <verse number="22" style="v"/>But we desire to hear of thee what thou thinkest: for as concerning this sect, it is known to us that everywhere it is spoken against.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>And when they had appointed him a day, they came to him into his lodging in great number; to whom he expounded <char style="add">the matter</char>, testifying the kingdom of God, and persuading them concerning Jesus, both from the law of Moses and from the prophets, from morning till evening. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And some believed the things which were spoken, and some disbelieved. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And when they agreed not among themselves, they departed after that Paul had spoken one word, Well spake the Holy Spirit through Isaiah the prophet unto your fathers, <verse number="26" style="v"/>saying,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 6:9">Isa. 6:9</ref>, <ref loc="ISA 6:10">10</ref>.</char></note>Go thou unto this people, and say,</para>
	<para style="q1">By hearing ye shall hear, and shall in no wise understand;</para>
	<para style="q1">And seeing ye shall see, and shall in no wise perceive:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="27" style="v"/>For this people&#8217;s heart is waxed gross,</para>
	<para style="q1">And their ears are dull of hearing,</para>
	<para style="q1">And their eyes they have closed;</para>
	<para style="q1">Lest haply they should perceive with their eyes,</para>
	<para style="q1">And hear with their ears,</para>
	<para style="q1">And understand with their heart,</para>
	<para style="q1">And should turn again,</para>
	<para style="q1">And I should heal them.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="28" style="v"/>Be it known therefore unto you, that this salvation of God is sent unto the Gentiles: they will also hear.<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities insert <ref loc="ACT 28:29">verse 29</ref> <char style="it">And when he had said these words, the Jews departed, having much disputing among themselves</char>.</char></note></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>And he abode two whole years in his own hired dwelling, and received all that went in unto him, <verse number="31" style="v"/>preaching the kingdom of God, and teaching the things concerning the Lord Jesus Christ with all boldness, none forbidding him.</para>
</usx>