<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="ROM" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Paul, a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant of Jesus Christ, called <char style="add">to be</char> an apostle, separated unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>: and so elsewhere. See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref>.</char></note>gospel of God, <verse number="2" style="v"/>which he promised afore through his prophets in the holy scriptures, <verse number="3" style="v"/>concerning his Son, who was born of the seed of David according to the flesh, <verse number="4" style="v"/>who was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">determined</char>.</char></note>declared <char style="add">to be</char> the Son of God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char></char></note>with power, according to the spirit of holiness, by the resurrection <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of the dead</char></char></note>from the dead; <char style="add">even</char> Jesus Christ our Lord, <verse number="5" style="v"/>through whom we received grace and apostleship, unto obedience <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to the faith</char></char></note>of faith among all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gentiles</char></char></note>nations, for his name&#8217;s sake; <verse number="6" style="v"/>among whom are ye also, called <char style="add">to be</char> Jesus Christ&#8217;s: <verse number="7" style="v"/>to all that are in Rome, beloved of God, called <char style="add">to be</char> saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">because</char></char></note>that your faith is proclaimed throughout the whole world. <verse number="9" style="v"/>For God is my witness, whom I serve in my spirit in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="ROM 1:1">verse 1</ref>.</char></note>gospel of his Son, how unceasingly I make mention of you, always in my prayers <verse number="10" style="v"/>making request, if by any means now at length I may be prospered <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in</char>.</char></note>by the will of God to come unto you. <verse number="11" style="v"/>For I long to see you, that I may impart unto you some spiritual gift, to the end ye may be established; <verse number="12" style="v"/>that is, that I with you may be comforted <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">among</char></char></note>in you, each of us by the other&#8217;s faith, both yours and mine. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that oftentimes I purposed to come unto you (and was hindered hitherto), that I might have some fruit <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">among</char></char></note>in you also, even as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">among</char></char></note>in the rest of the Gentiles. <verse number="14" style="v"/>I am debtor both to Greeks and to Barbarians, both to the wise and to the foolish. <verse number="15" style="v"/>So, as much as in me is, I am ready to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bring good tidings</char>. Compare <ref loc="ROM 10:15-10:21">10:15f</ref>.</char></note>preach the gospel to you also that are in Rome.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>For I am not ashamed of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="ROM 1:1">verse 1</ref>.</char></note>gospel: for it is the power of God unto salvation to every one that believeth; to the Jew first, and also to the Greek. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For therein is revealed a righteousness of God from faith unto faith: as it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="HAB 2:4">Hab. 2:4</ref>.</char></note>But the righteous shall live <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">from</char>.</char></note>by faith.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>For <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a wrath</char></char></note>the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men, who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hold the truth</char>. Compare <ref loc="1CO 7:30">1 Cor. 7:30</ref> (Greek).</char></note>hinder the truth in unrighteousness; <verse number="19" style="v"/>because that which is known of God is manifest in them; for God manifested it unto them. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For the invisible things of him since the creation of the world are clearly seen, being perceived through the things that are made, <char style="add">even</char> his everlasting power and divinity; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">so that they are</char></char></note>that they may be without excuse: <verse number="21" style="v"/>because that, knowing God, they glorified him not as God, neither gave thanks; but became vain in their reasonings, and their senseless heart was darkened. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Professing themselves to be wise, they became fools, <verse number="23" style="v"/>and changed the glory of the incorruptible God for the likeness of an image of corruptible man, and of birds, and four-footed beasts, and creeping things.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>Wherefore God gave them up in the lusts of their hearts unto uncleanness, that their bodies should be dishonored among themselves: <verse number="25" style="v"/>for that they exchanged the truth of God for a lie, and worshipped and served the creature rather than the Creator, who is blessed <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever. Amen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>For this cause God gave them up unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">passions of dishonor</char>.</char></note>vile passions: for their women changed the natural use into that which is against nature: <verse number="27" style="v"/>and likewise also the men, leaving the natural use of the woman, burned in their lust one toward another, men with men working unseemliness, and receiving in themselves that recompense of their error which was due.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v"/>And even as they <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">did not approve</char>.</char></note>refused to have God in <char style="add">their</char> knowledge, God gave them up unto a reprobate mind, to do those things which are not fitting; <verse number="29" style="v"/>being filled with all unrighteousness, wickedness, covetousness, maliciousness; full of envy, murder, strife, deceit, malignity; whisperers, <verse number="30" style="v"/>backbiters, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">haters of God</char></char></note>hateful to God, insolent, haughty, boastful, inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents, <verse number="31" style="v"/>without understanding, covenant-breakers, without natural affection, unmerciful: <verse number="32" style="v"/>who, knowing the ordinance of God, that they that practise such things are worthy of death, not only do the same, but also consent with them that practise them.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Wherefore thou art without excuse, O man, whosoever thou art that judgest: for wherein thou judgest <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the other</char>.</char></note>another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest dost practise the same things. <verse number="2" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">For</char>.</char></note>And we know that the judgment of God is according to truth against them that practise such things. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And reckonest thou this, O man, who judgest them that practise such things, and doest the same, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God? <verse number="4" style="v"/>Or despisest thou the riches of his goodness and forbearance and longsuffering, not knowing that the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance? <verse number="5" style="v"/>but after thy hardness and impenitent heart treasurest up for thyself wrath in the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God; <verse number="6" style="v"/>who will render to every man according to his works: <verse number="7" style="v"/>to them that by <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience in well-doing seek for glory and honor and incorruption, eternal life: <verse number="8" style="v"/>but unto them that are factious, and obey not the truth, but obey unrighteousness, <char style="add">shall be</char> wrath and indignation, <verse number="9" style="v"/>tribulation and anguish, upon every soul of man that worketh evil, of the Jew first, and also of the Greek; <verse number="10" style="v"/>but glory and honor and peace to every man that worketh good, to the Jew first, and also to the Greek: <verse number="11" style="v"/>for there is no respect of persons with God. <verse number="12" style="v"/>For as many as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sinned</char>.</char></note>have sinned without the law shall also perish without the law: and as many as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sinned</char>.</char></note>have sinned under the law shall be judged by the law; <verse number="13" style="v"/>for not the hearers of the law are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">righteous</char></char></note>just before God, but the doers of the law shall be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">accounted righteous</char>: and so elsewhere.</char></note>justified; <verse number="14" style="v"/>(for when Gentiles that have not the law do by nature the things of the law, these, not having the law, are the law unto themselves; <verse number="15" style="v"/>in that they show the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience bearing witness therewith, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">their thoughts accusing or else excusing</char> them <char style="it">one with another</char></char></note>their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">reasonings</char>. <ref loc="2CO 10:5">2 Cor. 10:5</ref></char></note>thoughts one with another accusing or else excusing <char style="add">them</char>); <verse number="16" style="v"/>in the day when God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">judgeth</char></char></note>shall judge the secrets of men, according to my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ROM 1:1">1:1</ref>.</char></note>gospel, by Jesus Christ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>But if thou bearest the name of a Jew, and restest upon the law, and gloriest in God, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and knowest <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the Will</char></char></note>his will, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">dost distinguish the things that differ</char></char></note>approvest the things that are excellent, being instructed out of the law, <verse number="19" style="v"/>and art confident that thou thyself art a guide of the blind, a light of them that are in darkness, <verse number="20" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">an instructor</char></char></note>a corrector of the foolish, a teacher of babes, having in the law the form of knowledge and of the truth; <verse number="21" style="v"/>thou therefore that teachest another, teachest thou not thyself? thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal? <verse number="22" style="v"/>thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou rob temples? <verse number="23" style="v"/>thou who gloriest in the law, through thy transgression of the law dishonorest thou God? <verse number="24" style="v"/>For the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles because of you, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 52:5">Isa. 52:5</ref>.</char></note>even as it is written. <verse number="25" style="v"/>For circumcision indeed profiteth, if thou be a doer of the law: but if thou be a transgressor of the law, thy circumcision is become uncircumcision. <verse number="26" style="v"/>If therefore the uncircumcision keep the ordinances of the law, shall not his uncircumcision be reckoned for circumcision? <verse number="27" style="v"/>and shall not the uncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfil the law, judge thee, who with the letter and circumcision art a transgressor of the law? <verse number="28" style="v"/>For he is not a Jew who is one outwardly; neither is that circumcision which is outward in the flesh: <verse number="29" style="v"/>but he is a Jew who is one inwardly; and circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit not in the letter; whose praise is not of men, but of God.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>What advantage then hath the Jew? or what is the profit of circumcision? <verse number="2" style="v"/>Much every way: first of all, that they were intrusted with the oracles of God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For what if some were without faith? shall their want of faith make of none effect the faithfulness of God? <verse number="4" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Be it not so</char>: and so elsewhere.</char></note>God forbid: yea, let God be found true, but every man a liar; as it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 51:4">Ps. 51:4</ref>.</char></note>That thou mightest be justified in thy words,</para>
	<para style="q1">And mightest prevail when thou comest into judgment.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="5" style="v"/>But if our unrighteousness commendeth the righteousness of God, what shall we say? Is God unrighteous who visiteth with wrath? (I speak after the manner of men.) <verse number="6" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Be it not so</char>: and so elsewhere.</char></note>God forbid: for then how shall God judge the world? <verse number="7" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">For</char>.</char></note>But if the truth of God through my lie abounded unto his glory, why am I also still judged as a sinner? <verse number="8" style="v"/>and why not (as we are slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say), Let us do evil, that good may come? whose condemnation is just.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>What then? are we better than they? No, in no wise: for we before laid to the charge both of Jews and Greeks, that they are all under sin; <verse number="10" style="v"/>as it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 14">Ps. 14:1ff</ref>; <ref loc="PSA 53">53:1ff</ref>.</char></note>There is none righteous, no, not one;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="11" style="v"/>There is none that understandeth,</para>
	<para style="q1">There is none that seeketh after God;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="12" style="v"/>They have all turned aside, they are together become unprofitable;</para>
	<para style="q1">There is none that doeth good, no, not so much as one:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="13" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 5:9">Ps. 5:9</ref>.</char></note>Their throat is an open sepulchre;</para>
	<para style="q1">With their tongues they have used deceit:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 140:3">Ps. 140:3</ref>.</char></note>The poison of asps is under their lips:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="14" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 10:7">Ps. 10:7</ref>.</char></note>Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="15" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 59:7-59:21">Isa. 59:7f</ref>.</char></note>Their feet are swift to shed blood;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="16" style="v"/>Destruction and misery are in their ways;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And the way of peace have they not known:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="18" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 36:1">Ps. 36:1</ref>.</char></note>There is no fear of God before their eyes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>Now we know that what things soever the law saith, it speaketh to them that are under the law; that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world may be brought under the judgment of God: <verse number="20" style="v"/>because <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">out of</char>.</char></note>by <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">works of law</char></char></note>the works of the law shall no flesh be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">accounted righteous</char></char></note>justified in his sight; for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">through law</char></char></note>through the law <char style="add">cometh</char> the knowledge of sin.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>But now apart from the law a righteousness of God hath been manifested, being witnessed by the law and the prophets; <verse number="22" style="v"/>even the righteousness of God through faith <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of</char></char></note>in Jesus Christ unto all <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities add <char style="it">and upon all</char>.</char></note>them that believe; for there is no distinction; <verse number="23" style="v"/>for all <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sinned</char>.</char></note>have sinned, and fall short of the glory of God; <verse number="24" style="v"/>being justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus: <verse number="25" style="v"/>whom God set forth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, to be <char style="it">propitiatory</char></char></note><char style="add">to be</char> a propitiation, through faith, in his blood, to show his righteousness because of the passing over of the sins done aforetime, in the forbearance of God; <verse number="26" style="v"/>for the showing, <char style="add">I say</char>, of his righteousness at this present season: that he might himself be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See <ref loc="ROM 2:13">2:13</ref> margin.</char></note>just, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See <ref loc="ROM 2:13">2:13</ref> margin.</char></note>justifier of him that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">is of faith</char>.</char></note>hath faith <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of</char></char></note>in Jesus. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Where then is the glorying? It is excluded. By what manner of law? of works? Nay: but by a law of faith. <verse number="28" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">For we reckon</char>.</char></note>We reckon therefore that a man is justified by faith apart from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">works of law</char></char></note>the works of the law. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Or is God <char style="add">the God</char> of Jews only? is he not <char style="add">the God</char> of Gentiles also? Yea, of Gentiles also: <verse number="30" style="v"/>if so be that God is one, and he shall justify the circumcision <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">out of</char>. <ref loc="GAL 3:8">Gal. 3:8</ref>.</char></note>by faith, and the uncircumcision <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">through the faith</char>. <ref loc="GAL 2:16">Gal. 2:16</ref></char></note>through faith.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>Do we then make <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">law</char></char></note>the law of none effect <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">through the faith</char>. <ref loc="GAL 2:16">Gal. 2:16</ref></char></note>through faith? God forbid: nay, we establish <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">law</char></char></note>the law.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>What then shall we say <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">of Abraham, our forefather according to the flesh?</char></char></note>that Abraham, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">our forefather according to the flesh hath found?</char></char></note>our forefather, hath found according to the flesh? <verse number="2" style="v"/>For if Abraham was justified <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">out of</char>. <ref loc="GAL 3:8">Gal. 3:8</ref>.</char></note>by works, he hath whereof to glory; but not toward God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For what saith the scripture? <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 15:6">Gen. 15:6</ref>.</char></note>And Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned unto him for righteousness. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Now to him that worketh, the reward is not reckoned as of grace, but as of debt. <verse number="5" style="v"/>But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is reckoned for righteousness. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Even as David also pronounceth blessing upon the man, unto whom God reckoneth righteousness apart from works, <verse number="7" style="v"/><char style="add">saying</char>,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 32">Ps. 32:1f</ref>.</char></note>Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven,</para>
	<para style="q1">And whose sins are covered.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="8" style="v"/>Blessed is the man to whom the Lord will not reckon sin.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="9" style="v"/>Is this blessing then pronounced upon the circumcision, or upon the uncircumcision also? for we say, To Abraham his faith was reckoned for righteousness. <verse number="10" style="v"/>How then was it reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision: <verse number="11" style="v"/>and he received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith which he had while he was in uncircumcision: that he might be the father of all them that believe, though they be in uncircumcision, that righteousness might be reckoned unto them; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and the father of circumcision to them who not only are of the circumcision, but who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham which he had in uncircumcision. <verse number="13" style="v"/>For not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">through law</char></char></note>through the law was the promise to Abraham or to his seed that he should be heir of the world, but through the righteousness of faith. <verse number="14" style="v"/>For if they that are of the law are heirs, faith is made void, and the promise is made of none effect: <verse number="15" style="v"/>for the law worketh wrath; but where there is no law, neither is there transgression. <verse number="16" style="v"/>For this cause <char style="add">it is</char> of faith, that <char style="add">it may be</char> according to grace; to the end that the promise may be sure to all the seed; not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of us all <verse number="17" style="v"/>(as it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 17:5">Gen. 17:5</ref>.</char></note>A father of many nations have I made thee) before him whom he believed, <char style="add">even</char> God, who giveth life to the dead, and calleth the things that are not, as though they were. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Who in hope believed against hope, to the end that he might become a father of many nations, according to that which had been spoken, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 15:5">Gen. 15:5</ref>.</char></note>So shall thy seed be. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And without being weakened in faith he considered his own body <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities omit <char style="it">now</char>.</char></note>now as good as dead (he being about a hundred years old), and the deadness of Sarah&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">womb: yea, etc.</char></char></note>womb; <verse number="20" style="v"/>yet, looking unto the promise of God, he wavered not through unbelief, but waxed strong through faith, giving glory to God, <verse number="21" style="v"/>and being fully assured that what he had promised, he was able also to perform. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Wherefore also it was reckoned unto him for righteousness. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Now it was not written for his sake alone, that it was reckoned unto him; <verse number="24" style="v"/>but for our sake also, unto whom it shall be reckoned, who believe on him that raised Jesus our Lord from the dead, <verse number="25" style="v"/>who was delivered up for our trespasses, and was raised for our justification.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Being therefore justified <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">out of</char>.</char></note>by faith, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">let us have</char>.</char></note>we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ; <verse number="2" style="v"/>through whom also we have had our access <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">by faith</char>.</char></note>by faith into this grace wherein we stand; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">let us rejoice</char></char></note>we <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">glory</char>. <ref loc="ROM 5:11">Verse 11</ref>; <ref loc="HEB 3:6">Heb. 3:6</ref>.</char></note>rejoice in hope of the glory of God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And not only so, but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">let us also rejoice</char></char></note>we also <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">glory</char>. <ref loc="ROM 5:11">Verse 11</ref>; <ref loc="HEB 3:6">Heb. 3:6</ref>.</char></note>rejoice in our tribulations: knowing that tribulation worketh stedfastness; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and stedfastness, approvedness; and approvedness, hope: <verse number="5" style="v"/>and hope putteth not to shame; because the love of God hath been <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">poured out</char>.</char></note>shed abroad in our hearts through the Holy Spirit which was given unto us. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For while we were yet weak, in due season Christ died for the ungodly. <verse number="7" style="v"/>For scarcely for a righteous man will one die: for peradventure for the good man some one would even dare to die. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But God commendeth his own love toward us, in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Much more then, being now justified <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in</char>.</char></note>by his blood, shall we be saved from the wrath <char style="add">of God</char> through him. <verse number="10" style="v"/>For if, while we were enemies, we were reconciled to God through the death of his Son, much more, being reconciled, shall we be saved <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in</char>.</char></note>by his life; <verse number="11" style="v"/>and not only so, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">but also glorying</char>. Compare <ref loc="ROM 5:2">verse 2</ref>.</char></note>but we also rejoice in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom we have now received the reconciliation.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Therefore, as through one man sin entered into the world, and death through sin; and so death passed unto all men, for that all sinned:&#8212;<verse number="13" style="v"/>for until the law sin was in the world; but sin is not imputed when there is no law. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Nevertheless death reigned from Adam until Moses, even over them that had not sinned after the likeness of Adam&#8217;s transgression, who is a figure of him that was to come. <verse number="15" style="v"/>But not as the trespass, so also <char style="add">is</char> the free gift. For if by the trespass of the one the many died, much more did the grace of God, and the gift by the grace of the one man, Jesus Christ, abound unto the many. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And not as through one that sinned, <char style="add">so</char> is the gift: for the judgment <char style="add">came</char> of one unto condemnation, but the free gift <char style="add">came</char> of many trespasses unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">an act of righteousness</char>. <ref loc="REV 15:4">Rev. 15:4</ref>; <ref loc="REV 19:8">19:8</ref>.</char></note>justification. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For if, by the trespass of the one, death reigned through the one; much more shall they that receive the abundance of grace and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">of the gift</char>.</char></note>of the gift of righteousness reign in life through the one, <char style="add">even</char> Jesus Christ. <verse number="18" style="v"/>So then as through one trespass <char style="add">the judgment came</char> unto all men to condemnation; even so through one act of righteousness <char style="add">the free gift came</char> unto all men to justification of life. <verse number="19" style="v"/>For as through the one man&#8217;s disobedience the many were made sinners, even so through the obedience of the one shall the many be made righteous. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">law</char></char></note>the law came in besides, that the trespass might abound; but where sin abounded, grace did abound more exceedingly: <verse number="21" style="v"/>that, as sin reigned in death, even so might grace reign through righteousness unto eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound? <verse number="2" style="v"/>God forbid. We who died to sin, how shall we any longer live therein? <verse number="3" style="v"/>Or are ye ignorant that all we who were baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death? <verse number="4" style="v"/>We were buried therefore with him through baptism into death: that like as Christ was raised from the dead through the glory of the Father, so we also might walk in newness of life. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For if we have become <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">united with the likeness</char> &#160;.&#160;.&#160;. with the likeness</char></note>united with <char style="add">him</char> in the likeness of his death, we shall be also <char style="add">in the likeness</char> of his resurrection; <verse number="6" style="v"/>knowing this, that our old man was crucified with <char style="add">him</char>, that the body of sin might be done away, that so we should no longer be in bondage to sin; <verse number="7" style="v"/>for he that hath died is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">released</char>. Compare <ref loc="SIR 26:29">Ecclus. 26:29</ref> (Greek); <ref loc="ROM 7:1">7:1</ref>.</char></note>justified from sin. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But if we died with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him; <verse number="9" style="v"/>knowing that Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more; death no more hath dominion over him. <verse number="10" style="v"/>For <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in that</char></char></note>the death that he died, he died unto sin <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">once for all</char>. <ref loc="HEB 7:27">Heb. 7:27</ref>.</char></note>once: but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in that</char></char></note>the life that he liveth, he liveth unto God. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Even so reckon ye also yourselves to be dead unto sin, but alive unto God in Christ Jesus.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body, that ye should obey the lusts thereof: <verse number="13" style="v"/>neither present your members unto sin <char style="add">as</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">weapons</char>. Compare <ref loc="2CO 10:4">2 Cor. 10:4</ref>.</char></note>instruments of unrighteousness; but present yourselves unto God, as alive from the dead, and your members <char style="add">as</char> instruments of righteousness unto God. <verse number="14" style="v"/>For sin shall not have dominion over you: for ye are not under law, but under grace.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>What then? shall we sin, because we are not under law, but under grace? God forbid. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Know ye not, that to whom ye present yourselves <char style="add">as</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants unto obedience, his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants ye are whom ye obey; whether of sin unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness? <verse number="17" style="v"/>But thanks be to God, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that ye were&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. but ye became</char></char></note>that, whereas ye were <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants of sin, ye became obedient from the heart to that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pattern</char></char></note>form of teaching whereunto ye were delivered; <verse number="18" style="v"/>and being made free from sin, ye became <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservents</char>.</char></note>servants of righteousness. <verse number="19" style="v"/>I speak after the manner of men because of the infirmity of your flesh: for as ye presented your members <char style="add">as</char> servants to uncleanness and to iniquity unto iniquity, even so now present your members <char style="add">as</char> servants to righteousness unto sanctification. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For when ye were <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants of sin, ye were free in regard of righteousness. <verse number="21" style="v"/>What fruit then had ye at that time in the things whereof ye are now ashamed? for the end of those things is death. <verse number="22" style="v"/>But now being made free from sin and become servants to God, ye have your fruit unto sanctification, and the end eternal life. <verse number="23" style="v"/>For the wages of sin is death; but the free gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Or are ye ignorant, brethren (for I speak to men who know <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">law</char></char></note>the law), that the law hath dominion over a man for so long time as he liveth? <verse number="2" style="v"/>For the woman that hath a husband is bound by law to the husband while he liveth; but if the husband die, she is discharged from the law of the husband. <verse number="3" style="v"/>So then if, while the husband liveth, she be joined to another man, she shall be called an adulteress: but if the husband die, she is free from the law, so that she is no adulteress, though she be joined to another man. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Wherefore, my brethren, ye also were made dead to the law through the body of Christ; that ye should be joined to another, <char style="add">even</char> to him who was raised from the dead, that we might bring forth fruit unto God. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For when we were in the flesh, the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">passions of sins</char>.</char></note>sinful passions, which were through the law, wrought in our members to bring forth fruit unto death. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But now we have been discharged from the law, having died to that wherein we were held; so that we serve in newness of the spirit, and not in oldness of the letter.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>What shall we say then? Is the law sin? God forbid. Howbeit, I had not known sin, except through <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">law</char></char></note>the law: for I had not known <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lust</char></char></note>coveting, except the law had said, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="EXO 20:17">Ex. 20:17</ref>; <ref loc="DEU 5:21">Dt. 5:21</ref>.</char></note>Thou shalt not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lust</char></char></note>covet: <verse number="8" style="v"/>but sin, finding occasion, wrought in me through the commandment all manner of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lust</char></char></note>coveting: for apart from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">law</char></char></note>the law sin <char style="add">is</char> dead. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And I was alive apart from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">law</char></char></note>the law once: but when the commandment came, sin revived, and I died; <verse number="10" style="v"/>and the commandment, which <char style="add">was</char> unto life, this I found <char style="add">to be</char> unto death: <verse number="11" style="v"/>for sin, finding occasion, through the commandment beguiled me, and through it slew me. <verse number="12" style="v"/>So that the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and righteous, and good. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Did then that which is good become death unto me? God forbid. But sin, that it might be shown to be sin, by working death to me through that which is good;&#8212;that through the commandment sin might become exceeding sinful. <verse number="14" style="v"/>For we know that the law is spiritual: but I am carnal, sold under sin. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For that which I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">work</char>.</char></note>do I know not: for not what I would, that do I practise; but what I hate, that I do. <verse number="16" style="v"/>But if what I would not, that I do, I consent unto the law that it is good. <verse number="17" style="v"/>So now it is no more I that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">work</char>.</char></note>do it, but sin which dwelleth in me. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, dwelleth no good thing: for to will is present with me, but to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">work</char>.</char></note>do that which is good <char style="add">is</char> not. <verse number="19" style="v"/>For the good which I would I do not: but the evil which I would not, that I practise. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But if what I would not, that I do, it is no more I that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">work</char>.</char></note>do it, but sin which dwelleth in me. <verse number="21" style="v"/>I find then <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in regard of the law</char>. Compare verses <ref loc="ROM 7:12">12</ref>, <ref loc="ROM 7:14">14</ref></char></note>the law, that, to me who would do good, evil is present. <verse number="22" style="v"/>For I delight <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">with</char>.</char></note>in the law of God after the inward man: <verse number="23" style="v"/>but I see a different law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in</char>. Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">to</char>.</char></note>under the law of sin which is in my members. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Wretched man that I am! who shall deliver me out of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">this body of death</char></char></note>the body of this death? <verse number="25" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">But thanks be to God</char>. Compare <ref loc="ROM 6:17">6:17</ref>.</char></note>I thank God through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then I of myself with the mind, indeed, serve the law of God; but with the flesh the law of sin.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>There is therefore now no condemnation to them that are in Christ Jesus. <verse number="2" style="v"/>For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus made me free from the law of sin and of death. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For what the law could not do, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wherein</char></char></note>in that it was weak through the flesh, God, sending his own Son in the likeness of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">flesh of sin</char>.</char></note>sinful flesh <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and</char> as an offering <char style="it">for sin</char>. <ref loc="LEV 7:37">Lev. 7:37</ref>; <ref loc="HEB 10:6">Heb. 10:6</ref>; etc.</char></note>and for sin, condemned sin in the flesh: <verse number="4" style="v"/>that the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">requirement</char></char></note>ordinance of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For they that are after the flesh mind the things of the flesh; but they that are after the Spirit the things of the Spirit. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For the mind of the flesh is death; but the mind of the Spirit is life and peace: <verse number="7" style="v"/>because the mind of the flesh is enmity against God; for it is not subject to the law of God, neither indeed can it be: <verse number="8" style="v"/>and they that are in the flesh cannot please God. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But ye are not in the flesh but in the Spirit, if so be that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you. But if any man hath not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And if Christ is in you, the body is dead because of sin; but the spirit is life because of righteousness. <verse number="11" style="v"/>But if the Spirit of him that raised up Jesus from the dead dwelleth in you, he that raised up Christ Jesus from the dead shall give life also to your mortal bodies <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">because of</char>.</char></note>through his Spirit that dwelleth in you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>So then, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live after the flesh: <verse number="13" style="v"/>for if ye live after the flesh, ye must die; but if by the Spirit ye put to death the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">doings</char>.</char></note>deeds of the body, ye shall live. <verse number="14" style="v"/>For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, these are sons of God. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For ye received not the spirit of bondage again unto fear; but ye received the spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father. <verse number="16" style="v"/>The Spirit himself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are children of God: <verse number="17" style="v"/>and if children, then heirs; heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ; if so be that we suffer with <char style="add">him</char>, that we may be also glorified with <char style="add">him</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be revealed to us-ward. <verse number="19" style="v"/>For the earnest expectation of the creation waiteth for the revealing of the sons of God. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For the creation was subjected to vanity, not of its own will, but by reason of him who subjected it, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in hope; because the creation etc.</char></char></note>in hope <verse number="21" style="v"/>that the creation itself also shall be delivered from the bondage of corruption into the liberty of the glory of the children of God. <verse number="22" style="v"/>For we know that the whole creation groaneth and travaileth in pain <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">with</char> us</char></note>together until now. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And not only so, but ourselves also, who have the first-fruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for <char style="add">our</char> adoption, <char style="add">to wit</char>, the redemption of our body. <verse number="24" style="v"/>For <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by</char></char></note>in hope were we saved: but hope that is seen is not hope: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">for what a man seeth, why doth he yet hope for?</char></char></note>for who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">awaiteth</char>.</char></note>hopeth for that which he seeth? <verse number="25" style="v"/>But if we hope for that which we see not, <char style="add">then</char> do we with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience wait for it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v"/>And in like manner the Spirit also helpeth our infirmity: for we know not how to pray as we ought; but the Spirit himself maketh intercession for <char style="add">us</char> with groanings which cannot be uttered; <verse number="27" style="v"/>and he that searcheth the hearts knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that</char></char></note>because he maketh intercession for the saints according to <char style="add">the will of</char> God. <verse number="28" style="v"/>And we know that to them that love God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">God worketh all things with them for good</char>.</char></note>all things work together for good, <char style="add">even</char> to them that are called according to <char style="add">his</char> purpose. <verse number="29" style="v"/>For whom he foreknew, he also foreordained <char style="add">to be</char> conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the firstborn among many brethren: <verse number="30" style="v"/>and whom he foreordained, them he also called: and whom he called, them he also justified: and whom he justified, them he also glorified.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v"/>What then shall we say to these things? If God <char style="add">is</char> for us, who <char style="add">is</char> against us? <verse number="32" style="v"/>He that spared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall he not also with him freely give us all things? <verse number="33" style="v"/>Who shall lay anything to the charge of God&#8217;s elect? <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Shall God that justifieth?</char></char></note>It is God that justifieth; <verse number="34" style="v"/>who is he that condemneth? <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Shall Christ Jesus that died, &#160;.&#160;.&#160;. us?</char></char></note>It is Christ Jesus that died, yea rather, that was raised from the dead, who is at the right hand of God, who also maketh intercession for us. <verse number="35" style="v"/>Who shall separate us from the love <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">of God</char>.</char></note>of Christ? shall tribulation, or anguish, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword? <verse number="36" style="v"/>Even as it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 44:22">Ps. 44:22</ref>.</char></note>For thy sake we are killed all the day long;</para>
	<para style="q1">We were accounted as sheep for the slaughter.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="37" style="v"/>Nay, in all these things we are more than conquerors through him that loved us. <verse number="38" style="v"/>For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers, <verse number="39" style="v"/>nor height, nor depth, nor any other <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">creation</char></char></note>creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience bearing witness with me in the Holy Spirit, <verse number="2" style="v"/>that I have great sorrow and unceasing pain in my heart. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For I could <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pray</char></char></note>wish that I myself were anathema from Christ for my brethren&#8217;s sake, my kinsmen according to the flesh: <verse number="4" style="v"/>who are Israelites; whose is the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the service <char style="add">of God</char>, and the promises; <verse number="5" style="v"/>whose are the fathers, and of whom is Christ as concerning the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">flesh; he who is over all, God</char>, be <char style="it">blessed for ever</char></char></note>flesh, who is over all, God blessed <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever. Amen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>But <char style="add">it is</char> not as though the word of God hath come to nought. For they are not all Israel, that are of Israel: <verse number="7" style="v"/>neither, because they are Abraham&#8217;s seed, are they all children: but, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 21:12">Gen. 21:12</ref>.</char></note>In Isaac shall thy seed be called. <verse number="8" style="v"/>That is, it is not the children of the flesh that are children of God; but the children of the promise are reckoned for a seed. <verse number="9" style="v"/>For this is a word of promise, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 18:10">Gen. 18:10</ref>.</char></note>According to this season will I come, and Sarah shall have a son. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And not only so; but Rebecca also having conceived by one, <char style="add">even</char> by our father Isaac&#8212;<verse number="11" style="v"/>for <char style="add">the children</char> being not yet born, neither having done anything good or bad, that the purpose of God according to election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth, <verse number="12" style="v"/>it was said unto her, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 25:23">Gen. 25:23</ref>.</char></note>The elder shall serve the younger. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Even as it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="MAL 1:2-1:14">Mal. 1:2f</ref>.</char></note>Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? God forbid. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For he saith to Moses, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="EXO 33:19">Ex. 33:19</ref>.</char></note>I will have mercy on whom I have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I have compassion. <verse number="16" style="v"/>So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that hath mercy. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For the scripture saith unto Pharaoh, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="EXO 9:16">Ex. 9:16</ref>.</char></note>For this very purpose did I raise thee up, that I might show in thee my power, and that my name might be published abroad in all the earth. <verse number="18" style="v"/>So then he hath mercy on whom he will, and whom he will he hardeneth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>Thou wilt say then unto me, Why doth he still find fault? For who withstandeth his will? <verse number="20" style="v"/>Nay but, O man, who art thou that repliest against God? Shall the thing formed say to him that formed it, Why didst thou make me thus? <verse number="21" style="v"/>Or hath not the potter a right over the clay, from the same lump to make one part a vessel unto honor, and another unto dishonor? <verse number="22" style="v"/>What if God, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">although willing</char></char></note>willing to show his wrath, and to make his power known, endured with much longsuffering vessels of wrath fitted unto destruction: <verse number="23" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">and</char>.</char></note>and that he might make known the riches of his glory upon vessels of mercy, which he afore prepared unto glory, <verse number="24" style="v"/><char style="add">even</char> us, whom he also called, not from the Jews only, but also from the Gentiles? <verse number="25" style="v"/>As he saith also in Hosea,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="HOS 2:23">Hos. 2:23</ref>.</char></note>I will call that my people, which was not my people;</para>
	<para style="q1">And her beloved, that was not beloved.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="26" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="HOS 1:10">Hos. 1:10</ref>.</char></note>And it shall be, <char style="add">that</char> in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people,</para>
	<para style="q1">There shall they be called sons of the living God.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="27" style="v"/>And Isaiah crieth concerning Israel, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 10:22-10:34">Isa. 10:22f</ref>.</char></note>If the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, it is the remnant that shall be saved: <verse number="28" style="v"/>for the Lord will execute <char style="add">his</char> word upon the earth, finishing it and cutting it short. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And, as Isaiah hath said before,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 1:9">Isa. 1:9</ref>.</char></note>Except the Lord of Sabaoth had left us a seed,</para>
	<para style="q1">We had become as Sodom, and had been made like unto Gomorrah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>What shall we say then? That the Gentiles, who followed not after righteousness, attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is of faith: <verse number="31" style="v"/>but Israel, following after a law of righteousness, did not arrive at <char style="add">that</char> law. <verse number="32" style="v"/>Wherefore? <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Because</char>, doing it <char style="it">not by faith, but as it were by works, they stumbled</char></char></note>Because <char style="add">they sought it</char> not by faith, but as it were by works. They stumbled at the stone of stumbling; <verse number="33" style="v"/>even as it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 28:16">Isa. 28:16</ref>.</char></note>Behold, I lay in Zion a stone of stumbling and a rock of offence:</para>
	<para style="q1">And he that believeth on <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">it</char></char></note>him shall not be put to shame.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Brethren, my heart&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good pleasure</char>.</char></note>desire and my supplication to God is for them, that they may be saved. <verse number="2" style="v"/>For I bear them witness that they have a zeal for God, but not according to knowledge. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For being ignorant of God&#8217;s righteousness, and seeking to establish their own, they did not subject themselves to the righteousness of God. <verse number="4" style="v"/>For Christ is the end of the law unto righteousness to every one that believeth. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For Moses writeth that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="LEV 18:5">Lev. 18:5</ref>.</char></note>the man that doeth the righteousness which is of the law shall live thereby. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But the righteousness which is of faith saith thus, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 30:12-30:20">Dt. 30:12f</ref>.</char></note>Say not in thy heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring Christ down:) <verse number="7" style="v"/>or, Who shall descend into the abyss? (that is, to bring Christ up from the dead.) <verse number="8" style="v"/>But what saith it? <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 30:14">Dt. 30:14</ref>.</char></note>The word is nigh thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach: <verse number="9" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that</char></char></note>because if thou shalt <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">confess the word with thy mouth, that Jesus</char> is <char style="it">Lord</char>.</char></note>confess with thy mouth Jesus <char style="add">as</char> Lord, and shalt believe in thy heart that God raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved: <verse number="10" style="v"/>for with the heart man believeth unto righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation. <verse number="11" style="v"/>For the scripture saith, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 28:16">Isa. 28:16</ref>.</char></note>Whosoever believeth on him shall not be put to shame. <verse number="12" style="v"/>For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek: for the same <char style="add">Lord</char> is Lord of all, and is rich unto all that call upon him: <verse number="13" style="v"/>for, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="JOL 2:32">Joel 2:32</ref>.</char></note>Whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. <verse number="14" style="v"/>How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe in him whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without a preacher? <verse number="15" style="v"/>and how shall they preach, except they be sent? even as it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 52:7">Isa. 52:7</ref>.</char></note>How beautiful are the feet of them that bring <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a gospel</char></char></note>glad tidings of good things!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>But they did not all hearken to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gospel</char></char></note>glad tidings. For Isaiah saith, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 53:1">Isa. 53:1</ref>.</char></note>Lord, who hath believed our report? <verse number="17" style="v"/>So belief <char style="add">cometh</char> of hearing, and hearing by the word of Christ. <verse number="18" style="v"/>But I say, Did they not hear? Yea, verily,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 19:4">Ps. 19:4</ref>.</char></note>Their sound went out into all the earth,</para>
	<para style="q1">And their words unto the ends of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>the world.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="19" style="v"/>But I say, Did Israel not know? First Moses saith,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 32:21">Dt. 32:21</ref>.</char></note>I will provoke you to jealousy with that which is no nation,</para>
	<para style="q1">With a nation void of understanding will I anger you.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="20" style="v"/>And Isaiah is very bold, and saith,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 65:1">Isa. 65:1</ref>.</char></note>I was found of them that sought me not;</para>
	<para style="q1">I became manifest unto them that asked not of me.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="21" style="v"/>But as to Israel he saith, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 65:2">Isa. 65:2</ref>.</char></note>All the day long did I spread out my hands unto a disobedient and gainsaying people.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>I say then, Did God cast off his people? God forbid. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin. <verse number="2" style="v"/>God did not cast off his people which he foreknew. Or know ye not what the scripture <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="1KI 19:10">1 Kin. 19:10</ref>.</char></note>saith <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char>. Compare <ref loc="MRK 12:26">Mk. 12:26</ref>.</char></note>of Elijah? how he pleadeth with God against Israel: <verse number="3" style="v"/>Lord, they have killed thy prophets, they have digged down thine altars; and I am left alone, and they seek my life. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But what <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="1KI 19:18">1 Kin. 19:18</ref>.</char></note>saith the answer of God unto him? I have left for myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed the knee to Baal. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Even so then at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But if it is by grace, it is no more of works: otherwise grace is no more grace. <verse number="7" style="v"/>What then? That which Israel seeketh for, that he obtained not; but the election obtained it, and the rest were hardened: <verse number="8" style="v"/>according as it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 29:10">Isa. 29:10</ref>; <ref loc="DEU 29:4">Dt. 29:4</ref>.</char></note>God gave them a spirit of stupor, eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear, unto this very day. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And David saith,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 69:22-69:36">Ps. 69:22f</ref>.</char></note>Let their table be made a snare, and a trap,</para>
	<para style="q1">And a stumblingblock, and a recompense unto them:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="10" style="v"/>Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see,</para>
	<para style="q1">And bow thou down their back always.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>I say then, Did they stumble that they might fall? God forbid: but by their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">trespass</char>. Compare <ref loc="ROM 5:15-5:21">5:15ff</ref>.</char></note>fall salvation <char style="add">is come</char> unto the Gentiles, to provoke them to jealousy. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Now if their fall is the riches of the world, and their loss the riches of the Gentiles; how much more their fulness? <verse number="13" style="v"/>But I speak to you that are Gentiles. Inasmuch then as I am an apostle of Gentiles, I glorify my ministry; <verse number="14" style="v"/>if by any means I may provoke to jealousy <char style="add">them that are</char> my flesh, and may save some of them. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For if the casting away of them <char style="add">is</char> the reconciling of the world, what <char style="add">shall</char> the receiving <char style="add">of them be</char>, but life from the dead? <verse number="16" style="v"/>And if the firstfruit is holy, so is the lump: and if the root is holy, so are the branches. <verse number="17" style="v"/>But if some of the branches were broken off, and thou, being a wild olive, wast grafted in among them, and didst become partaker with them <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">of the root and of the fatness</char>.</char></note>of the root of the fatness of the olive tree; <verse number="18" style="v"/>glory not over the branches: but if thou gloriest, it is not thou that bearest the root, but the root thee. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Thou wilt say then, Branches were broken off, that I might be grafted in. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Well; by their unbelief they were broken off, and thou standest by thy faith. Be not highminded, but fear: <verse number="21" style="v"/>for if God spared not the natural branches, neither will he spare thee. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Behold then the goodness and severity of God: toward them that fell, severity; but toward thee, God&#8217;s goodness, if thou continue in his goodness: otherwise thou also shalt be cut off. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And they also, if they continue not in their unbelief, shall be grafted in: for God is able to graft them in again. <verse number="24" style="v"/>For if thou wast cut out of that which is by nature a wild olive tree, and wast grafted contrary to nature into a good olive tree; how much more shall these, which are the natural <char style="add">branches</char>, be grafted into their own olive tree?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>For I would not, brethren, have you ignorant of this mystery, lest ye be wise in your own conceits, that a hardening in part hath befallen Israel, until the fulness of the Gentiles be come in; <verse number="26" style="v"/>and so all Israel shall be saved: even as it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 59:20-59:21">Isa. 59:20f</ref>.</char></note>There shall come out of Zion the Deliverer;</para>
	<para style="q1">He shall turn away <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">ungodlinesses</char>.</char></note>ungodliness from Jacob:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="27" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 27:9">Isa. 27:9</ref>.</char></note>And this is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the covenant from me</char>.</char></note>my covenant unto them,</para>
	<para style="q1">When I shall take away their sins.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="28" style="v"/>As touching the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See <ref loc="ROM 10:15">10:15</ref>, <ref loc="ROM 10:16">16</ref> and marginal note on <ref loc="ROM 1:1">1:1</ref>.</char></note>gospel, they are enemies for your sake: but as touching the election, they are beloved for the fathers&#8217; sake. <verse number="29" style="v"/>For the gifts and the calling of God are not repented of. <verse number="30" style="v"/>For as ye in time past were disobedient to God, but now have obtained mercy by their disobedience, <verse number="31" style="v"/>even so have these also now been disobedient, that by the mercy shown to you they also may now obtain mercy. <verse number="32" style="v"/>For God hath shut up all unto disobedience, that he might have mercy upon all.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v"/>O the depth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of the riches and the wisdom etc.</char></char></note>of the riches <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">both of wisdom etc.</char></char></note>both of the wisdom and the knowledge of God! how unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past tracing out! <verse number="34" style="v"/>For who hath known the mind of the Lord? or who hath been his counsellor? <verse number="35" style="v"/>or who hath first given to him, and it shall be recompensed unto him again? <verse number="36" style="v"/>For of him, and through him, and unto him, are all things. To him <char style="add">be</char> the glory <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever. Amen.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, to present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">well-pleasing</char>.</char></note>acceptable to God, <char style="add">which is</char> your <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">belonging to the reason</char>.</char></note>spiritual <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">worship</char></char></note>service. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And be not fashioned according to this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">age</char></char></note>world: but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind, that ye may prove what is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the will of God</char>, even <char style="it">the thing which is good and acceptable and perfect</char></char></note>the good and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">well-pleasing</char>.</char></note>acceptable and perfect will of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>For I say, through the grace that was given me, to every man that is among you, not to think of himself more highly than he ought to think; but so to think as to think soberly, according as God hath dealt to each man a measure of faith. <verse number="4" style="v"/>For even as we have many members in one body, and all the members have not the same office: <verse number="5" style="v"/>so we, who are many, are one body in Christ, and severally members one of another. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And having gifts differing according to the grace that was given to us, whether prophecy, <char style="add">let us prophesy</char> according to the proportion of our faith; <verse number="7" style="v"/>or ministry, <char style="add">let us give ourselves</char> to our ministry; or he that teacheth, to his teaching; <verse number="8" style="v"/>or he that exhorteth, to his exhorting: he that giveth, <char style="add">let him do it</char> with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">singleness</char>.</char></note>liberality; he that ruleth, with diligence; he that showeth mercy, with cheerfulness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>Let love be without hypocrisy. Abhor that which is evil; cleave to that which is good. <verse number="10" style="v"/>In love of the brethren be tenderly affectioned one to another; in honor preferring one another; <verse number="11" style="v"/>in diligence not slothful; fervent in spirit; serving <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">the opportunity</char>.</char></note>the Lord; <verse number="12" style="v"/>rejoicing in hope; patient in tribulation; continuing stedfastly in prayer; <verse number="13" style="v"/>communicating to the necessities of the saints; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">pursuing</char>.</char></note>given to hospitality. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Bless them that persecute you; bless, and curse not. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Rejoice with them that rejoice; weep with them that weep. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Be of the same mind one toward another. Set not your mind on high things, but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">be carried away with</char>.</char></note>condescend to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">them</char></char></note>things that are lowly. Be not wise in your own conceits. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Render to no man evil for evil. Take thought for things honorable in the sight of all men. <verse number="18" style="v"/>If it be possible, as much as in you lieth, be at peace with all men. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Avenge not yourselves, beloved, but give place unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wrath</char></char></note>the wrath <char style="add">of God</char>: for it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 32:35">Dt. 32:35</ref>.</char></note>Vengeance belongeth unto me; I will recompense, saith the Lord. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">(<ref loc="PRO 25:21-25:28">Prov. 25:21f</ref>)</char></note>if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirst, give him to drink: for in so doing thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Let every soul be in subjection to the higher powers: for there is no power but of God; and the <char style="add">powers</char> that be are ordained of God. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Therefore he that resisteth the power, withstandeth the ordinance of God: and they that withstand shall receive to themselves judgment. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For rulers are not a terror to the good work, but to the evil. And wouldest thou have no fear of the power? do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise from the same: <verse number="4" style="v"/>for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">it</char></char></note>he is a minister of God to thee for good. But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid; for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">it</char></char></note>he beareth not the sword in vain: for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">it</char></char></note>he is a minister of God, an avenger for wrath to him that doeth evil. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Wherefore <char style="add">ye</char> must needs be in subjection, not only because of the wrath, but also for conscience&#8217; sake. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For for this cause ye pay tribute also; for they are ministers of God&#8217;s service, attending continually upon this very thing. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Render to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute <char style="add">is due</char>; custom to whom custom; fear to whom fear; honor to whom honor.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>Owe no man anything, save to love one another: for he that loveth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the other</char>. Compare <ref loc="1CO 6:1">1 Cor. 6:1</ref>; <ref loc="1CO 10:24">10:24</ref>; <ref loc="GAL 6:4">Gal. 6:4</ref>.</char></note>his neighbor hath fulfilled the law. <verse number="9" style="v"/>For this, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="EXO 20:13-20:26">Ex. 20:13ff</ref>; <ref loc="DEU 5:17-5:33">Dt. 5:17ff</ref>.</char></note>Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not covet, and if there be any other commandment, it is summed up in this word, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Love worketh no ill to his neighbor: love therefore is the fulfilment of the law.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And this, knowing the season, that already it is time for you to awake out of sleep: for now is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">our salvation nearer than when etc.</char></char></note>salvation nearer to us than when we <char style="add">first</char> believed. <verse number="12" style="v"/>The night is far spent, and the day is at hand: let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the armor of light. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Let us walk becomingly, as in the day; not in revelling and drunkenness, not in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and jealousy. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the flesh, to <char style="add">fulfil</char> the lusts <char style="add">thereof</char>.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>But him that is weak in faith receive ye, <char style="add">yet</char> not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to doubtful disputations</char></char></note>for decision of scruples. <verse number="2" style="v"/>One man hath faith to eat all things: but he that is weak eateth herbs. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Let not him that eateth set at nought him that eateth not; and let not him that eateth not judge him that eateth: for God hath received him. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Who art thou that judgest the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">household-servant</char>.</char></note>servant of another? to his own lord he standeth or falleth. Yea, he shall be made to stand; for the Lord hath power to make him stand. <verse number="5" style="v"/>One man esteemeth one day above another: another esteemeth every day <char style="add">alike</char>. Let each man be fully assured in his own mind. <verse number="6" style="v"/>He that regardeth the day, regardeth it unto the Lord: and he that eateth, eateth unto the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, unto the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks. <verse number="7" style="v"/>For none of us liveth to himself, and none dieth to himself. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For whether we live, we live unto the Lord; or whether we die, we die unto the Lord: whether we live therefore, or die, we are the Lord&#8217;s. <verse number="9" style="v"/>For to this end Christ died and lived <char style="add">again</char>, that he might be Lord of both the dead and the living. <verse number="10" style="v"/>But thou, why dost thou judge thy brother? or thou again, why dost thou set at nought thy brother? for we shall all stand before the judgment-seat of God. <verse number="11" style="v"/>For it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 45:23">Isa. 45:23</ref>.</char></note>As I live, saith the Lord, to me every knee shall bow,</para>
	<para style="q1">And every tongue shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">give praise</char></char></note>confess to God.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="12" style="v"/>So then each one of us shall give account of himself to God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>Let us not therefore judge one another any more: but judge ye this rather, that no man put a stumblingblock in his brother&#8217;s way, or an occasion of falling. <verse number="14" style="v"/>I know, and am persuaded in the Lord Jesus, that nothing is unclean of itself: save that to him who accounteth anything to be unclean, to him it is unclean. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For if because of meat thy brother is grieved, thou walkest no longer in love. Destroy not with thy meat him for whom Christ died. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Let not then your good be evil spoken of: <verse number="17" style="v"/>for the kingdom of God is not eating and drinking, but righteousness and peace and joy in the Holy Spirit. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For he that herein serveth Christ is well-pleasing to God, and approved of men. <verse number="19" style="v"/>So then <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">we follow</char>.</char></note>let us follow after things which make for peace, and things whereby we may edify one another. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Overthrow not for meat&#8217;s sake the work of God. All things indeed are clean; howbeit it is evil for that man who eateth with offence. <verse number="21" style="v"/>It is good not to eat flesh, nor to drink wine, nor <char style="add">to do anything</char> whereby thy brother stumbleth<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities add <char style="it">or is offended, or is weak</char>.</char></note>. <verse number="22" style="v"/>The faith which thou hast, have thou to thyself before God. Happy is he that judgeth not himself in that which he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">putteth to the test</char></char></note>approveth. <verse number="23" style="v"/>But he that doubteth is condemned if he eat, because <char style="add">he eateth</char> not of faith; and whatsoever is not of faith is sin.<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many authorities, some ancient, insert here <ref loc="ROM 16:25-16:27">16:25-27</ref>.</char></note></para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now we that are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Let each one of us please his neighbor for that which is good, unto edifying. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For Christ also pleased not himself; but, as it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 69:9">Ps. 69:9</ref>.</char></note>The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell upon me. <verse number="4" style="v"/>For whatsoever things were written aforetime were written for our learning, that through <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience and through comfort of the scriptures we might have hope. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Now the God of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience and of comfort grant you to be of the same mind one with another according to Christ Jesus: <verse number="6" style="v"/>that with one accord ye may with one mouth glorify <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">God and the Father</char>. So <ref loc="2CO 1:3">2 Cor. 1:3</ref>; <ref loc="2CO 11:31">11:31</ref>; <ref loc="EPH 1:3">Eph. 1:3</ref>; <ref loc="1PE 1:3">1 Pet. 1:3</ref></char></note>the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Wherefore receive ye one another, even as Christ also received <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">us</char>.</char></note>you, to the glory of God. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For I say that Christ hath been made a minister of the circumcision for the truth of God, that he might confirm the promises <char style="add">given</char> unto the fathers, <verse number="9" style="v"/>and that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy; as it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 18:49">Ps. 18:49</ref> (or <ref loc="2SA 22:50">2 Sam. 22:50</ref>)</char></note>Therefore will I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">confess</char></char></note>give praise unto thee among the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>. Compare <ref loc="MAT 4:15">Mt. 4:15</ref>.</char></note>Gentiles,</para>
	<para style="q1">And sing unto thy name.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And again he saith,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 32:43">Dt. 32:43</ref>.</char></note>Rejoice, ye <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles, with his people.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And again,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 117:1">Ps. 117:1</ref>.</char></note>Praise the Lord, all ye <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles;</para>
	<para style="q1">And let all the peoples praise him.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And again, Isaiah saith,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 11:10">Isa. 11:10</ref>.</char></note>There shall be the root of Jesse,</para>
	<para style="q1">And he that ariseth to rule over the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles;</para>
	<para style="q1">On him shall the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles hope.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="13" style="v"/>Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that ye may abound in hope, in the power of the Holy Spirit.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And I myself also am persuaded of you, my brethren, that ye yourselves are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish one another. <verse number="15" style="v"/>But I write the more boldly unto you in some measure, as putting you again in remembrance, because of the grace that was given me of God, <verse number="16" style="v"/>that I should be a minister of Christ Jesus unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">ministering in sacrifice</char>.</char></note>ministering the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ROM 1:1">1:1</ref>.</char></note>gospel of God, that the offering up of the Gentiles might be made acceptable, being sanctified by the Holy Spirit. <verse number="17" style="v"/>I have therefore my glorying in Christ Jesus in things pertaining to God. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For I will not dare to speak of any <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">of those things which Christ wrought not through me</char>.</char></note>things save those which Christ wrought through me, for the obedience of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles, by word and deed, <verse number="19" style="v"/>in the power of signs and wonders, in the power of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">the Spirit of God</char>. One reads <char style="it">the Spirit</char>.</char></note>the Holy Spirit; so that from Jerusalem, and round about even unto Illyricum, I have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">fulfilled</char>. Compare <ref loc="COL 1:25">Col. 1:25</ref>.</char></note>fully preached the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ROM 1:1">1:1</ref>.</char></note>gospel of Christ; <verse number="20" style="v"/>yea, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">being ambitious</char>. <ref loc="2CO 5:9">2 Cor. 5:9</ref>; <ref loc="1TH 4:11">1 Th. 4:11</ref>.</char></note>making it my aim so to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ROM 1:15">1:15</ref>.</char></note>preach the gospel, not where Christ was <char style="add">already</char> named, that I might not build upon another man&#8217;s foundation; <verse number="21" style="v"/>but, as it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 52:15">Isa. 52:15</ref>.</char></note>They shall see, to whom no tidings of him came,</para>
	<para style="q1">And they who have not heard shall understand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>Wherefore also I was hindered these many times from coming to you: <verse number="23" style="v"/>but now, having no more any place in these regions, and having these many years a longing to come unto you, <verse number="24" style="v"/>whensoever I go unto Spain (for I hope to see you in my journey, and to be brought on my way thitherward by you, if first in some measure I shall have been satisfied with your company)&#8212;<verse number="25" style="v"/>but now, <char style="add">I say</char>, I go unto Jerusalem, ministering unto the saints. <verse number="26" style="v"/>For it hath been the good pleasure of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor among the saints that are at Jerusalem. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Yea, it hath been their good pleasure; and their debtors they are. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, they owe it <char style="add">to them</char> also to minister unto them in carnal things. <verse number="28" style="v"/>When therefore I have accomplished this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will go on by you unto Spain. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And I know that, when I come unto you, I shall come in the fulness of the blessing of Christ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v"/>Now I beseech you, brethren, by our Lord Jesus Christ, and by the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in your prayers to God for me; <verse number="31" style="v"/>that I may be delivered from them that are disobedient in Judaea, and <char style="add">that</char> my ministration which <char style="add">I have</char> for Jerusalem may be acceptable to the saints; <verse number="32" style="v"/>that I may come unto you in joy through the will of God, and together with you find rest. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>I commend unto you Phoebe our sister, who is a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">deaconess</char></char></note>servant of the church that is at Cenchreae: <verse number="2" style="v"/>that ye receive her in the Lord, worthily of the saints, and that ye assist her in whatsoever matter she may have need of you: for she herself also hath been a helper of many, and of mine own self.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>Salute Prisca and Aquila my fellow-workers in Christ Jesus, <verse number="4" style="v"/>who for my life laid down their own necks; unto whom not only I give thanks, but also all the churches of the Gentiles: <verse number="5" style="v"/>and <char style="add">salute</char> the church that is in their house. Salute Epaenetus my beloved, who is the first-fruits of Asia unto Christ. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Salute Mary, who bestowed much labor on you. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Salute Andronicus and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Junia</char></char></note>Junias, my kinsmen, and my fellow-prisoners, who are of note among the apostles, who also have been in Christ before me. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Salute Ampliatus my beloved in the Lord. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Salute Urbanus our fellow-worker in Christ, and Stachys my beloved. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Salute Apelles the approved in Christ. Salute them that are of the <char style="add">household</char> of Aristobulus. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Salute Herodion my kinsman. Salute them of the <char style="add">household</char> of Narcissus, that are in the Lord. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Salute Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who labor in the Lord. Salute Persis the beloved, who labored much in the Lord. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Salute Rufus the chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and the brethren that are with them. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Salute Philologus and Julia, Nereus and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints that are with them. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Salute one another with a holy kiss. All the churches of Christ salute you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them that are causing the divisions and occasions of stumbling, contrary to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">teaching</char></char></note>doctrine which ye learned: and turn away from them. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For they that are such serve not our Lord Christ, but their own belly; and by their smooth and fair speech they beguile the hearts of the innocent. <verse number="19" style="v"/>For your obedience is come abroad unto all men. I rejoice therefore over you: but I would have you wise unto that which is good, and simple unto that which is evil. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the God of peace shall bruise Satan under your feet shortly.</para>
	<para style="p">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>Timothy my fellow-worker saluteth you; and Lucius and Jason and Sosipater, my kinsmen. <verse number="22" style="v"/>I Tertius, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">who write the epistle in the Lord, salute you</char></char></note>who write the epistle, salute you in the Lord. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Gaius my host, and of the whole church, saluteth you. Erastus the treasurer of the city saluteth you, and Quartus the brother.<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities insert here <ref loc="ROM 16:24">verse 24</ref> <char style="it">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen</char>, and omit the like words in <ref loc="ROM 16:20">verse 20</ref>.</char></note></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <ref loc="ROM 16:25-16:27">verses 25&#8211;27</ref>. Compare the <ref loc="ROM 14:23">end of chapter 14</ref>.</char></note>Now to him that is able to establish you according to my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="ROM 1:1">1:1</ref>.</char></note>gospel and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery which hath been kept in silence through times eternal, <verse number="26" style="v"/>but now is manifested, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">through</char>.</char></note>by the scriptures of the prophets, according to the commandment of the eternal God, is made known unto all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gentiles</char></char></note>nations unto obedience <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to the faith</char></char></note>of faith: <verse number="27" style="v"/>to the only wise God, through Jesus Christ, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">to whom</char>.</char></note>to whom be the glory <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever. Amen.</para>
</usx>