<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="GAL" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Paul, an apostle (not from men, neither through <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a man</char></char></note>man, but through Jesus Christ, and God the Father, who raised him from the dead), <verse number="2" style="v"/>and all the brethren that are with me, unto the churches of Galatia: <verse number="3" style="v"/>Grace to you and peace <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ</char>.</char></note>from God the Father, and our Lord Jesus Christ, <verse number="4" style="v"/>who gave himself for our sins, that he might deliver us out of this present evil <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">age</char></char></note>world, according to the will of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">God and our Father</char></char></note>our God and Father: <verse number="5" style="v"/>to whom <char style="add">be</char> the glory <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever. Amen.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>I marvel that ye are so quickly removing from him that called you in the grace of Christ unto a different <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref>.</char></note>gospel; <verse number="7" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">which is nothing else save that there etc.</char></char></note>which is not another <char style="add">gospel</char>: only there are some that trouble you, and would pervert the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="GAL 1:6">verse 6</ref>.</char></note>gospel of Christ. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But though we, or an angel from heaven, should <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 11:5">Mt. 11:5</ref>.</char></note>preach <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">unto you</char>.</char></note>unto you any gospel <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">contrary to that</char></char></note>other than that which we <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 11:5">Mt. 11:5</ref>.</char></note>preached unto you, let him be anathema. <verse number="9" style="v"/>As we have said before, so say I now again, If any man <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 11:5">Mt. 11:5</ref>.</char></note>preacheth unto you any gospel <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">contrary to that</char></char></note>other than that which ye received, let him be anathema. <verse number="10" style="v"/>For am I now seeking the favor of men, or of God? or am I striving to please men? if I were still pleasing men, I should not be a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant of Christ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>For I make known to you, brethren, as touching the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="GAL 1:6">verse 6</ref>.</char></note>gospel which was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 11:5">Mt. 11:5</ref>.</char></note>preached by me, that it is not after man. <verse number="12" style="v"/>For neither did I receive it from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a man</char></char></note>man, nor was I taught it, but <char style="add">it came to me</char> through revelation of Jesus Christ. <verse number="13" style="v"/>For ye have heard of my manner of life in time past in the Jews&#8217; religion, how that beyond measure I persecuted the church of God, and made havoc of it: <verse number="14" style="v"/>and I advanced in the Jews&#8217; religion beyond many of mine own age <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in my race</char>. Compare <ref loc="2CO 11:26">2 Cor. 11:26</ref>.</char></note>among my countrymen, being more exceedingly zealous for the traditions of my fathers. <verse number="15" style="v"/>But when it was the good pleasure of God, who separated me, <char style="add">even</char> from my mother&#8217;s womb, and called me through his grace, <verse number="16" style="v"/>to reveal his Son in me, that I might <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 11:5">Mt. 11:5</ref>.</char></note>preach him among the Gentiles; straightway I conferred not with flesh and blood: <verse number="17" style="v"/>neither went I up to Jerusalem to them that were apostles before me: but I went away into Arabia; and again I returned unto Damascus.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>Then after three years I went up to Jerusalem to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">become acquainted with</char></char></note>visit Cephas, and tarried with him fifteen days. <verse number="19" style="v"/>But other of the apostles saw I none, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">but only</char></char></note>save <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Jacob</char></char></note>James the Lord&#8217;s brother. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Now touching the things which I write unto you, behold, before God, I lie not. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Then I came into the regions of Syria and Cilicia. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And I was still unknown by face unto the churches of Judaea which were in Christ: <verse number="23" style="v"/>but they only heard say, He that once persecuted us now <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 11:5">Mt. 11:5</ref>.</char></note>preacheth the faith of which he once made havoc; <verse number="24" style="v"/>and they glorified God in me.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Then after the space of fourteen years I went up again to Jerusalem with Barnabas, taking Titus also with me. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And I went up by revelation; and I laid before them the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="GAL 1:6">1:6</ref>.</char></note>gospel which I preach among the Gentiles but privately before them who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">are</char></char></note>were of repute, lest by any means I should be running, or had run, in vain. <verse number="3" style="v"/>But not even Titus who was with me, being a Greek, was compelled to be circumcised: <verse number="4" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">but</char> it was <char style="it">because of</char></char></note>and that because of the false brethren privily brought in, who came in privily to spy out our liberty which we have in Christ Jesus, that they might bring us into bondage: <verse number="5" style="v"/>to whom we gave place in the way of subjection, no, not for an hour; that the truth of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="GAL 1:6">1:6</ref>.</char></note>gospel might continue with you. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But from those who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">are</char></char></note>were reputed to be somewhat <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">what they once were</char></char></note>(whatsoever they were, it maketh no matter to me: God accepteth not man&#8217;s person)&#8212;they, I say, who were of repute imparted nothing to me: <verse number="7" style="v"/>but contrariwise, when they saw that I had been intrusted with the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="GAL 1:6">1:6</ref>.</char></note>gospel of the uncircumcision, even as Peter with <char style="add">the</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="GAL 1:6">1:6</ref>.</char></note><char style="add">gospel</char> of the circumcision <verse number="8" style="v"/>(for he that wrought for Peter unto the apostleship of the circumcision wrought for me also unto the Gentiles); <verse number="9" style="v"/>and when they perceived the grace that was given unto me, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Jacob</char></char></note>James and Cephas and John, they who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">are</char></char></note>were reputed to be pillars, gave to me and Barnabas the right hands of fellowship, that we should go unto the Gentiles, and they unto the circumcision; <verse number="10" style="v"/>only <char style="add">they would</char> that we should remember the poor; which very thing I was also zealous to do.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>But when Cephas came to Antioch, I resisted him to the face, because he stood condemned. <verse number="12" style="v"/>For before that certain came from James, he ate with the Gentiles; but when they came, he drew back and separated himself, fearing them that were of the circumcision. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And the rest of the Jews dissembled likewise with him; insomuch that even Barnabas was carried away with their dissimulation. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But when I saw that they walked not uprightly according to the truth of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="GAL 1:6">1:6</ref>.</char></note>gospel, I said unto Cephas before <char style="add">them</char> all, If thou, being a Jew, livest as do the Gentiles, and not as do the Jews, how compellest thou the Gentiles to live as do the Jews? <verse number="15" style="v"/>We being Jews by nature, and not sinners of the Gentiles, <verse number="16" style="v"/>yet knowing that a man is not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">accounted righteous</char>: and so elsewhere. Compare <ref loc="ROM 2:13">Rom. 2:13</ref>.</char></note>justified by the works of the law but through faith in Jesus Christ, even we believed on Christ Jesus, that we might be justified by faith in Christ, and not by the works of the law: because by the works of the law shall no flesh be justified. <verse number="17" style="v"/>But if, while we sought to be justified in Christ, we ourselves also were found sinners, is Christ a minister of sin? God forbid. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For if I build up again those things which I destroyed, I prove myself a transgressor. <verse number="19" style="v"/>For I through the law died unto the law, that I might live unto God. <verse number="20" style="v"/>I have been crucified with Christ; and it is no longer I that live, but Christ liveth in me: and that <char style="add">life</char> which I now live in the flesh I live in faith, <char style="add">the faith</char> which is in the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himself up for me. <verse number="21" style="v"/>I do not make void the grace of God: for if righteousness is through the law, then Christ died for nought.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>O foolish Galatians, who did bewitch you, before whose eyes Jesus Christ was openly set forth crucified? <verse number="2" style="v"/>This only would I learn from you, Received ye the Spirit by the works of the law, or by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">message</char></char></note>hearing of faith? <verse number="3" style="v"/>Are ye so foolish? having begun in the Spirit, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">do ye now make an end in the flesh?</char></char></note>are ye now perfected in the flesh? <verse number="4" style="v"/>Did ye suffer so many things in vain? if it be indeed in vain. <verse number="5" style="v"/>He therefore that supplieth to you the Spirit, and worketh <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">powers</char>.</char></note>miracles <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char></char></note>among you, <char style="add">doeth he it</char> by the works of the law, or by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">message</char></char></note>hearing of faith? <verse number="6" style="v"/>Even as Abraham <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 15:6">Gen. 15:6</ref>.</char></note>believed God, and it was reckoned unto him for righteousness. <verse number="7" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Ye perceive</char></char></note>Know therefore that they that are of faith, the same are sons of Abraham. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And the scripture, foreseeing that God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">justifieth</char>.</char></note>would justify the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">nations</char>.</char></note>Gentiles by faith, preached the gospel beforehand unto Abraham, <char style="add">saying</char>, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 12:3">Gen. 12:3</ref>.</char></note>In thee shall all the nations be blessed. <verse number="9" style="v"/>So then they that are of faith are blessed with the faithful Abraham. <verse number="10" style="v"/>For as many as are of the works of the law are under a curse: for it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 27:26">Dt. 27:26</ref>.</char></note>Cursed is every one who continueth not in all things that are written in the book of the law, to do them. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Now that no man is justified <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in</char>.</char></note>by the law before God, is evident: for, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="HAB 2:4">Hab. 2:4</ref>.</char></note>The righteous shall live by faith; <verse number="12" style="v"/>and the law is not of faith; but, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="LEV 18:5">Lev. 18:5</ref>.</char></note>He that doeth them shall live in them. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law, having become a curse for us; for it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="DEU 21:23">Dt. 21:23</ref>.</char></note>Cursed is every one that hangeth on a tree: <verse number="14" style="v"/>that upon the Gentiles might come the blessing of Abraham in Christ Jesus; that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>Brethren, I speak after the manner of men: Though it be but a man&#8217;s covenant, yet when it hath been confirmed, no one maketh it void, or addeth thereto. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Now to Abraham were the promises spoken, and to his seed. He saith not, And to seeds, as of many; but as of one, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 13:15">Gen. 13:15</ref>; <ref loc="GEN 17:8">17:8</ref>.</char></note>And to thy seed, which is Christ. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Now this I say: A covenant confirmed beforehand by God, the law, which came four hundred and thirty years after, doth not disannul, so as to make the promise of none effect. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For if the inheritance is of the law, it is no more of promise: but God hath granted it to Abraham by promise. <verse number="19" style="v"/>What then is the law? It was added because of transgressions, till the seed should come to whom the promise hath been made; <char style="add">and it was</char> ordained through angels by the hand of a mediator. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Now a mediator is not <char style="add">a mediator</char> of one; but God is one. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Is the law then against the promises of God? God forbid: for if there had been a law given which could make alive, verily righteousness would have been of the law. <verse number="22" style="v"/>But the scripture shut up all things under sin, that the promise by faith in Jesus Christ might be given to them that believe.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>But before faith came, we were kept in ward under the law, shut up unto the faith which should afterwards be revealed. <verse number="24" style="v"/>So that the law is become our tutor <char style="add">to bring us</char> unto Christ, that we might be justified by faith. <verse number="25" style="v"/>But now that faith is come, we are no longer under a tutor. <verse number="26" style="v"/>For ye are all sons of God, through faith, in Christ Jesus. <verse number="27" style="v"/>For as many of you as were baptized into Christ did put on Christ. <verse number="28" style="v"/>There can be neither Jew nor Greek, there can be neither bond nor free, there can be no male and female; for ye all are one <char style="add">man</char> in Christ Jesus. <verse number="29" style="v"/>And if ye are Christ&#8217;s, then are ye Abraham&#8217;s seed, heirs according to promise.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>But I say that so long as the heir is a child, he differeth nothing from a bondservant though he is lord of all; <verse number="2" style="v"/>but is under guardians and stewards until the day appointed of the father. <verse number="3" style="v"/>So we also, when we were children, were held in bondage under the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">elements</char>. <ref loc="2PE 3:10">2 Pet. 3:10</ref>, <ref loc="2PE 3:12">12</ref></char></note>rudiments of the world: <verse number="4" style="v"/>but when the fulness of the time came, God sent forth his Son, born of a woman, born under the law, <verse number="5" style="v"/>that he might redeem them that were under the law, that we might receive the adoption of sons. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And because ye are sons, God sent forth the Spirit of his Son into our hearts, crying, Abba, Father. <verse number="7" style="v"/>So that thou art no longer a bondservant, but a son; and if a son, then an heir through God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>Howbeit at that time, not knowing God, ye were in bondage to them that by nature are no gods: <verse number="9" style="v"/>but now that ye have come to know God, or rather to be known by God, how turn ye back again to the weak and beggarly <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">elements</char>. See <ref loc="GAL 4:3">verse 3</ref>.</char></note>rudiments, whereunto ye desire to be in bondage over again? <verse number="10" style="v"/>Ye observe days, and months, and seasons, and years. <verse number="11" style="v"/>I am afraid of you, lest by any means I have bestowed labor upon you in vain.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>I beseech you, brethren, become as I <char style="add">am</char>, for I also <char style="add">am become</char> as ye <char style="add">are</char>. Ye did me no wrong: <verse number="13" style="v"/>but ye know that because of an infirmity of the flesh I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="GAL 1:8">1:8</ref>.</char></note>preached the gospel unto you the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">former</char>.</char></note>first time: <verse number="14" style="v"/>and that which was a temptation to you in my flesh ye despised not, nor <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">spat out</char>.</char></note>rejected; but ye received me as an angel of God, <char style="add">even</char> as Christ Jesus. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Where then is that gratulation <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of yours</char></char></note>of yourselves? for I bear you witness, that, if possible, ye would have plucked out your eyes and given them to me. <verse number="16" style="v"/>So then am I become your enemy, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by dealing truly with you</char></char></note>by telling you the truth? <verse number="17" style="v"/>They zealously seek you in no good way; nay, they desire to shut you out, that ye may seek them. <verse number="18" style="v"/>But it is good to be zealously sought in a good matter at all times, and not only when I am present with you. <verse number="19" style="v"/>My little children, of whom I am again in travail until Christ be formed in you&#8212;<verse number="20" style="v"/>but I could wish to be present with you now, and to change my tone; for I am perplexed about you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>Tell me, ye that desire to be under the law, do ye not hear the law? <verse number="22" style="v"/>For it is written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 16:15">Gen. 16:15</ref>.</char></note>that Abraham had two sons, one by the handmaid, and one by the freewoman. <verse number="23" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 21:2">Gen. 21:2</ref>.</char></note>Howbeit the <char style="add">son</char> by the handmaid is born after the flesh; but the <char style="add">son</char> by the freewoman <char style="add">is born</char> through promise. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Which things contain an allegory: for these <char style="add">women</char> are two covenants; one from mount Sinai, bearing children unto bondage, which is Hagar. <verse number="25" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">For Sinai is a mountain in Arabia</char>.</char></note>Now this Hagar is mount Sinai in Arabia and answereth to the Jerusalem that now is: for she is in bondage with her children. <verse number="26" style="v"/>But the Jerusalem that is above is free, which is our mother. <verse number="27" style="v"/>For it is written,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 54:1">Isa. 54:1</ref>.</char></note>Rejoice, thou barren that bearest not;</para>
	<para style="q1">Break forth and cry, thou that travailest not:</para>
	<para style="q1">For more are the children of the desolate than of her that hath the husband.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="28" style="v"/>Now <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">ye</char>.</char></note>we, brethren, as Isaac was, are children of promise. <verse number="29" style="v"/>But as then he that was born after the flesh persecuted him <char style="add">that was born</char> after the Spirit, so also it is now. <verse number="30" style="v"/>Howbeit what saith the scripture? <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 21:10">Gen. 21:10</ref>, <ref loc="GEN 21:12">12</ref>.</char></note>Cast out the handmaid and her son: for the son of the handmaid shall not inherit with the son of the freewoman. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Wherefore, brethren, we are not children of a handmaid, but of the freewoman.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>For freedom did Christ set us free: stand fast therefore, and be not entangled again in a yoke of bondage.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>Behold, I Paul say unto you, that, if ye receive circumcision, Christ will profit you nothing. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Yea, I testify again to every man that receiveth circumcision, that he is a debtor to do the whole law. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Ye are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">brought to nought</char>. Compare <ref loc="ROM 7:2">Rom. 7:2</ref>, <ref loc="ROM 7:6">6</ref> (in the Greek).</char></note>severed from Christ, ye who would be justified by the law; ye are fallen away from grace. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For we through the Spirit by faith wait for the hope of righteousness. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For in Christ Jesus neither circumcision availeth anything, nor uncircumcision; but faith <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wrought</char></char></note>working through love. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Ye were running well; who hindered you that ye should not obey the truth? <verse number="8" style="v"/>This persuasion <char style="add">came</char> not of him that calleth you. <verse number="9" style="v"/>A little leaven leaveneth the whole lump. <verse number="10" style="v"/>I have confidence to you-ward in the Lord, that ye will be none otherwise minded: but he that troubleth you shall bear his judgment, whosoever he be. <verse number="11" style="v"/>But I, brethren, if I still preach circumcision, why am I still persecuted? then hath the stumbling-block of the cross been done away. <verse number="12" style="v"/>I would that they that unsettle you would even <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">mutilate themselves</char>.</char></note>go beyond circumcision.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>For ye, brethren, were called for freedom; only <char style="add">use</char> not your freedom for an occasion to the flesh, but through love be servants one to another. <verse number="14" style="v"/>For the whole law is fulfilled in one word, <char style="add">even</char> in this: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="LEV 19:18">Lev. 19:18</ref>.</char></note>Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. <verse number="15" style="v"/>But if ye bite and devour one another, take heed that ye be not consumed one of another.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>But I say, Walk by the Spirit, and ye shall not fulfil the lust of the flesh. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For the flesh lusteth against the Spirit, and the Spirit against the flesh; for these are contrary the one to the other; that ye may not do the things that ye would. <verse number="18" style="v"/>But if ye are led by the Spirit, ye are not under the law. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Now the works of the flesh are manifest, which are <char style="add">these</char>: fornication, uncleanness, lasciviousness, <verse number="20" style="v"/>idolatry, sorcery, enmities, strife, jealousies, wraths, factions, divisions, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">heresies</char>.</char></note>parties, <verse number="21" style="v"/>envyings, drunkenness, revellings, and such like; of which I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">tell you plainly</char></char></note>forewarn you, even as I did <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">tell you plainly</char></char></note>forewarn you, that they who practise such things shall not inherit the kingdom of God. <verse number="22" style="v"/>But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, longsuffering, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, <verse number="23" style="v"/>meekness, self-control; against such there is no law. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And they that are of Christ Jesus have crucified the flesh with the passions and the lusts thereof.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>If we live by the Spirit, by the Spirit let us also walk. <verse number="26" style="v"/>Let us not become vainglorious, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">challenging</char></char></note>provoking one another, envying one another.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Brethren, even if a man be overtaken <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by</char></char></note>in any trespass, ye who are spiritual, restore such a one in a spirit of gentleness; looking to thyself, lest thou also be tempted. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Bear ye one another&#8217;s burdens, and so fulfil the law of Christ. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For if a man thinketh himself to be something when he is nothing, he deceiveth himself. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But let each man prove his own work, and then shall he have his glorying in regard of himself alone, and not of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the other</char>. See <ref loc="ROM 13:8">Rom. 13:8</ref>.</char></note>his neighbor. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For each man shall bear his own <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">load</char></char></note>burden.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>But let him that is taught in the word communicate unto him that teacheth in all good things. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Be not deceived; God is not mocked: for whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For he that soweth unto his own flesh shall of the flesh reap corruption; but he that soweth unto the Spirit shall of the Spirit reap eternal life. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And let us not be weary in well-doing: for in due season we shall reap, if we faint not. <verse number="10" style="v"/>So then, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">while</char></char></note>as we have opportunity, let us work that which is good toward all men, and especially toward them that are of the household of the faith.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>See with how large letters I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">have written</char></char></note>write unto you with mine own hand. <verse number="12" style="v"/>As many as desire to make a fair show in the flesh, they compel you to be circumcised; only that they may not be persecuted <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by reason of</char></char></note>for the cross of Christ. <verse number="13" style="v"/>For not even they who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">have been circumcised</char>.</char></note>receive circumcision do themselves keep the law; but they desire to have you circumcised, that they may glory in your flesh. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But far be it from me to glory, save in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">whom</char></char></note>which the world hath been crucified unto me, and I unto the world. <verse number="15" style="v"/>For neither is circumcision anything, nor uncircumcision, but a new <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">creation</char></char></note>creature. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And as many as shall walk by this rule, peace <char style="add">be</char> upon them, and mercy, and upon the Israel of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>Henceforth let no man trouble me; for I bear branded on my body the marks of Jesus.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit, brethren. Amen.</para>
</usx>