<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="EPH" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, to the saints that are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some very ancient authorities omit <char style="it">at Ephesus</char>.</char></note>at Ephesus, and the faithful in Christ Jesus: <verse number="2" style="v"/>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>Blessed <char style="add">be</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">God and the Father</char>. See <ref loc="ROM 15:6">Rom. 15:6</ref> margin.</char></note>the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who hath blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly <char style="add">places</char> in Christ: <verse number="4" style="v"/>even as he chose us in him before the foundation of the world, that we should be holy and without blemish before <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">him: having in love foreordained us</char></char></note>him in love: <verse number="5" style="v"/>having foreordained us unto adoption as sons through Jesus Christ unto himself, according to the good pleasure of his will, <verse number="6" style="v"/>to the praise of the glory of his grace, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wherewith he endued us</char></char></note>which he freely bestowed on us in the Beloved: <verse number="7" style="v"/>in whom we have our redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of our trespasses, according to the riches of his grace, <verse number="8" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wherewith he abounded</char></char></note>which he made to abound toward us in all wisdom and prudence, <verse number="9" style="v"/>making known unto us the mystery of his will, according to his good pleasure which he purposed in him <verse number="10" style="v"/>unto a dispensation of the fulness of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">seasons</char>.</char></note>times, to sum up all things in Christ, the things <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">upon</char>.</char></note>in the heavens, and the things upon the earth; in him, <char style="add">I say</char>, <verse number="11" style="v"/>in whom also we were made a heritage, having been foreordained according to the purpose of him who worketh all things after the counsel of his will; <verse number="12" style="v"/>to the end that we should be unto the praise of his glory, we who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">have</char></char></note>had before hoped in Christ: <verse number="13" style="v"/>in whom ye also, having heard the word of the truth, the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref>.</char></note>gospel of your salvation,&#8212;in whom, having also believed, ye were sealed with the Holy Spirit of promise, <verse number="14" style="v"/>which is an earnest of our inheritance, unto the redemption of <char style="add">God&#8217;s</char> own possession, unto the praise of his glory.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>For this cause I also, having heard of the faith in the Lord Jesus which is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in</char></char></note>among you, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities omit <char style="it">the love</char>.</char></note>the love which <char style="add">ye show</char> toward all the saints, <verse number="16" style="v"/>cease not to give thanks for you, making mention <char style="add">of you</char> in my prayers; <verse number="17" style="v"/>that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give unto you a spirit of wisdom and revelation in the knowledge of him; <verse number="18" style="v"/>having the eyes of your heart enlightened, that ye may know what is the hope of his calling, what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the saints, <verse number="19" style="v"/>and what the exceeding greatness of his power to us-ward who believe, according to that working of the strength of his might <verse number="20" style="v"/>which he wrought in Christ, when he raised him from the dead, and made him to sit at his right hand in the heavenly <char style="add">places</char>, <verse number="21" style="v"/>far above all rule, and authority, and power, and dominion, and every name that is named, not only in this <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">age</char></char></note>world, but also in that which is to come: <verse number="22" style="v"/>and he put all things in subjection under his feet, and gave him to be head over all things to the church, <verse number="23" style="v"/>which is his body, the fulness of him that filleth all in all.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And you <char style="add">did he make alive</char>, when ye were dead through your trespasses and sins, <verse number="2" style="v"/>wherein ye once walked according to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">age</char>.</char></note>course of this world, according to the prince of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">power</char>.</char></note>powers of the air, of the spirit that now worketh in the sons of disobedience; <verse number="3" style="v"/>among whom we also all once lived in the lusts of our flesh, doing the desires of the flesh and of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">thoughts</char>.</char></note>mind, and were by nature children of wrath, even as the rest:&#8212;<verse number="4" style="v"/>but God, being rich in mercy, for his great love wherewith he loved us, <verse number="5" style="v"/>even when we were dead through our trespasses, made us alive together <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">in Christ</char>.</char></note>with Christ (by grace have ye been saved), <verse number="6" style="v"/>and raised us up with him, and made us to sit with him in the heavenly <char style="add">places</char>, in Christ Jesus: <verse number="7" style="v"/>that in the ages to come he might show the exceeding riches of his grace in kindness toward us in Christ Jesus: <verse number="8" style="v"/>for by grace have ye been saved through faith; and that not of yourselves, <char style="add">it is</char> the gift of God; <verse number="9" style="v"/>not of works, that no man should glory. <verse number="10" style="v"/>For we are his workmanship, created in Christ Jesus for good works, which God afore prepared that we should walk in them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>Wherefore remember, that once ye, the Gentiles in the flesh, who are called Uncircumcision by that which is called Circumcision, in the flesh, made by hands; <verse number="12" style="v"/>that ye were at that time separate from Christ, alienated from the commonwealth of Israel, and strangers from the covenants of the promise, having no hope and without God in the world. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But now in Christ Jesus ye that once were far off are made nigh in the blood of Christ. <verse number="14" style="v"/>For he is our peace, who made both one, and brake down the middle wall of partition, <verse number="15" style="v"/>having abolished in his flesh the enmity, <char style="add">even</char> the law of commandments <char style="add">contained</char> in ordinances; that he might create in himself of the two one new man, <char style="add">so</char> making peace; <verse number="16" style="v"/>and might reconcile them both in one body unto God through the cross, having slain the enmity thereby: <verse number="17" style="v"/>and he came and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">brought good tidings of peace</char>. Compare <ref loc="MAT 11:5">Mt. 11:5</ref>.</char></note>preached peace to you that were far off, and peace to them that were nigh: <verse number="18" style="v"/>for through him we both have our access in one Spirit unto the Father. <verse number="19" style="v"/>So then ye are no more strangers and sojourners, but ye are fellow-citizens with the saints, and of the household of God, <verse number="20" style="v"/>being built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Christ Jesus himself being the chief corner stone; <verse number="21" style="v"/>in whom <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">every building</char>.</char></note>each several building, fitly framed together, groweth into a holy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple in the Lord; <verse number="22" style="v"/>in whom ye also are builded together <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">into</char>.</char></note>for a habitation of God in the Spirit.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>For this cause I Paul, the prisoner of Christ Jesus in behalf of you Gentiles,&#8212;<verse number="2" style="v"/>if so be that ye have heard of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stewardship</char></char></note>dispensation of that grace of God which was given me to you-ward; <verse number="3" style="v"/>how that by revelation was made known unto me the mystery, as I wrote before in few words, <verse number="4" style="v"/>whereby, when ye read, ye can perceive my understanding in the mystery of Christ; <verse number="5" style="v"/>which in other generations was not made known unto the sons of men, as it hath now been revealed unto his holy apostles and prophets in the Spirit; <verse number="6" style="v"/><char style="add">to wit</char>, that the Gentiles are fellow-heirs, and fellow-members of the body, and fellow-partakers of the promise in Christ Jesus through the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref> margin.</char></note>gospel, <verse number="7" style="v"/>whereof I was made a minister, according to the gift of that grace of God which was given me according to the working of his power. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Unto me, who am less than the least of all saints, was this grace given, to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bring good tidings of the etc.</char> Compare <ref loc="EPH 2:17">2:17</ref>.</char></note>preach unto the Gentiles the unsearchable riches of Christ; <verse number="9" style="v"/>and to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">bring to light what is</char>.</char></note>make all men see what is the dispensation of the mystery which for ages hath been hid in God who created all things; <verse number="10" style="v"/>to the intent that now unto the principalities and the powers in the heavenly <char style="add">places</char> might be made known through the church the manifold wisdom of God, <verse number="11" style="v"/>according to the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">purpose of the ages</char>.</char></note>eternal purpose which he purposed in Christ Jesus our Lord: <verse number="12" style="v"/>in whom we have boldness and access in confidence through <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the faith of him</char></char></note>our faith in him. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Wherefore I ask that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">I</char></char></note>ye may not faint at my tribulations for you, which <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">is</char></char></note>are your glory.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>For this cause I bow my knees unto the Father, <verse number="15" style="v"/>from whom every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">fatherhood</char>.</char></note>family in heaven and on earth is named, <verse number="16" style="v"/>that he would grant you, according to the riches of his glory, that ye may be strengthened with power through his Spirit in the inward man; <verse number="17" style="v"/>that Christ may dwell in your hearts through faith; to the end that ye, being rooted and grounded in love, <verse number="18" style="v"/>may be strong to apprehend with all the saints what is the breadth and length and height and depth, <verse number="19" style="v"/>and to know the love of Christ which passeth knowledge, that ye may be filled unto all the fulness of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>Now unto him that is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think, according to the power that worketh in us, <verse number="21" style="v"/>unto him <char style="add">be</char> the glory in the church and in Christ Jesus unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">all the generations of the age of the ages</char>.</char></note>all generations for ever and ever. Amen.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>I therefore, the prisoner in the Lord, beseech you to walk worthily of the calling wherewith ye were called, <verse number="2" style="v"/>with all lowliness and meekness, with longsuffering, forbearing one another in love; <verse number="3" style="v"/>giving diligence to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. <verse number="4" style="v"/><char style="add">There is</char> one body, and one Spirit, even as also ye were called in one hope of your calling; <verse number="5" style="v"/>one Lord, one faith, one baptism, <verse number="6" style="v"/>one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in all. <verse number="7" style="v"/>But unto each one of us was the grace given according to the measure of the gift of Christ. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Wherefore he saith,</para>
	<para style="q1"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 68:18">Ps. 68:18</ref>.</char></note>When he ascended on high, he led captivity captive,</para>
	<para style="q1">And gave gifts unto men.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="9" style="v"/>(Now this, He ascended, what is it but that he also descended <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities insert <char style="it">first</char>.</char></note>into the lower parts of the earth? <verse number="10" style="v"/>He that descended is the same also that ascended far above all the heavens, that he might fill all things.) <verse number="11" style="v"/>And he gave some <char style="add">to be</char> apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some, pastors and teachers; <verse number="12" style="v"/>for the perfecting of the saints, unto the work of ministering, unto the building up of the body of Christ: <verse number="13" style="v"/>till we all attain unto the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a fullgrown man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ: <verse number="14" style="v"/>that we may be no longer children, tossed to and fro and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the sleight of men, in craftiness, after the wiles of error; <verse number="15" style="v"/>but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">dealing truly</char></char></note>speaking truth in love, may grow up in all things into him, who is the head, <char style="add">even</char> Christ; <verse number="16" style="v"/>from whom all the body fitly framed and knit together <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">through every joint of the supply</char>.</char></note>through that which every joint supplieth, according to the working in <char style="add">due</char> measure of each several part, maketh the increase of the body unto the building up of itself in love.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>This I say therefore, and testify in the Lord, that ye no longer walk as the Gentiles also walk, in the vanity of their mind, <verse number="18" style="v"/>being darkened in their understanding, alienated from the life of God, because of the ignorance that is in them, because of the hardening of their heart; <verse number="19" style="v"/>who being past feeling gave themselves up to lasciviousness, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to make a trade of</char></char></note>to work all uncleanness with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">covetousness</char>. Compare <ref loc="EPH 5:3">5:3</ref> <ref loc="COL 3:5">Col. 3:5</ref>.</char></note>greediness. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But ye did not so learn Christ; <verse number="21" style="v"/>if so be that ye heard him, and were taught in him, even as truth is in Jesus: <verse number="22" style="v"/>that ye put away, as concerning your former manner of life, the old man, that waxeth corrupt after the lusts of deceit; <verse number="23" style="v"/>and that ye be renewed in the spirit of your mind, <verse number="24" style="v"/>and put on the new man, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that is after God, created etc.</char></char></note>that after God hath been created in righteousness and holiness of truth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v"/>Wherefore, putting away falsehood, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ZEC 8:16">Zech. 8:16</ref>.</char></note>speak ye truth each one with his neighbor: for we are members one of another. <verse number="26" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PSA 4:4">Ps. 4:4</ref>.</char></note>Be ye angry, and sin not: let not the sun go down upon your <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">provocation</char>.</char></note>wrath: <verse number="27" style="v"/>neither give place to the devil. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Let him that stole steal no more: but rather let him labor, working with his hands the thing that is good, that he may have whereof to give to him that hath need. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Let no corrupt speech proceed out of your mouth, but such as is good for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the building up of the need</char>.</char></note>edifying as the need may be, that it may give grace to them that hear. <verse number="30" style="v"/>And grieve not the Holy Spirit of God, in whom ye were sealed unto the day of redemption. <verse number="31" style="v"/>Let all bitterness, and wrath, and anger, and clamor, and railing, be put away from you, with all malice: <verse number="32" style="v"/>and be ye kind one to another, tenderhearted, forgiving each other, even as God also in Christ forgave <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">us</char>.</char></note>you.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Be ye therefore imitators of God, as beloved children; <verse number="2" style="v"/>and walk in love, even as Christ also loved you, and gave himself up for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">you</char>.</char></note>us, an offering and a sacrifice to God for an odor of a sweet smell.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>But fornication, and all uncleanness, or covetousness, let it not even be named among you, as becometh saints; <verse number="4" style="v"/>nor filthiness, nor foolish talking, or jesting, which are not befitting: but rather giving of thanks. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For this ye know of a surety, that no fornicator, nor unclean person, nor covetous man, who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and God. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Let no man deceive you with empty words: for because of these things cometh the wrath of God upon the sons of disobedience. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Be not ye therefore partakers with them; <verse number="8" style="v"/>for ye were once darkness, but are now light in the Lord: walk as children of light <verse number="9" style="v"/>(for the fruit of the light is in all goodness and righteousness and truth), <verse number="10" style="v"/>proving what is well-pleasing unto the Lord; <verse number="11" style="v"/>and have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather even <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">convict</char></char></note>reprove them; <verse number="12" style="v"/>for the things which are done by them in secret it is a shame even to speak of. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But all things when they are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">convicted</char></char></note>reproved are made manifest by the light: for everything that is made manifest is light. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Wherefore <char style="add">he</char> saith, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">(?). Compare <ref loc="1TI 3:16">1 Tim. 3:16</ref>.</char></note>Awake, thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead, and Christ shall shine upon thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>Look therefore carefully how ye walk, not as unwise, but as wise; <verse number="16" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">buying up the opportunity</char>.</char></note>redeeming the time, because the days are evil. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Wherefore be ye not foolish, but understand what the will of the Lord is. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And be not drunken with wine, wherein is riot, but be filled <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in spirit</char></char></note>with the Spirit; <verse number="19" style="v"/>speaking <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to yourselves</char></char></note>one to another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody with your heart to the Lord; <verse number="20" style="v"/>giving thanks always for all things in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the God and Father</char>.</char></note>God, even the Father; <verse number="21" style="v"/>subjecting yourselves one to another in the fear of Christ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>Wives, <char style="add">be in subjection</char> unto your own husbands, as unto the Lord. <verse number="23" style="v"/>For the husband is the head of the wife, as Christ also is the head of the church, <char style="add">being</char> himself the saviour of the body. <verse number="24" style="v"/>But as the church is subject to Christ, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">so</char> are <char style="it">the wives also</char></char></note>so <char style="add">let</char> the wives also <char style="add">be</char> to their husbands in everything. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Husbands, love your wives, even as Christ also loved the church, and gave himself up for it; <verse number="26" style="v"/>that he might sanctify it, having cleansed it by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">laver</char>.</char></note>washing of water with the word, <verse number="27" style="v"/>that he might present the church to himself a glorious <char style="add">church</char>, not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing; but that it should be holy and without blemish. <verse number="28" style="v"/>Even so ought husbands also to love their own wives as their own bodies. He that loveth his own wife loveth himself: <verse number="29" style="v"/>for no man ever hated his own flesh; but nourisheth and cherisheth it, even as Christ also the church; <verse number="30" style="v"/>because we are members of his body. <verse number="31" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="GEN 2:24">Gen. 2:24</ref>.</char></note>For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife; and the two shall become one flesh. <verse number="32" style="v"/>This mystery is great: but I speak in regard of Christ and of the church. <verse number="33" style="v"/>Nevertheless do ye also severally love each one his own wife even as himself; and <char style="add">let</char> the wife <char style="add">see</char> that she fear her husband.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Children, obey your parents in the Lord: for this is right. <verse number="2" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="EXO 20:12">Ex. 20:12</ref>; <ref loc="DEU 5:16">Dt. 5:16</ref>.</char></note>Honor thy father and mother (which is the first commandment with promise), <verse number="3" style="v"/>that it may be well with thee, and thou <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">shalt</char></char></note>mayest live long on the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">land</char></char></note>earth. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And, ye fathers, provoke not your children to wrath: but nurture them in the chastening and admonition of the Lord.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Bondservants</char>.</char></note>Servants, be obedient unto them that according to the flesh are your <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lords</char>.</char></note>masters, with fear and trembling, in singleness of your heart, as unto Christ; <verse number="6" style="v"/>not in the way of eyeservice, as men-pleasers; but as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants of Christ, doing the will of God from the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">soul</char>.</char></note>heart; <verse number="7" style="v"/>with good will doing service, as unto the Lord, and not unto men: <verse number="8" style="v"/>knowing that whatsoever good thing each one doeth, the same shall he receive again from the Lord, whether <char style="add">he be</char> bond or free. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And, ye <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lords</char>.</char></note>masters, do the same things unto them, and forbear threatening: knowing that he who is both their Master and yours is in heaven, and there is no respect of persons with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Henceforth</char></char></note>Finally, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">be made powerful</char>.</char></note>be strong in the Lord, and in the strength of his might. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Put on the whole armor of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil. <verse number="12" style="v"/>For our wrestling is not against <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">blood and flesh</char>.</char></note>flesh and blood, but against the principalities, against the powers, against the world-rulers of this darkness, against the spiritual <char style="add">hosts</char> of wickedness in the heavenly <char style="add">places</char>. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Wherefore take up the whole armor of God, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and, having done all, to stand. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Stand therefore, having girded your loins with truth, and having put on the breastplate of righteousness, <verse number="15" style="v"/>and having shod your feet with the preparation of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref> margin.</char></note>gospel of peace; <verse number="16" style="v"/>withal taking up the shield of faith, wherewith ye shall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the evil <char style="add">one</char>. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God: <verse number="18" style="v"/>with all prayer and supplication praying at all seasons in the Spirit, and watching thereunto in all perseverance and supplication for all the saints, <verse number="19" style="v"/>and on my behalf, that utterance may be given unto me <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in opening my mouth with boldness, to make known</char></char></note>in opening my mouth, to make known with boldness the mystery of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref> margin.</char></note>gospel, <verse number="20" style="v"/>for which I am an ambassador in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">a chain</char>.</char></note>chains; that in it I may speak boldly, as I ought to speak.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>But that ye also may know my affairs, how I do, Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, shall make known to you all things: <verse number="22" style="v"/>whom I have sent unto you for this very purpose, that ye may know our state, and that he may comfort your hearts.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>Peace be to the brethren, and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. <verse number="24" style="v"/>Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jesus Christ <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in incorruption</char>. See <ref loc="ROM 2:7">Rom. 2:7</ref>.</char></note>with <char style="add">a love</char> incorruptible.</para>
</usx>