<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="PHP" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Paul and Timothy, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants of Christ Jesus, to all the saints in Christ Jesus that are at Philippi, with the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">overseers</char></char></note>bishops and deacons: <verse number="2" style="v"/>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>I thank my God upon all my remembrance of you, <verse number="4" style="v"/>always in every supplication of mine on behalf of you all making my supplication with joy, <verse number="5" style="v"/>for your fellowship in furtherance of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>: and so elsewhere. See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref>.</char></note>gospel from the first day until now; <verse number="6" style="v"/>being confident of this very thing, that he who began a good work in you will perfect it until the day of Jesus Christ: <verse number="7" style="v"/>even as it is right for me to be thus minded on behalf of you all, because <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">ye have me in your heart</char></char></note>I have you in my heart, inasmuch as, both in my bonds and in the defence and confirmation of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="PHP 1:5">verse 5</ref>.</char></note>gospel, ye all are partakers with me of grace. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For God is my witness, how I long after you all in the tender mercies of Christ Jesus. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in knowledge and all discernment; <verse number="10" style="v"/>so that ye may <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">distinguish the things that differ</char></char></note>approve the things that are excellent; that ye may be sincere and void of offence unto the day of Christ; <verse number="11" style="v"/>being filled with the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">fruit</char>.</char></note>fruits of righteousness, which are through Jesus Christ, unto the glory and praise of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Now I would have you know, brethren, that the things <char style="add">which happened</char> unto me have fallen out rather unto the progress of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="PHP 1:5">verse 5</ref>.</char></note>gospel; <verse number="13" style="v"/>so that my bonds became manifest in Christ <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in the whole Praetorium</char>.</char></note>throughout the whole praetorian guard, and to all the rest; <verse number="14" style="v"/>and that most of the brethren in the Lord, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">trusting in my bonds</char>.</char></note>being confident through my bonds, are more abundantly bold to speak the word of God without fear. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Some indeed preach Christ even of envy and strife; and some also of good will: <verse number="16" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">they that are moved by love</char> do it, <char style="it">knowing etc.</char></char></note>the one <char style="add">do it</char> of love, knowing that I am set for the defence of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="PHP 1:5">verse 5</ref>.</char></note>gospel; <verse number="17" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">but they that are factious proclaim Christ, not etc.</char></char></note>but the other proclaim Christ of faction, not sincerely, thinking to raise up affliction for me in my bonds. <verse number="18" style="v"/>What then? only that in every way, whether in pretence or in truth, Christ is proclaimed; and therein I rejoice, yea, and will rejoice. <verse number="19" style="v"/>For I know that this shall turn out to my salvation, through your supplication and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ, <verse number="20" style="v"/>according to my earnest expectation and hope, that in nothing shall I be put to shame, but <char style="add">that</char> with all boldness, as always, <char style="add">so</char> now also Christ shall be magnified in my body, whether by life, or by death. <verse number="21" style="v"/>For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain. <verse number="22" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">But if to live in the flesh</char> be my lot, <char style="it">this is the fruit of my work: and what I shall choose I know not</char>.</char></note>But if to live in the flesh,&#8212;<char style="add">if</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">this is for me fruit of work</char>.</char></note>this shall bring fruit from my work, then <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">what shall I choose?</char></char></note>what I shall choose I know not. <verse number="23" style="v"/>But I am in a strait betwixt the two, having the desire to depart and be with Christ; for it is very far better: <verse number="24" style="v"/>yet to abide in the flesh is more needful for your sake. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And having this confidence, I know that I shall abide, yea, and abide with you all, for your progress and joy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">of faith</char></char></note>in the faith; <verse number="26" style="v"/>that your glorying may abound in Christ Jesus in me through my presence with you again. <verse number="27" style="v"/>Only <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">behave as citizens worthily</char>. Compare <ref loc="PHP 3:20">3:20</ref>.</char></note>let your manner of life be worthy of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="PHP 1:5">verse 5</ref>.</char></note>gospel of Christ: that, whether I come and see you or be absent, I may hear of your state, that ye stand fast in one spirit, with one soul striving <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">with</char>.</char></note>for the faith of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="PHP 1:5">verse 5</ref>.</char></note>gospel; <verse number="28" style="v"/>and in nothing affrighted by the adversaries: which is for them an evident token of perdition, but of your salvation, and that from God; <verse number="29" style="v"/>because to you it hath been granted in the behalf of Christ, not only to believe on him, but also to suffer in his behalf: <verse number="30" style="v"/>having the same conflict which ye saw in me, and now hear to be in me.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>If there is therefore any exhortation in Christ, if any <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">persuasion</char></char></note>consolation of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any tender mercies and compassions, <verse number="2" style="v"/>make full my joy, that ye be of the same mind, having the same love, being of one accord, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">of the same mind</char>.</char></note>of one mind; <verse number="3" style="v"/><char style="add">doing</char> nothing through faction or through vainglory, but in lowliness of mind each counting other better than himself; <verse number="4" style="v"/>not looking each of you to his own things, but each of you also to the things of others. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Have this mind in you, which was also in Christ Jesus: <verse number="6" style="v"/>who, existing in the form of God, counted not the being on an equality with God a thing to be grasped, <verse number="7" style="v"/>but emptied himself, taking the form of a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">becoming in</char>.</char></note>being made in the likeness of men; <verse number="8" style="v"/>and being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, becoming obedient <char style="add">even</char> unto death, yea, the death of the cross. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Wherefore also God highly exalted him, and gave unto him the name which is above every name; <verse number="10" style="v"/>that in the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of <char style="add">things</char> in heaven and <char style="add">things</char> on earth and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, things <char style="it">of the world below</char></char></note><char style="add">things</char> under the earth, <verse number="11" style="v"/>and that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>So then, my beloved, even as ye have always obeyed, not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">as</char>.</char></note>as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling; <verse number="13" style="v"/>for it is God who worketh in you both to will and to work, for his good pleasure. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Do all things without murmurings and questionings: <verse number="15" style="v"/>that ye may become blameless and harmless, children of God without blemish in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation, among whom ye are seen as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">luminaries</char>. <ref loc="WIS 13:2">Wisd. 13:2</ref>; compare <ref loc="REV 21:11">Rev. 21:11</ref>.</char></note>lights in the world, <verse number="16" style="v"/>holding forth the word of life; that I may have whereof to glory in the day of Christ, that I did not run in vain neither labor in vain. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Yea, and if I am <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">poured out as a drink-offering</char>.</char></note>offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I joy, and rejoice with you all: <verse number="18" style="v"/>and in the same manner do ye also joy, and rejoice with me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>But I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy shortly unto you, that I also may be of good comfort, when I know your state. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For I have no man likeminded, who will care <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">genuinely</char>.</char></note>truly for your state. <verse number="21" style="v"/>For they all seek their own, not the things of Jesus Christ. <verse number="22" style="v"/>But ye know the proof of him, that, as a child <char style="add">serveth</char> a father, <char style="add">so</char> he served with me in furtherance of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="PHP 1:5">1:5</ref>.</char></note>gospel. <verse number="23" style="v"/>Him therefore I hope to send forthwith, so soon as I shall see how it will go with me: <verse number="24" style="v"/>but I trust in the Lord that I myself also shall come shortly. <verse number="25" style="v"/>But I counted it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow-worker and fellow-soldier, and your <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">apostle</char>.</char></note>messenger and minister to my need; <verse number="26" style="v"/>since he longed <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">to see you all</char>.</char></note>after you all, and was sore troubled, because ye had heard that he was sick: <verse number="27" style="v"/>for indeed he was sick nigh unto death: but God had mercy on him; and not on him only, but on me also, that I might not have sorrow upon sorrow. <verse number="28" style="v"/>I have sent him therefore the more diligently, that, when ye see him again, ye may rejoice, and that I may be the less sorrowful. <verse number="29" style="v"/>Receive him therefore in the Lord with all joy; and hold such in honor: <verse number="30" style="v"/>because for the work of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">the Lord</char>.</char></note>Christ he came nigh unto death, hazarding his life to supply that which was lacking in your service toward me.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same things to you, to me indeed is not irksome, but for you it is safe. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Beware of the dogs, beware of the evil workers, beware of the concision: <verse number="3" style="v"/>for we are the circumcision, who worship by the Spirit of God, and glory in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh: <verse number="4" style="v"/>though I myself might have confidence even in the flesh: if any other man <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">seemeth</char></char></note>thinketh to have confidence in the flesh, I yet more: <verse number="5" style="v"/>circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew of Hebrews; as touching the law, a Pharisee; <verse number="6" style="v"/>as touching zeal, persecuting the church; as touching the righteousness which is in the law, found blameless. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Howbeit what things were <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">gains</char>.</char></note>gain to me, these have I counted loss for Christ. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Yea verily, and I count all things to be loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord: for whom I suffered the loss of all things, and do count them but refuse, that I may gain Christ, <verse number="9" style="v"/>and be found in him, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">not having</char> as <char style="it">my righteousness that which is of the law</char></char></note>not having a righteousness of mine own, <char style="add">even</char> that which is of the law, but that which is through faith in Christ, the righteousness which is from God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">upon</char>.</char></note>by faith: <verse number="10" style="v"/>that I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, becoming conformed unto his death; <verse number="11" style="v"/>if by any means I may attain unto the resurrection from the dead. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Not that I have already obtained, or am already made perfect: but I press on, if so be that I may <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lay hold, seeing that also I was laid hold on</char></char></note>lay hold on that for which also I was laid hold on by Christ Jesus. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Brethren, I count not myself <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities omit <char style="it">yet</char>.</char></note>yet to have laid hold: but one thing <char style="add">I do</char>, forgetting the things which are behind, and stretching forward to the things which are before, <verse number="14" style="v"/>I press on toward the goal unto the prize of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">upward</char></char></note>high calling of God in Christ Jesus. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Let us therefore, as many as are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">full-grown</char>. <ref loc="1CO 2:6">1 Cor. 2:6</ref></char></note>perfect, be thus minded: and if in anything ye are otherwise minded, this also shall God reveal unto you: <verse number="16" style="v"/>only, whereunto we have attained, by that same <char style="add">rule</char> let us walk.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>Brethren, be ye imitators together of me, and mark them that so walk even as ye have us for an ensample. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For many walk, of whom I told you often, and now tell you even weeping, <char style="add">that they are</char> the enemies of the cross of Christ: <verse number="19" style="v"/>whose end is perdition, whose god is the belly, and <char style="add">whose</char> glory is in their shame, who mind earthly things. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For our <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">commonwealth</char></char></note>citizenship is in heaven; whence also we wait for a Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ: <verse number="21" style="v"/>who shall fashion anew the body of our humiliation, <char style="add">that it may be</char> conformed to the body of his glory, according to the working whereby he is able even to subject all things unto himself.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Wherefore, my brethren beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, so stand fast in the Lord, my beloved.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>I exhort Euodia, and I exhort Syntyche, to be of the same mind in the Lord. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Yea, I beseech thee also, true yokefellow, help these women, for they labored with me in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="PHP 1:5">1:5</ref>.</char></note>gospel, with Clement also, and the rest of my fellow-workers, whose names are in the book of life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>Rejoice in the Lord always: again I will say, Rejoice. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Let your <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gentleness</char>. Compare <ref loc="2CO 10:1">2 Cor. 10:1</ref>.</char></note>forbearance be known unto all men. The Lord is at hand. <verse number="6" style="v"/>In nothing be anxious; but in everything by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your requests be made known unto God. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, shall guard your hearts and your thoughts in Christ Jesus.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>Finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">reverend</char>.</char></note>honorable, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are lovely, whatsoever things are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gracious</char></char></note>of good report; if there be any virtue, and if there be any praise, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">take account of</char>.</char></note>think on these things. <verse number="9" style="v"/>The things which ye both learned and received and heard and saw in me, these things do: and the God of peace shall be with you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>But I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">rejoiced</char>.</char></note>rejoice in the Lord greatly, that now at length ye have revived your thought for me; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">seeing that</char></char></note>wherein ye did indeed take thought, but ye lacked opportunity. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Not that I speak in respect of want: for I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, therein to be content. <verse number="12" style="v"/>I know how to be abased, and I know also how to abound: in everything and in all things have I learned the secret both to be filled and to be hungry, both to abound and to be in want. <verse number="13" style="v"/>I can do all things in him that strengtheneth me. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Howbeit ye did well that ye had fellowship with my affliction. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And ye yourselves also know, ye Philippians, that in the beginning of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="PHP 1:5">1:5</ref>.</char></note>gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church had fellowship with me in the matter of giving and receiving but ye only; <verse number="16" style="v"/>for even in Thessalonica ye sent once and again unto my need. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Not that I seek for the gift; but I seek for the fruit that increaseth to your account. <verse number="18" style="v"/>But I have all things, and abound: I am filled, having received from Epaphroditus the things <char style="add">that came</char> from you, an odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable, well-pleasing to God. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And my God shall supply every need of yours according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Now unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">God and our Father</char></char></note>our God and Father <char style="add">be</char> the glory <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever. Amen.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren that are with me salute you. <verse number="22" style="v"/>All the saints salute you, especially they that are of Caesar&#8217;s household.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v"/>The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit.</para>
</usx>