<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="2TH" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Paul, and Silvanus, and Timothy, unto the church of the Thessalonians in God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ; <verse number="2" style="v"/>Grace to you and peace from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>We are bound to give thanks to God always for you, brethren, even as it is meet, for that your faith groweth exceedingly, and the love of each one of you all toward one another aboundeth; <verse number="4" style="v"/>so that we ourselves glory in you in the churches of God for your <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience and faith in all your persecutions and in the afflictions which ye endure; <verse number="5" style="v"/><char style="add">which is</char> a manifest token of the righteous judgment of God; to the end that ye may be counted worthy of the kingdom of God, for which ye also suffer: <verse number="6" style="v"/>if so be that it is a righteous thing with God to recompense affliction to them that afflict you, <verse number="7" style="v"/>and to you that are afflicted rest with us, at the revelation of the Lord Jesus from heaven with the angels of his power in flaming fire, <verse number="8" style="v"/>rendering vengeance to them that know not God, and to them that obey not the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>: and so elsewhere. See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref>.</char></note>gospel of our Lord Jesus: <verse number="9" style="v"/>who shall suffer punishment, <char style="add">even</char> eternal destruction from the face of the Lord and from the glory of his might, <verse number="10" style="v"/>when he shall come to be glorified in his saints, and to be marvelled at in all them that believed (because our testimony unto you was believed) in that day. <verse number="11" style="v"/>To which end we also pray always for you, that our God may count you worthy of your calling, and fulfil every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good pleasure of goodness</char>. Compare <ref loc="ROM 10:1">Rom. 10:1</ref>.</char></note>desire of goodness and <char style="add">every</char> work of faith, with power; <verse number="12" style="v"/>that the name of our Lord Jesus may be glorified in you, and ye in him, according to the grace of our God and the Lord Jesus Christ.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Now we beseech you, brethren, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in behalf of</char>.</char></note>touching the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">presence</char>.</char></note>coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, and our gathering together unto him; <verse number="2" style="v"/>to the end that ye be not quickly shaken from your mind, nor yet be troubled, either by spirit, or by word, or by epistle as from us, as that the day of the Lord is just at hand; <verse number="3" style="v"/>let no man beguile you in any wise: for <char style="add">it will not be</char>, except the falling away come first, and the man of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">lawlessness</char>.</char></note>sin be revealed, the son of perdition, <verse number="4" style="v"/>he that opposeth and exalteth himself against all that is called God or <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">an object of worship</char>. <ref loc="ACT 17:23">Acts 17:23</ref>.</char></note>that is worshipped; so that he sitteth in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple of God, setting himself forth as God. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Remember ye not, that, when I was yet with you, I told you these things? <verse number="6" style="v"/>And now ye know that which restraineth, to the end that he may be revealed in his own season. <verse number="7" style="v"/>For the mystery of lawlessness doth already work: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">only until he that now restraineth be taken etc.</char></char></note>only <char style="add">there is</char> one that restraineth now, until he be taken out of the way. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And then shall be revealed the lawless one, whom the Lord <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">Jesus</char>.</char></note>Jesus shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">consume</char>.</char></note>slay with the breath of his mouth, and bring to nought by the manifestation of his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">presence</char>.</char></note>coming; <verse number="9" style="v"/><char style="add">even he</char>, whose <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">presence</char>.</char></note>coming is according to the working of Satan with all <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">power and signs and wonders of falsehood</char>.</char></note>power and signs and lying wonders, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and with all deceit of unrighteousness for them that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">are perishing</char></char></note>perish; because they received not the love of the truth, that they might be saved. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And for this cause God sendeth them a working of error, that they should believe a lie: <verse number="12" style="v"/>that they all might be judged who believed not the truth, but had pleasure in unrighteousness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>But we are bound to give thanks to God always for you, brethren beloved of the Lord, for that God chose you <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">as firstfruits</char>.</char></note>from the beginning unto salvation in sanctification of the Spirit and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">faith</char></char></note>belief of the truth: <verse number="14" style="v"/>whereunto he called you through our <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="2TH 1:8">1:8</ref>.</char></note>gospel, to the obtaining of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse number="15" style="v"/>So then, brethren, stand fast, and hold the traditions which ye were taught, whether by word, or by epistle of ours.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>Now our Lord Jesus Christ himself, and God our Father who loved us and gave us eternal comfort and good hope through grace, <verse number="17" style="v"/>comfort your hearts and establish them in every good work and word.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Finally, brethren, pray for us, that the word of the Lord may run and be glorified, even as also <char style="add">it is</char> with you; <verse number="2" style="v"/>and that we may be delivered from unreasonable and evil men; for all have not faith. <verse number="3" style="v"/>But the Lord is faithful, who shall establish you, and guard you from <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">evil</char></char></note>the evil <char style="add">one</char>. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And we have confidence in the Lord touching you, that ye both do and will do the things which we command. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the Lord direct your hearts into the love of God, and into the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience of Christ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>Now we command you, brethren, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye withdraw yourselves from every brother that walketh disorderly, and not after the tradition which <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">ye</char>.</char></note>they received of us. <verse number="7" style="v"/>For yourselves know how ye ought to imitate us: for we behaved not ourselves disorderly among you; <verse number="8" style="v"/>neither did we eat bread for nought at any man&#8217;s hand, but in labor and travail, working night and day, that we might not burden any of you: <verse number="9" style="v"/>not because we have not the right, but to make ourselves an ensample unto you, that ye should imitate us. <verse number="10" style="v"/>For even when we were with you, this we commanded you, If any will not work, neither let him eat. <verse number="11" style="v"/>For we hear of some that walk among you disorderly, that work not at all, but are busybodies. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Now them that are such we command and exhort in the Lord Jesus Christ, that with quietness they work, and eat their own bread. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But ye, brethren, be not weary in well-doing. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And if any man obeyeth not our word by this epistle, note that man, that ye have no company with him, to the end that he may be ashamed. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And <char style="add">yet</char> count him not as an enemy, but admonish him as a brother.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>Now the Lord of peace himself give you peace at all times in all ways. The Lord be with you all.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>The salutation of me Paul with mine own hand, which is the token in every epistle: so I write. <verse number="18" style="v"/>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all.</para>
</usx>