<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="2TI" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, according to the promise of the life which is in Christ Jesus, <verse number="2" style="v"/>to Timothy, my beloved child: Grace, mercy, peace, from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>I thank God, whom I serve from my forefathers in a pure conscience, how unceasing is my remembrance of thee in my supplications, night and day <verse number="4" style="v"/>longing to see thee, remembering thy tears, that I may be filled with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">joy in being reminded</char></char></note>joy; <verse number="5" style="v"/>having been reminded of the unfeigned faith that is in thee; which dwelt first in thy grandmother Lois, and thy mother Eunice; and, I am persuaded, in thee also. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For which cause I put thee in remembrance that thou <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">stir into flame</char>.</char></note>stir up the gift of God, which is in thee through the laying on of my hands. <verse number="7" style="v"/>For God gave us not a spirit of fearfulness; but of power and love and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sobering</char>.</char></note>discipline. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Be not ashamed therefore of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner: but suffer hardship with the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>: and so elsewhere. See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 4:23">Mt. 4:23</ref>.</char></note>gospel according to the power of God; <verse number="9" style="v"/>who saved us, and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given us in Christ Jesus <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">long ages ago</char></char></note>before times eternal, <verse number="10" style="v"/>but hath now been manifested by the appearing of our Saviour Christ Jesus, who abolished death, and brought life and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">incorruption</char>. See <ref loc="ROM 2:7">Rom. 2:7</ref>.</char></note>immortality to light through the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">good tidings</char>. See <ref loc="2TI 1:8">verse 8</ref>.</char></note>gospel, <verse number="11" style="v"/>whereunto I was appointed a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">herald</char>.</char></note>preacher, and an apostle, and a teacher. <verse number="12" style="v"/>For which cause I suffer also these things: yet I am not ashamed; for I know him whom I have believed, and I am persuaded that he is able to guard <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">that which he hath committed unto me</char>. Greek <char style="it">my deposit</char>.</char></note>that which I have committed unto him against that day. <verse number="13" style="v"/>Hold the pattern of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">healthful</char>.</char></note>sound words which thou hast heard from me, in faith and love which is in Christ Jesus. <verse number="14" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">The good deposit</char>.</char></note>That good thing which was committed unto <char style="add">thee</char> guard through the Holy Spirit which dwelleth in us.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>This thou knowest, that all that are in Asia turned away from me; of whom are Phygelus and Hermogenes. <verse number="16" style="v"/>The Lord grant mercy unto the house of Onesiphorus: for he oft refreshed me, and was not ashamed of my chain; <verse number="17" style="v"/>but, when he was in Rome, he sought me diligently, and found me <verse number="18" style="v"/>(the Lord grant unto him to find mercy of the Lord in that day); and in how many things he ministered at Ephesus, thou knowest very well.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>Thou therefore, my child, be strengthened in the grace that is in Christ Jesus. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the things which thou hast heard from me among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithful men, who shall be able to teach others also. <verse number="3" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Take thy part in suffering hardship, as etc.</char></char></note>Suffer hardship with <char style="add">me</char>, as a good soldier of Christ Jesus. <verse number="4" style="v"/>No soldier on service entangleth himself in the affairs of <char style="add">this</char> life; that he may please him who enrolled him as a soldier. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And if also a man contend in the games, he is not crowned, except he have contended lawfully. <verse number="6" style="v"/>The husbandman that laboreth must be the first to partake of the fruits. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Consider what I say; for the Lord shall give thee understanding in all things. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Remember Jesus Christ, risen from the dead, of the seed of David, according to my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="2TI 1:8">1:8</ref>.</char></note>gospel: <verse number="9" style="v"/>wherein I suffer hardship unto bonds, as a malefactor; but the word of God is not bound. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Therefore I endure all things for the elect&#8217;s sake, that they also may obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Faithful is the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">saying; for if etc.</char></char></note>saying: For if we died with him, we shall also live with him: <verse number="12" style="v"/>if we endure, we shall also reign with him: if we shall deny him, he also will deny us: <verse number="13" style="v"/>if we are faithless, he abideth faithful; for he cannot deny himself.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>Of these things put them in remembrance, charging <char style="add">them</char> in the sight of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">God</char>.</char></note>the Lord, that they strive not about words, to no profit, to the subverting of them that hear. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Give diligence to present thyself approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">holding a straight course in the word of truth</char>. Or, <char style="it">rightly dividing the word of truth</char></char></note>handling aright the word of truth. <verse number="16" style="v"/>But shun profane babblings: for they will proceed further in ungodliness, <verse number="17" style="v"/>and their word will <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">spread</char></char></note>eat as doth a gangrene: of whom is Hymenaeus and Philetus; <verse number="18" style="v"/>men who concerning the truth have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">missed the mark</char>. <ref loc="1TI 1:6">1 Tim. 1:6</ref>.</char></note>erred, saying that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">a resurrection</char>.</char></note>the resurrection is past already, and overthrow the faith of some. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Howbeit the firm foundation of God standeth, having this seal, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="NUM 16:5">Num. 16:5</ref>?</char></note>The Lord knoweth them that are his: and, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="ISA 26:13">Isa. 26:13</ref>?</char></note>Let every one that nameth the name of the Lord depart from unrighteousness. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Now in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of wood and of earth; and some unto honor, and some unto dishonor. <verse number="21" style="v"/>If a man therefore purge himself from these, he shall be a vessel unto honor, sanctified, meet for the master&#8217;s use, prepared unto every good work. <verse number="22" style="v"/>But flee youthful lusts, and follow after righteousness, faith, love, peace, with them that call on the Lord out of a pure heart. <verse number="23" style="v"/>But foolish and ignorant questionings refuse, knowing that they gender strifes. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And the Lord&#8217;s <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant must not strive, but be gentle towards all, apt to teach, forbearing, <verse number="25" style="v"/>in meekness <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">instructing</char></char></note>correcting them that oppose themselves; if peradventure God may give them repentance unto the knowledge of the truth, <verse number="26" style="v"/>and they may <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">return to soberness</char>.</char></note>recover themselves out of the snare of the devil, having been <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">taken alive</char>.</char></note>taken captive <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by him, unto the will of God</char>. Compare <ref loc="2CO 10:5">2 Cor. 10:5</ref>. Greek <char style="it">by him, unto the will of him</char>. In the Greek the two pronouns are different.</char></note>by him unto his will.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>But know this, that in the last days grievous times shall come. <verse number="2" style="v"/>For men shall be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, railers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy, <verse number="3" style="v"/>without natural affection, implacable, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, no lovers of good, <verse number="4" style="v"/>traitors, headstrong, puffed up, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God; <verse number="5" style="v"/>holding a form of godliness, but having denied the power thereof: from these also turn away. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For of these are they that creep into houses, and take captive silly women laden with sins, led away by divers lusts, <verse number="7" style="v"/>ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And even as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so do these also withstand the truth; men corrupted in mind, reprobate concerning the faith. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But they shall proceed no further: for their folly shall be evident unto all men, as theirs also came to be. <verse number="10" style="v"/>But thou didst follow my teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, longsuffering, love, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience, <verse number="11" style="v"/>persecutions, sufferings; what things befell me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra; what persecutions I endured: and out of them all the Lord delivered me. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Yea, and all that would live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution. <verse number="13" style="v"/>But evil men and impostors shall wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But abide thou in the things which thou hast learned and hast been assured of, knowing of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">what persons</char>.</char></note>whom thou hast learned them; <verse number="15" style="v"/>and that from a babe thou hast known the sacred writings which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus. <verse number="16" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Every scripture</char> is <char style="it">inspired of God, and profitable</char></char></note>Every scripture inspired of God <char style="add">is</char> also profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, for <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">discipline</char></char></note>instruction which is in righteousness: <verse number="17" style="v"/>that the man of God may be complete, furnished completely unto every good work.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">I testify, in the sight&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. dead, both of his appearing etc.</char></char></note>I charge <char style="add">thee</char> in the sight of God, and of Christ Jesus, who shall judge the living and the dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom: <verse number="2" style="v"/>preach the word; be urgent in season, out of season; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">bring to the proof</char></char></note>reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all longsuffering and teaching. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For the time will come when they will not endure the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">healthful</char>.</char></note>sound <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">teaching</char></char></note>doctrine; but, having itching ears, will heap to themselves teachers after their own lusts; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and will turn away their ears from the truth, and turn aside unto fables. <verse number="5" style="v"/>But be thou sober in all things, suffer hardship, do the work of an evangelist, fulfil thy ministry. <verse number="6" style="v"/>For I am already being <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">poured out as a drink-offering</char>.</char></note>offered, and the time of my departure is come. <verse number="7" style="v"/>I have fought the good fight, I have finished the course, I have kept the faith: <verse number="8" style="v"/>henceforth there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give to me at that day; and not to me only, but also to all them that have loved his appearing.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>Give diligence to come shortly unto me: <verse number="10" style="v"/>for Demas forsook me, having loved this present <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">age</char></char></note>world, and went to Thessalonica; Crescens to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gaul</char></char></note>Galatia, Titus to Dalmatia. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Only Luke is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with thee; for he is useful to me for ministering. <verse number="12" style="v"/>But Tychicus I sent to Ephesus. <verse number="13" style="v"/>The cloak that I left at Troas with Carpus, bring when thou comest, and the books, especially the parchments. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Alexander the coppersmith <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">showed</char>.</char></note>did me much evil: the Lord will render to him according to his works: <verse number="15" style="v"/>of whom do thou also beware; for he greatly withstood our words. <verse number="16" style="v"/>At my first defence no one took my part, but all forsook me: may it not be laid to their account. <verse number="17" style="v"/>But the Lord stood by me, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gave me power</char></char></note>strengthened me; that through me the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">proclamation</char></char></note>message might be fully proclaimed, and that all the Gentiles might hear: and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion. <verse number="18" style="v"/>The Lord will deliver me from every evil work, and will save me unto his heavenly kingdom: to whom <char style="add">be</char> the glory <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever. Amen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Erastus remained at Corinth: but Trophimus I left at Miletus sick. <verse number="21" style="v"/>Give diligence to come before winter. Eubulus saluteth thee, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v"/>The Lord be with thy spirit. Grace be with you.</para>
</usx>