<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="2PE" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">Symeon</char>. See <ref loc="ACT 15:14">Acts 15:14</ref>.</char></note>Simon Peter, a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant and apostle of Jesus Christ, to them that have obtained <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">an equally precious</char>.</char></note>a like precious faith with us in the righteousness of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">our God and Saviour</char>. Compare <ref loc="2PE 1:11">verse 11</ref>; <ref loc="2PE 2:20">2:20</ref>; <ref loc="2PE 3:18">3:18</ref>; <ref loc="TIT 2:13">Titus 2:13</ref>.</char></note>our God and <char style="add">the</char> Saviour Jesus Christ: <verse number="2" style="v"/>Grace to you and peace be multiplied in the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord; <verse number="3" style="v"/>seeing that his divine power hath granted unto us all things that pertain unto life and godliness, through the knowledge of him that called us <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">through glory and virtue</char>.</char></note>by his own glory and virtue; <verse number="4" style="v"/>whereby he hath granted unto us his precious and exceeding great promises; that through these ye may become partakers of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a</char></char></note>the divine nature, having escaped from the corruption that is in the world by lust. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Yea, and for this very cause adding on your part all diligence, in your faith supply virtue; and in <char style="add">your</char> virtue knowledge; <verse number="6" style="v"/>and in <char style="add">your</char> knowledge self-control; and in <char style="add">your</char> self-control <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience; and in <char style="add">your</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience godliness; <verse number="7" style="v"/>and in <char style="add">your</char> godliness <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">love of the brethren</char>.</char></note>brotherly kindness; and in <char style="add">your</char> <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">love of the brethren</char>.</char></note>brotherly kindness love. <verse number="8" style="v"/>For if these things are yours and abound, they make you to be not idle nor unfruitful unto the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse number="9" style="v"/>For he that lacketh these things is blind, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">closing his eyes</char></char></note>seeing only what is near, having forgotten the cleansing from his old sins. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Wherefore, brethren, give the more diligence to make your calling and election sure: for if ye do these things, ye shall never stumble: <verse number="11" style="v"/>for thus shall be richly supplied unto you the entrance into the eternal kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Wherefore I shall be ready always to put you in remembrance of these things, though ye know them, and are established in the truth which is with <char style="add">you</char>. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And I think it right, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to stir you up by putting you in remembrance; <verse number="14" style="v"/>knowing that the putting off of my tabernacle cometh swiftly, even as our Lord Jesus Christ signified unto me. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Yea, I will give diligence that at every time ye may be able after my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">departure</char></char></note>decease to call these things to remembrance. <verse number="16" style="v"/>For we did not follow cunningly devised fables, when we made known unto you the power and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">presence</char>.</char></note>coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but we were eyewitnesses of his majesty. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">having received</char>.</char></note>received from God the Father honor and glory, when there was borne such a voice to him by the Majestic Glory, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased: <verse number="18" style="v"/>and this voice we <char style="add">ourselves</char> heard borne out of heaven, when we were with him in the holy mount. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And we have the word of prophecy <char style="add">made</char> more sure; whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a lamp shining in a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">squalid</char>.</char></note>dark place, until the day dawn, and the day-star arise in your hearts: <verse number="20" style="v"/>knowing this first, that no prophecy of scripture is of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">special</char></char></note>private interpretation. <verse number="21" style="v"/>For no prophecy ever <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">was brought</char>.</char></note>came by the will of man: but men spake from God, being moved by the Holy Spirit.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>But there arose false prophets also among the people, as among you also there shall be false teachers, who shall privily bring in <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sects of perdition</char></char></note>destructive heresies, denying even the Master that bought them, bringing upon themselves swift destruction. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And many shall follow their lascivious doings; by reason of whom the way of the truth shall be evil spoken of. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And in covetousness shall they with feigned words make merchandise of you: whose sentence now from of old lingereth not, and their destruction slumbereth not. <verse number="4" style="v"/>For if God spared not angels when they sinned, but <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cast them into dungeons</char></char></note>cast them down to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Tartarus</char>.</char></note>hell, and committed them to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">chains</char>. Compare <ref loc="WIS 17:17">Wisd. 17:17</ref>.</char></note>pits of darkness, to be reserved unto judgment; <verse number="5" style="v"/>and spared not the ancient world, but preserved Noah with seven others, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">a herald</char>.</char></note>a preacher of righteousness, when he brought a flood upon the world of the ungodly; <verse number="6" style="v"/>and turning the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah into ashes condemned them with an overthrow, having made them an example unto those that should live ungodly; <verse number="7" style="v"/>and delivered righteous Lot, sore distressed by the lascivious life of the wicked <verse number="8" style="v"/>(for that righteous man dwelling among them, in seeing and hearing, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">tormented</char>.</char></note>vexed <char style="add">his</char> righteous soul from day to day with <char style="add">their</char> lawless deeds): <verse number="9" style="v"/>the Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptation, and to keep the unrighteous under punishment unto the day of judgment; <verse number="10" style="v"/>but chiefly them that walk after the flesh in the lust of defilement, and despise dominion. Daring, self-willed, they tremble not to rail at <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">glories</char>.</char></note>dignities: <verse number="11" style="v"/>whereas angels, though greater in might and power, bring not a railing judgment against them before the Lord. <verse number="12" style="v"/>But these, as creatures without reason, born <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">natural</char>.</char></note>mere animals <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to take and to destroy</char></char></note>to be taken and destroyed, railing in matters whereof they are ignorant, shall in their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">corruption</char>. Compare <ref loc="1TI 6:9">1 Tim. 6:9</ref>.</char></note>destroying surely be destroyed, <verse number="13" style="v"/>suffering wrong as the hire of wrong-doing; <char style="add">men</char> that count it pleasure to revel in the day-time, spots and blemishes, revelling in their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">love-feasts</char>. Compare <ref loc="JUD 1:12">Jude 12</ref>.</char></note>deceivings while they feast with you; <verse number="14" style="v"/>having eyes full of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">an adulteress</char>.</char></note>adultery, and that cannot cease from sin; enticing unstedfast souls; having a heart exercised in covetousness; children of cursing; <verse number="15" style="v"/>forsaking the right way, they went astray, having followed the way of Balaam the <char style="add">son</char> of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">Bosor</char>.</char></note>Beor, who loved the hire of wrong-doing; <verse number="16" style="v"/>but he was rebuked for his own transgression: a dumb ass spake with man&#8217;s voice and stayed the madness of the prophet. <verse number="17" style="v"/>These are springs without water, and mists driven by a storm; for whom the blackness of darkness hath been reserved. <verse number="18" style="v"/>For, uttering great swelling <char style="add">words</char> of vanity, they entice in the lusts of the flesh, by lasciviousness, those who are just escaping from them that live in error; <verse number="19" style="v"/>promising them liberty, while they themselves are bondservants of corruption; for of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">what</char></char></note>whom a man is overcome, of the same is he also brought into bondage. <verse number="20" style="v"/>For if, after they have escaped the defilements of the world through the knowledge of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">our</char>.</char></note>the Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, they are again entangled therein and overcome, the last state is become worse with them than the first. <verse number="21" style="v"/>For it were better for them not to have known the way of righteousness, than, after knowing it, to turn back from the holy commandment delivered unto them. <verse number="22" style="v"/>It has happened unto them according to the true proverb, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft"><ref loc="PRO 26:11">Prov. 26:11</ref>.</char></note>The dog turning to his own vomit again, and the sow that had washed to wallowing in the mire.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>This is now, beloved, the second epistle that I write unto you; and in both of them I stir up your sincere mind by putting you in remembrance; <verse number="2" style="v"/>that ye should remember the words which were spoken before by the holy prophets, and the commandment of the Lord and Saviour through your apostles: <verse number="3" style="v"/>knowing this first, that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in the last of the days</char>.</char></note>in the last days mockers shall come with mockery, walking after their own lusts, <verse number="4" style="v"/>and saying, Where is the promise of his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">presence</char>.</char></note>coming? for, from the day that the fathers fell asleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the creation. <verse number="5" style="v"/>For this they wilfully forget, that there were heavens from of old, and an earth compacted out of water and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">through</char></char></note>amidst water, by the word of God; <verse number="6" style="v"/>by which means the world that then was, being overflowed with water, perished: <verse number="7" style="v"/>but the heavens that now are, and the earth, by the same word have been <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stored with fire</char></char></note>stored up for fire, being reserved against the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>But forget not this one thing, beloved, that one day is with the Lord as a thousand years, and a thousand years as one day. <verse number="9" style="v"/>The Lord is not slack concerning his promise, as some count slackness; but is longsuffering to you-ward, not wishing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance. <verse number="10" style="v"/>But the day of the Lord will come as a thief; in the which the heavens shall pass away with a great noise, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">heavenly bodies</char></char></note>elements shall be dissolved with fervent heat, and the earth and the works that are therein shall be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The most ancient manuscripts read <char style="it">discovered</char>.</char></note>burned up. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Seeing that these things are thus all to be dissolved, what manner of persons ought ye to be in <char style="add">all</char> holy living and godliness, <verse number="12" style="v"/>looking for and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">hastening</char></char></note>earnestly desiring the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">presence</char>.</char></note>coming of the day of God, by reason of which the heavens being on fire shall be dissolved, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">heavenly bodies</char></char></note>elements shall melt with fervent heat? <verse number="13" style="v"/>But, according to his promise, we look for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteousness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>Wherefore, beloved, seeing that ye look for these things, give diligence that ye may be found in peace, without spot and blameless in his sight. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And account that the longsuffering of our Lord is salvation; even as our beloved brother Paul also, according to the wisdom given to him, wrote unto you; <verse number="16" style="v"/>as also in all <char style="add">his</char> epistles, speaking in them of these things; wherein are some things hard to be understood, which the ignorant and unstedfast wrest, as <char style="add">they do</char> also the other scriptures, unto their own destruction. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Ye therefore, beloved, knowing <char style="add">these things</char> beforehand, beware lest, being carried away with the error of the wicked, ye fall from your own stedfastness. <verse number="18" style="v"/>But grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. To him <char style="add">be</char> the glory both now and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the day of eternity</char>. <ref loc="SIR 18:10">Ecclus. 18:10</ref>.</char></note>for ever. Amen.</para>
</usx>