<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="2JN" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>The elder unto the elect <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Cyria</char></char></note>lady and her children, whom I love in truth; and not I only, but also all they that know the truth; <verse number="2" style="v"/>for the truth&#8217;s sake which abideth in us, and it shall be with us for ever: <verse number="3" style="v"/>Grace, mercy, peace shall be with us, from God the Father, and from Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, in truth and love.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>I rejoice greatly that I have found <char style="add">certain</char> of thy children walking in truth, even as we received commandment from the Father. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And now I beseech thee, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Cyria</char></char></note>lady, not as though I wrote to thee a new commandment, but that which we had from the beginning, that we love one another. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And this is love, that we should walk after his commandments. This is the commandment, even as ye heard from the beginning, that ye should walk in it. <verse number="7" style="v"/>For many deceivers are gone forth into the world, <char style="add">even</char> they that confess not that Jesus Christ cometh in the flesh. This is the deceiver and the antichrist. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Look to yourselves, that ye <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">destroy</char></char></note>lose not the things which <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">ye</char>.</char></note>we have wrought, but that ye receive a full reward. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Whosoever <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">taketh the lead</char>. Compare <ref loc="3JN 1:9">3 Jn. 9</ref>.</char></note>goeth onward and abideth not in the teaching of Christ, hath not God: he that abideth in the teaching, the same hath both the Father and the Son. <verse number="10" style="v"/>If any one cometh unto you, and bringeth not this teaching, receive him not into <char style="add">your</char> house, and give him no greeting: <verse number="11" style="v"/>for he that giveth him greeting partaketh in his evil works.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>Having many things to write unto you, I would not <char style="add">write them</char> with paper and ink: but I hope to come unto you, and to speak face to face, that your joy may be made full. <verse number="13" style="v"/>The children of thine elect sister salute thee.</para>
</usx>