<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="JUD" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">Judas</char>.</char></note>Jude, a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Jacob</char></char></note>James, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to them that are beloved in God the Father, and kept for Jesus Christ</char>, being <char style="it">called</char></char></note>to them that are called, beloved in God the Father, and kept for Jesus Christ: <verse number="2" style="v"/>Mercy unto you and peace and love be multiplied.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>Beloved, while I was giving all diligence to write unto you of our common salvation, I was constrained to write unto you exhorting you to contend earnestly for the faith which was once for all delivered unto the saints. <verse number="4" style="v"/>For there are certain men crept in privily, <char style="add">even</char> they who were of old <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">set forth</char></char></note>written of beforehand unto this condemnation, ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness, and denying <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the only Master, and our Lord Jesus Christ</char></char></note>our only Master and Lord, Jesus Christ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>Now I desire to put you in remembrance, though ye know all things once for all, that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many very ancient authorities read <char style="it">Jesus</char>.</char></note>the Lord, having saved a people out of the land of Egypt, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">the second time</char>.</char></note>afterward destroyed them that believed not. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And angels that kept not their own principality, but left their proper habitation, he hath kept in everlasting bonds under darkness unto the judgment of the great day. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Even as Sodom and Gomorrah, and the cities about them, having in like manner with these given themselves over to fornication and gone after strange flesh, are set forth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">as an example of eternal fire, suffering punishment</char></char></note>as an example, suffering the punishment of eternal fire. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Yet in like manner these also in their dreamings defile the flesh, and set at nought dominion, and rail at <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">glories</char>.</char></note>dignities. <verse number="9" style="v"/>But Michael the archangel, when contending with the devil he disputed about the body of Moses, durst not bring against him a railing judgment, but said, The Lord rebuke thee. <verse number="10" style="v"/>But these rail at whatsoever things they know not: and what they understand naturally, like the creatures without reason, in these things are they <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">corrupted</char>. Compare <ref loc="2PE 2:12">2 Pet. 2:12</ref> margin.</char></note>destroyed. <verse number="11" style="v"/>Woe unto them! for they went in the way of Cain, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">cast themselves away through</char></char></note>ran riotously in the error of Balaam for hire, and perished in the gainsaying of Korah. <verse number="12" style="v"/>These are they who are <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">spots</char></char></note>hidden rocks in your love-feasts when they feast with you, shepherds that without fear feed themselves; clouds without water, carried along by winds; autumn trees without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots; <verse number="13" style="v"/>wild waves of the sea, foaming out their own <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">shames</char>.</char></note>shame; wandering stars, for whom the blackness of darkness hath been reserved for ever. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And to these also Enoch, the seventh from Adam, prophesied, saying, Behold, the Lord came with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">his holy myriads</char>.</char></note>ten thousands of his holy ones, <verse number="15" style="v"/>to execute judgment upon all, and to convict all the ungodly of all their works of ungodliness which they have ungodly wrought, and of all the hard things which ungodly sinners have spoken against him. <verse number="16" style="v"/>These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their lusts (and their mouth speaketh great swelling <char style="add">words</char>), showing respect of persons for the sake of advantage.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>But ye, beloved, remember ye the words which have been spoken before by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ; <verse number="18" style="v"/>that they said to you, In the last time there shall be mockers, walking after <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">their own lusts of ungodlinesses</char>.</char></note>their own ungodly lusts. <verse number="19" style="v"/>These are they who make separations, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">natural</char>. Or, <char style="it">animal</char></char></note>sensual, having not the Spirit. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But ye, beloved, building up yourselves on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Spirit, <verse number="21" style="v"/>keep yourselves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ unto eternal life. <verse number="22" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The Greek text in this passage (<char style="it">And&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. fire</char>) is somewhat uncertain. Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">And some refute while they dispute</char> with you. Compare <ref loc="1TI 5:20">1 Tim. 5:20</ref>; <ref loc="TIT 1:9">Titus 1:9</ref>.</char></note>And on some have mercy, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">while they dispute</char> with you</char></note>who are in doubt; <verse number="23" style="v"/>and some save, snatching them out of the fire; and on some have mercy with fear; hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v"/>Now unto him that is able to guard you from stumbling, and to set you before the presence of his glory without blemish in exceeding joy, <verse number="25" style="v"/>to the only God our Saviour, through Jesus Christ our Lord, <char style="add">be</char> glory, majesty, dominion and power, before all time, and now, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto all the ages</char>.</char></note>for evermore. Amen.</para>
</usx>