<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<usx version="2.0">
	<book code="REV" style="id">American Standard Version (1901)</book>
	<chapter number="1" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>The Revelation of Jesus Christ, which God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">gave unto him, to show unto his servants the things etc.</char></char></note>gave him to show unto his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants, <char style="add">even</char> the things which must shortly come to pass: and he sent and signified <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, them</char></note><char style="add">it</char> by his angel unto his servant John; <verse number="2" style="v"/>who bare witness of the word of God, and of the testimony of Jesus Christ, <char style="add">even</char> of all things that he saw. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Blessed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of the prophecy, and keep the things that are written therein: for the time is at hand.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>John to the seven churches that are in Asia: Grace to you and peace, from him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">who cometh</char></char></note>who is and who was and who is to come; and from the seven Spirits that are before his throne; <verse number="5" style="v"/>and from Jesus Christ, <char style="add">who is</char> the faithful witness, the firstborn of the dead, and the ruler of the kings of the earth. Unto him that loveth us, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many authorities, some ancient, read <char style="it">washed</char>. <ref loc="HEB 9:14">Heb. 9:14</ref>; compare <ref loc="REV 7:14">7:14</ref>.</char></note>loosed us from our sins <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">in</char>.</char></note>by his blood; <verse number="6" style="v"/>and he made us <char style="add">to be</char> a kingdom, <char style="add">to be</char> priests unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">God and his Father</char></char></note>his God and Father; to him <char style="add">be</char> the glory and the dominion <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>. Many ancient authorities omit <char style="it">of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever. Amen. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Behold, he cometh with the clouds; and every eye shall see him, and they that pierced him; and all the tribes of the earth shall mourn over him. Even so, Amen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>I am the Alpha and the Omega, saith the Lord God, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">he who</char></char></note>who is and who was and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">who cometh</char></char></note>who is to come, the Almighty.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>I John, your brother and partaker with you in the tribulation and kingdom and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience <char style="add">which are</char> in Jesus, was in the isle that is called Patmos, for the word of God and the testimony of Jesus. <verse number="10" style="v"/>I was in the Spirit on the Lord&#8217;s day, and I heard behind me a great voice, as of a trumpet <verse number="11" style="v"/>saying, What thou seest, write in a book and send <char style="add">it</char> to the seven churches: unto Ephesus, and unto Smyrna, and unto Pergamum, and unto Thyatira, and unto Sardis, and unto Philadelphia, and unto Laodicea. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And I turned to see the voice that spake with me. And having turned I saw seven golden <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lampstands</char>.</char></note>candlesticks; <verse number="13" style="v"/>and in the midst of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lampstands</char>.</char></note>candlesticks one like unto a son of man, clothed with a garment down to the foot, and girt about at the breasts with a golden girdle. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And his head and his hair were white as white wool, <char style="add">white</char> as snow; and his eyes were as a flame of fire; <verse number="15" style="v"/>and his feet like unto burnished brass, as if it had been refined in a furnace; and his voice as the voice of many waters. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he had in his right hand seven stars: and out of his mouth proceeded a sharp two-edged sword: and his countenance was as the sun shineth in his strength. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And when I saw him, I fell at his feet as one dead. And he laid his right hand upon me, saying, Fear not; I am the first and the last, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and the Living one; and I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">became</char>.</char></note>was dead, and behold, I am alive <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for evermore, and I have the keys of death and of Hades. <verse number="19" style="v"/>Write therefore the things which thou sawest, and the things which are, and the things which shall come to pass hereafter; <verse number="20" style="v"/>the mystery of the seven stars which thou sawest <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">upon</char>.</char></note>in my right hand, and the seven golden <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lampstands</char>.</char></note>candlesticks. The seven stars are the angels of the seven churches: and the seven <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lampstands</char>.</char></note>candlesticks are seven churches.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>To the angel of the church in Ephesus write:</para>
	<para style="p">These things saith he that holdeth the seven stars in his right hand, he that walketh in the midst of the seven golden <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lampstands</char>.</char></note>candlesticks: <verse number="2" style="v"/>I know thy works, and thy toil and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience, and that thou canst not bear evil men, and didst try them that call themselves apostles, and they are not, and didst find them false; <verse number="3" style="v"/>and thou hast <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience and didst bear for my name&#8217;s sake, and hast not grown weary. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But I have <char style="add">this</char> against thee, that thou didst leave thy first love. <verse number="5" style="v"/>Remember therefore whence thou art fallen, and repent and do the first works; or else I come to thee, and will move thy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lampstand</char>.</char></note>candlestick out of its place, except thou repent. <verse number="6" style="v"/>But this thou hast, that thou hatest the works of the Nicolaitans, which I also hate. <verse number="7" style="v"/>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches. To him that overcometh, to him will I give to eat of the tree of life, which is in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">garden</char>: as in <ref loc="GEN 2:8">Gen. 2:8</ref>.</char></note>Paradise of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And to the angel of the church in Smyrna write:</para>
	<para style="p">These things saith the first and the last, who <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">became</char>.</char></note>was dead, and lived <char style="add">again</char>: <verse number="9" style="v"/>I know thy tribulation, and thy poverty (but thou art rich), and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">reviling</char></char></note>blasphemy of them that say they are Jews, and they are not, but are a synagogue of Satan. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Fear not the things which thou art about to suffer: behold, the devil is about to cast some of you into prison, that ye may be tried; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">and may have</char>.</char></note>and ye shall have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">a tribulation of ten days</char>.</char></note>tribulation ten days. Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee the crown of life. <verse number="11" style="v"/>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches. He that overcometh shall not be hurt of the second death.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And to the angel of the church in Pergamum write:</para>
	<para style="p">These things saith he that hath the sharp two-edged sword: <verse number="13" style="v"/>I know where thou dwellest, <char style="add">even</char> where Satan&#8217;s throne is; and thou holdest fast my name, and didst not deny my faith, even in the days <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The Greek text here is somewhat uncertain.</char></note>of Antipas my witness, my faithful one, who was killed among you, where Satan dwelleth. <verse number="14" style="v"/>But I have a few things against thee, because thou hast there some that hold the teaching of Balaam, who taught Balak to cast a stumblingblock before the children of Israel, to eat things sacrificed to idols, and to commit fornication. <verse number="15" style="v"/>So hast thou also some that hold the teaching of the Nicolaitans in like manner. <verse number="16" style="v"/>Repent therefore; or else I come to thee quickly, and I will make war against them with the sword of my mouth. <verse number="17" style="v"/>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches. To him that overcometh, to him will I give of the hidden manna, and I will give him a white stone, and upon the stone a new name written, which no one knoweth but he that receiveth it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>And to the angel of the church in Thyatira write:</para>
	<para style="p">These things saith the Son of God, who hath his eyes like a flame of fire, and his feet are like unto burnished brass: <verse number="19" style="v"/>I know thy works, and thy love and faith and ministry and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience, and that thy last works are more than the first. <verse number="20" style="v"/>But I have <char style="add">this</char> against thee, that thou sufferest <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many authorities, some ancient, read <char style="it">thy wife</char>.</char></note>the woman Jezebel, who calleth herself a prophetess; and she teacheth and seduceth my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants to commit fornication, and to eat things sacrificed to idols. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And I gave her time that she should repent; and she willeth not to repent of her fornication. <verse number="22" style="v"/>Behold, I cast her into a bed, and them that commit adultery with her into great tribulation, except they repent of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">their</char>.</char></note>her works. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And I will kill her children with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pestilence</char>. Septuagint <ref loc="EXO 5:3">Ex. 5:3</ref>, etc.</char></note>death; and all the churches shall know that I am he that searcheth the reins and hearts: and I will give unto each one of you according to your works. <verse number="24" style="v"/>But to you I say, to the rest that are in Thyatira, as many as have not this teaching, who know not the deep things of Satan, as they are wont to say; I cast upon you none other burden. <verse number="25" style="v"/>Nevertheless that which ye have, hold fast till I come. <verse number="26" style="v"/>And he that overcometh, and he that keepeth my works unto the end, to him will I give authority over the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gentiles</char></char></note>nations: <verse number="27" style="v"/>and he shall rule them with a rod of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">iron; as vessels of the potter, are they broken</char></char></note>iron, as the vessels of the potter are broken to shivers; as I also have received of my Father: <verse number="28" style="v"/>and I will give him the morning star. <verse number="29" style="v"/>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And to the angel of the church in Sardis write:</para>
	<para style="p">These things saith he that hath the seven Spirits of God, and the seven stars: I know thy works, that thou hast a name that thou livest, and thou art dead. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Be thou watchful, and establish the things that remain, which were ready to die: for I have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">not found thy works</char>.</char></note>found no works of thine perfected before my God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>Remember therefore how thou hast received and didst hear; and keep <char style="add">it</char>, and repent. If therefore thou shalt not watch, I will come as a thief, and thou shalt not know what hour I will come upon thee. <verse number="4" style="v"/>But thou hast a few names in Sardis that did not defile their garments: and they shall walk with me in white; for they are worthy. <verse number="5" style="v"/>He that overcometh shall thus be arrayed in white garments; and I will in no wise blot his name out of the book of life, and I will confess his name before my Father, and before his angels. <verse number="6" style="v"/>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And to the angel of the church in Philadelphia write:</para>
	<para style="p">These things saith he that is holy, he that is true, he that hath the key of David, he that openeth and none shall shut, and that shutteth and none openeth: <verse number="8" style="v"/>I know thy works (behold, I have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">given</char>.</char></note>set before thee a door opened, which none can shut), that thou hast a little power, and didst keep my word, and didst not deny my name. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Behold, I give of the synagogue of Satan, of them that say they are Jews, and they are not, but do lie; behold, I will make them to come and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The Greek word denotes an act of reverence, whether paid to a creature, or to the Creator.</char></note>worship before thy feet, and to know that I have loved thee. <verse number="10" style="v"/>Because thou didst keep the word of my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience, I also will keep thee from the hour of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">temptation</char></char></note>trial, that <char style="add">hour</char> which is to come upon the whole <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>world, to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">tempt</char></char></note>try them that dwell upon the earth. <verse number="11" style="v"/>I come quickly: hold fast that which thou hast, that no one take thy crown. <verse number="12" style="v"/>He that overcometh, I will make him a pillar in the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple of my God, and he shall go out thence no more: and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem, which cometh down out of heaven from my God, and mine own new name. <verse number="13" style="v"/>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And to the angel of the church in Laodicea write:</para>
	<para style="p">These things saith the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation of God: <verse number="15" style="v"/>I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot: I would thou wert cold or hot. <verse number="16" style="v"/>So because thou art lukewarm, and neither hot nor cold, I will spew thee out of my mouth. <verse number="17" style="v"/>Because thou sayest, I am rich, and have gotten riches, and have need of nothing; and knowest not that thou art the wretched one and miserable and poor and blind and naked: <verse number="18" style="v"/>I counsel thee to buy of me gold refined by fire, that thou mayest become rich; and white garments, that thou mayest clothe thyself, and <char style="add">that</char> the shame of thy nakedness be not made manifest; and eyesalve to anoint thine eyes, that thou mayest see. <verse number="19" style="v"/>As many as I love, I reprove and chasten: be zealous therefore, and repent. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Behold, I stand at the door and knock: if any man hear my voice and open the door, I will come in to him, and will sup with him, and he with me. <verse number="21" style="v"/>He that overcometh, I will give to him to sit down with me in my throne, as I also overcame, and sat down with my Father in his throne. <verse number="22" style="v"/>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After these things I saw, and behold, a door opened in heaven, and the first voice that I heard, <char style="add">a voice</char> as of a trumpet speaking with me, one saying, Come up hither, and I will show thee the things which must <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">come to pass. After these things straightway etc.</char></char></note>come to pass hereafter. <verse number="2" style="v"/>Straightway I was in the Spirit: and behold, there was a throne set in heaven, and one sitting upon the throne; <verse number="3" style="v"/>and he that sat <char style="add">was</char> to look upon like a jasper stone and a sardius: and <char style="add">there was</char> a rainbow round about the throne, like an emerald to look upon. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And round about the throne <char style="add">were</char> four and twenty thrones: and upon the thrones <char style="add">I saw</char> four and twenty elders sitting, arrayed in white garments; and on their heads crowns of gold. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And out of the throne proceed lightnings and voices and thunders. And <char style="add">there were</char> seven lamps of fire burning before the throne, which are the seven Spirits of God; <verse number="6" style="v"/>and before the throne, as it were a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">glassy sea</char></char></note>sea of glass like unto crystal; and in the midst <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">before</char>. See <ref loc="REV 7:17">7:17</ref>; compare <ref loc="REV 5:6">5:6</ref>.</char></note>of the throne, and round about the throne, four living creatures full of eyes before and behind. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the first creature <char style="add">was</char> like a lion, and the second creature like a calf, and the third creature had a face as of a man, and the fourth creature <char style="add">was</char> like a flying eagle. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And the four living creatures, having each one of them six wings, are full of eyes round about and within: and they have no rest day and night, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Holy, holy, holy, <char style="add">is</char> the Lord God, the Almighty, who was and who is and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">who cometh</char></char></note>who is to come.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And when the living creatures shall give glory and honor and thanks to him that sitteth on the throne, to him that liveth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever, <verse number="10" style="v"/>the four and twenty elders shall fall down before him that sitteth on the throne, and shall worship him that liveth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever, and shall cast their crowns before the throne, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi"><verse number="11" style="v"/>Worthy art thou, our Lord and our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power: for thou didst create all things, and because of thy will they were, and were created.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And I saw <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">on</char>.</char></note>in the right hand of him that sat on the throne a book written within and on the back, close sealed with seven seals. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And I saw a strong angel proclaiming with a great voice, Who is worthy to open the book, and to loose the seals thereof? <verse number="3" style="v"/>And no one in the heaven, or on the earth, or under the earth, was able to open the book, or to look thereon. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And I wept much, because no one was found worthy to open the book, or to look thereon: <verse number="5" style="v"/>and one of the elders saith unto me, Weep not; behold, the Lion that is of the tribe of Judah, the Root of David, hath overcome to open the book and the seven seals thereof. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And I saw <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">between the throne with the four living creatures, and the elders</char></char></note>in the midst of the throne and of the four living creatures, and in the midst of the elders, a Lamb standing, as though it had been slain, having seven horns, and seven eyes, which are the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">seven</char>.</char></note>seven Spirits of God, sent forth into all the earth. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And he came, and he <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">hath taken</char>.</char></note>taketh <char style="add">it</char> out of the right hand of him that sat on the throne. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And when he had taken the book, the four living creatures and the four and twenty elders fell down before the Lamb, having each one a harp, and golden bowls full of incense, which are the prayers of the saints. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And they sing a new song, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Worthy art thou to take the book, and to open the seals thereof: for thou wast slain, and didst purchase unto God with thy blood <char style="add">men</char> of every tribe, and tongue, and people, and nation, <verse number="10" style="v"/>and madest them <char style="add">to be</char> unto our God a kingdom and priests; and they reign upon the earth.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And I saw, and I heard a voice of many angels round about the throne and the living creatures and the elders; and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands of thousands; <verse number="12" style="v"/>saying with a great voice,</para>
	<para style="mi">Worthy is the Lamb that hath been slain to receive the power, and riches, and wisdom, and might, and honor, and glory, and blessing.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And every created thing which is in the heaven, and on the earth, and under the earth, and on the sea, and all things that are in them, heard I saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Unto him that sitteth on the throne, and unto the Lamb, <char style="add">be</char> the blessing, and the honor, and the glory, and the dominion, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And the four living creatures said, Amen. And the elders fell down and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worshipped.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c"/>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And I saw when the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures saying as with a voice of thunder, Come<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities add <char style="it">and see</char>.</char></note>. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And I saw, and behold, a white horse, and he that sat thereon had a bow; and there was given unto him a crown: and he came forth conquering, and to conquer.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>And when he opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature saying, Come<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities add <char style="it">and see</char>.</char></note>. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And another <char style="add">horse</char> came forth, a red horse: and to him that sat thereon it was given to take <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">the peace of the earth</char>.</char></note>peace from the earth, and that they should slay one another: and there was given unto him a great sword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>And when he opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature saying, Come. <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities add <char style="it">and see</char>.</char></note>And I saw, and behold, a black horse; and he that sat thereon had a balance in his hand. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And I heard as it were a voice in the midst of the four living creatures saying, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">A choenix</char> (i.e. about a quart) <char style="it">of wheat for a shilling</char>&#8212;implying great scarcity. Compare <ref loc="EZK 4:16-4:17">Ezek. 4:16f</ref>; <ref loc="EZK 5:16">5:16</ref>.</char></note>A measure of wheat for a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 18:28">Mt. 18:28</ref>.</char></note>shilling, and three measures of barley for a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="MAT 18:28">Mt. 18:28</ref>.</char></note>shilling; and the oil and the wine hurt thou not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And when he opened the fourth seal, I heard the voice of the fourth living creature saying, Come<note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities add <char style="it">and see</char>.</char></note>. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And I saw, and behold, a pale horse: and he that sat upon him, his name was Death; and Hades followed with him. And there was given unto them authority over the fourth part of the earth, to kill with sword, and with famine, and with <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">pestilence</char>. Compare <ref loc="REV 2:23">2:23</ref> margin.</char></note>death, and by the wild beasts of the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And when he opened the fifth seal, I saw underneath the altar the souls of them that had been slain for the word of God, and for the testimony which they held: <verse number="10" style="v"/>and they cried with a great voice, saying, How long, O Master, the holy and true, dost thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth? <verse number="11" style="v"/>And there was given them to each one a white robe; and it was said unto them, that they should rest yet for a little time, until their fellow-servants also and their brethren, who should be killed even as they were, should <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">be fulfilled</char> in number; <ref loc="2ESD 4:36">2 Esdr. 4:36</ref></char></note>have fulfilled <char style="add">their course</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And I saw when he opened the sixth seal, and there was a great earthquake; and the sun became black as sackcloth of hair, and the whole moon became as blood; <verse number="13" style="v"/>and the stars of the heaven fell unto the earth, as a fig tree casteth her unripe figs when she is shaken of a great wind. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the heaven was removed as a scroll when it is rolled up; and every mountain and island were moved out of their places. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the kings of the earth, and the princes, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribunes</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarchs</char>.</char></note>chief captains, and the rich, and the strong, and every bondman and freeman, hid themselves in the caves and in the rocks of the mountains; <verse number="16" style="v"/>and they say to the mountains and to the rocks, Fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that sitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb: <verse number="17" style="v"/>for the great day of their wrath is come; and who is able to stand?</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After this I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding the four winds of the earth, that no wind should blow on the earth, or on the sea, or upon any tree. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And I saw another angel ascend from the sunrising, having the seal of the living God: and he cried with a great voice to the four angels to whom it was given to hurt the earth and the sea, <verse number="3" style="v"/>saying, Hurt not the earth, neither the sea, nor the trees, till we shall have sealed the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants of our God on their foreheads. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And I heard the number of them that were sealed, a hundred and forty and four thousand, sealed out of every tribe of the children of Israel:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="5" style="v"/>Of the tribe of Judah <char style="add">were</char> sealed twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1">Of the tribe of Reuben twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1">Of the tribe of Gad twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="6" style="v"/>Of the tribe of Asher twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1">Of the tribe of Naphtali twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1">Of the tribe of Manasseh twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="7" style="v"/>Of the tribe of Simeon twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1">Of the tribe of Levi twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1">Of the tribe of Issachar twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="8" style="v"/>Of the tribe of Zebulun twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1">Of the tribe of Joseph twelve thousand;</para>
	<para style="q1">Of the tribe of Benjamin <char style="add">were</char> sealed twelve thousand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>After these things I saw, and behold, a great multitude, which no man could number, out of every nation and of <char style="add">all</char> tribes and peoples and tongues, standing before the throne and before the Lamb, arrayed in white robes, and palms in their hands; <verse number="10" style="v"/>and they cry with a great voice, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Salvation unto our God who sitteth on the throne, and unto the Lamb.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And all the angels were standing round about the throne, and <char style="add">about</char> the elders and the four living creatures; and they fell before the throne on their faces, and worshipped God, <verse number="12" style="v"/>saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Amen: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">The blessing, and the glory etc.</char></char></note>Blessing, and glory, and wisdom, and thanksgiving, and honor, and power, and might, <char style="add">be</char> unto our God <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever. Amen.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And one of the elders answered, saying unto me, These that are arrayed in the white robes, who are they, and whence came they? <verse number="14" style="v"/>And I <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">have said</char>.</char></note>say unto him, My lord, thou knowest. And he said to me, These are they that come out of the great tribulation, and they washed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Therefore are they before the throne of God; and they serve him day and night in his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple: and he that sitteth on the throne shall spread his tabernacle over them. <verse number="16" style="v"/>They shall hunger no more, neither thirst any more; neither shall the sun strike upon them, nor any heat: <verse number="17" style="v"/>for the Lamb that is in the midst <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">before</char>. See <ref loc="REV 4:6">4:6</ref>; compare <ref loc="REV 5:6">5:6</ref>.</char></note>of the throne shall be their shepherd, and shall guide them unto fountains of waters of life: and God shall wipe away every tear from their eyes.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And when he opened the seventh seal, there followed a silence in heaven about the space of half an hour. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And I saw the seven angels that stand before God; and there were given unto them seven trumpets.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>And another angel came and stood <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">at</char></char></note>over the altar, having a golden censer; and there was given unto him much incense, that he should <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">give</char>.</char></note>add it unto the prayers of all the saints upon the golden altar which was before the throne. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the smoke of the incense, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">for</char></char></note>with the prayers of the saints, went up before God out of the angel&#8217;s hand. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the angel <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">hath taken</char>.</char></note>taketh the censer; and he filled it with the fire of the altar, and cast it <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">into</char></char></note>upon the earth: and there followed thunders, and voices, and lightnings, and an earthquake.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And the seven angels that had the seven trumpets prepared themselves to sound.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And the first sounded, and there followed hail and fire, mingled with blood, and they were cast <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">into</char></char></note>upon the earth: and the third part of the earth was burnt up, and the third part of the trees was burnt up, and all green grass was burnt up.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And the second angel sounded, and as it were a great mountain burning with fire was cast into the sea: and the third part of the sea became blood; <verse number="9" style="v"/>and there died the third part of the creatures which were in the sea, <char style="add">even</char> they that had life; and the third part of the ships was destroyed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And the third angel sounded, and there fell from heaven a great star, burning as a torch, and it fell upon the third part of the rivers, and upon the fountains of the waters; <verse number="11" style="v"/>and the name of the star is called Wormwood: and the third part of the waters became wormwood; and many men died of the waters, because they were made bitter.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And the fourth angel sounded, and the third part of the sun was smitten, and the third part of the moon, and the third part of the stars; that the third part of them should be darkened, and the day should not shine for the third part of it, and the night in like manner.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And I saw, and I heard <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">one eagle</char>.</char></note>an eagle, flying in mid heaven, saying with a great voice, Woe, woe, woe, for them that dwell on the earth, by reason of the other voices of the trumpet of the three angels, who are yet to sound.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And the fifth angel sounded, and I saw a star from heaven fallen unto the earth: and there was given to him the key of the pit of the abyss. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he opened the pit of the abyss; and there went up a smoke out of the pit, as the smoke of a great furnace; and the sun and the air were darkened by reason of the smoke of the pit. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And out of the smoke came forth locusts upon the earth; and power was given them, as the scorpions of the earth have power. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And it was said unto them that they should not hurt the grass of the earth, neither any green thing, neither any tree, but only such men as have not the seal of God on their foreheads. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And it was given them that they should not kill them, but that they should be tormented five months: and their torment was as the torment of a scorpion, when it striketh a man. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And in those days men shall seek death, and shall in no wise find it; and they shall desire to die, and death fleeth from them. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">likenesses</char>.</char></note>shapes of the locusts were like unto horses prepared for war; and upon their heads as it were crowns like unto gold, and their faces were as men&#8217;s faces. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And they had hair as the hair of women, and their teeth were as <char style="add">the teeth</char> of lions. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And they had breastplates, as it were breastplates of iron; and the sound of their wings was as the sound of chariots, of many horses rushing to war. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And they have tails like unto scorpions, and stings; and in their tails is their power to hurt men five months. <verse number="11" style="v"/>They have over them as king the angel of the abyss: his name in Hebrew is Abaddon, and in the Greek <char style="add">tongue</char> he hath the name <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">That is, <char style="it">Destroyer</char>.</char></note>Apollyon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>The first Woe is past: behold, there come yet two Woes hereafter.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And the sixth angel sounded, and I heard <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">one voice</char>.</char></note>a voice from the horns of the golden altar which is before God, <verse number="14" style="v"/>one saying to the sixth angel that had the trumpet, Loose the four angels that are bound at the great river Euphrates. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the four angels were loosed, that had been prepared for the hour and day and month and year, that they should kill the third part of men. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the number of the armies of the horsemen was twice ten thousand times ten thousand: I heard the number of them. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And thus I saw the horses in the vision, and them that sat on them, having breastplates <char style="add">as</char> of fire and of hyacinth and of brimstone: and the heads of the horses are as the heads of lions; and out of their mouths proceedeth fire and smoke and brimstone. <verse number="18" style="v"/>By these three plagues was the third part of men killed, by the fire and the smoke and the brimstone, which proceeded out of their mouths. <verse number="19" style="v"/>For the power of the horses is in their mouth, and in their tails: for their tails are like unto serpents, and have heads; and with them they hurt. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the rest of mankind, who were not killed with these plagues, repented not of the works of their hands, that they should not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship demons, and the idols of gold, and of silver, and of brass, and of stone, and of wood; which can neither see, nor hear, nor walk: <verse number="21" style="v"/>and they repented not of their murders, nor of their sorceries, nor of their fornication, nor of their thefts.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And I saw another strong angel coming down out of heaven, arrayed with a cloud; and the rainbow was upon his head, and his face was as the sun, and his feet as pillars of fire; <verse number="2" style="v"/>and he had in his hand a little book open: and he set his right foot upon the sea, and his left upon the earth; <verse number="3" style="v"/>and he cried with a great voice, as a lion roareth: and when he cried, the seven thunders uttered their voices. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And when the seven thunders uttered <char style="add">their voices</char>, I was about to write: and I heard a voice from heaven saying, Seal up the things which the seven thunders uttered, and write them not. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And the angel that I saw standing upon the sea and upon the earth lifted up his right hand to heaven, <verse number="6" style="v"/>and sware by him that liveth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever, who created the heaven and the things that are therein, and the earth and the things that are therein, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">and the sea and the things that are therein</char>.</char></note>and the sea and the things that are therein, that there shall be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">time</char></char></note>delay no longer: <verse number="7" style="v"/>but in the days of the voice of the seventh angel, when he is about to sound, then is finished the mystery of God, according to the good tidings which he declared to his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants the prophets. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And the voice which I heard from heaven, <char style="add">I heard it</char> again speaking with me, and saying, Go, take the book which is open in the hand of the angel that standeth upon the sea and upon the earth. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And I went unto the angel, saying unto him that he should give me the little book. And he saith unto me, Take it, and eat it up; and it shall make thy belly bitter, but in thy mouth it shall be sweet as honey. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And I took the little book out of the angel&#8217;s hand, and ate it up; and it was in my mouth sweet as honey: and when I had eaten it, my belly was made bitter. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And they say unto me, Thou must prophesy again <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">concerning</char>. Compare <ref loc="JHN 12:16">Jn. 12:16</ref>.</char></note>over many peoples and nations and tongues and kings.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And there was given me a reed like unto a rod: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">saying</char>.</char></note>and one said, Rise, and measure the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple of God, and the altar, and them that worship therein. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the court which is without the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">cast without</char>.</char></note>leave without, and measure it not; for it hath been given unto the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gentiles</char></char></note>nations: and the holy city shall they tread under foot forty and two months. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And I will give unto my two witnesses, and they shall prophesy a thousand two hundred and threescore days, clothed in sackcloth. <verse number="4" style="v"/>These are the two olive trees and the two <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">lampstands</char>.</char></note>candlesticks, standing before the Lord of the earth. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And if any man desireth to hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth and devoureth their enemies; and if any man shall desire to hurt them, in this manner must he be killed. <verse number="6" style="v"/>These have the power to shut the heaven, that it rain not during the days of their prophecy: and they have power over the waters to turn them into blood, and to smite the earth with every plague, as often as they shall desire. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And when they shall have finished their testimony, the beast that cometh up out of the abyss shall make war with them, and overcome them, and kill them. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">carcase</char>.</char></note>dead bodies <char style="add">lie</char> in the street of the great city, which spiritually is called Sodom and Egypt, where also their Lord was crucified. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And from among the peoples and tribes and tongues and nations do <char style="add">men</char> look upon their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">carcase</char>.</char></note>dead bodies three days and a half, and suffer not their dead bodies to be laid in a tomb. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And they that dwell on the earth rejoice over them, and make merry; and they shall send gifts one to another; because these two prophets tormented them that dwell on the earth. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And after the three days and a half the breath of life from God entered into them, and they stood upon their feet; and great fear fell upon them that beheld them. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And they heard a great voice from heaven saying unto them, Come up hither. And they went up into heaven in the cloud; and their enemies beheld them. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And in that hour there was a great earthquake, and the tenth part of the city fell; and there were killed in the earthquake <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">names of men, seven thousand</char>. Compare <ref loc="REV 3:4">3:4</ref>.</char></note>seven thousand persons: and the rest were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of heaven.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>The second Woe is past: behold, the third Woe cometh quickly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v"/>And the seventh angel sounded; and there followed great voices in heaven, and they said,</para>
	<para style="mi">The kingdom of the world is become <char style="add">the kingdom</char> of our Lord, and of his Christ: and he shall reign <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="16" style="v"/>And the four and twenty elders, who sit before God on their thrones, fell upon their faces and worshipped God, <verse number="17" style="v"/>saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">We give thee thanks, O Lord God, the Almighty, who art and who wast; because thou hast taken thy great power, and didst reign. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the nations were wroth, and thy wrath came, and the time of the dead to be judged, and <char style="add">the time</char> to give their reward to thy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants the prophets, and to the saints, and to them that fear thy name, the small and the great; and to destroy them that destroy the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>And there was opened the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple of God that is in heaven; and there was seen in his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple the ark of his covenant; and there followed lightnings, and voices, and thunders, and an earthquake, and great hail.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And a great sign was seen in heaven: a woman arrayed with the sun, and the moon under her feet, and upon her head a crown of twelve stars; <verse number="2" style="v"/>and she was with child; and she crieth out, travailing in birth, and in pain to be delivered. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And there was seen another sign in heaven: and behold, a great red dragon, having seven heads and ten horns, and upon his heads seven diadems. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And his tail draweth the third part of the stars of heaven, and did cast them to the earth: and the dragon standeth before the woman that is about to be delivered, that when she is delivered he may devour her child. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And she was delivered of a son, a man child, who is to rule all the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gentiles</char></char></note>nations with a rod of iron: and her child was caught up unto God, and unto his throne. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And the woman fled into the wilderness, where she hath a place prepared of God, that there they may nourish her a thousand two hundred and threescore days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And there was war in heaven: Michael and his angels <char style="add">going forth</char> to war with the dragon; and the dragon warred and his angels; <verse number="8" style="v"/>and they prevailed not, neither was their place found any more in heaven. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the great dragon was cast down, the old serpent, he that is called the Devil and Satan, the deceiver of the whole <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>world; he was cast down to the earth, and his angels were cast down with him. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And I heard a great voice in heaven, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi"><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Now is the salvation, and the power, and the kingdom, become our God&#8217;s, and the authority</char> is become <char style="it">his Christ&#8217;s</char></char></note>Now is come the salvation, and the power, and the kingdom of our God, and the authority of his Christ: for the accuser of our brethren is cast down, who accuseth them before our God day and night. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And they overcame him because of the blood of the Lamb, and because of the word of their testimony; and they loved not their life even unto death. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Therefore rejoice, O heavens, and ye that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">tabernacle</char>.</char></note>dwell in them. Woe for the earth and for the sea: because the devil is gone down unto you, having great wrath, knowing that he hath but a short time.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And when the dragon saw that he was cast down to the earth, he persecuted the woman that brought forth the man <char style="add">child</char>. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And there were given to the woman the two wings of the great eagle, that she might fly into the wilderness unto her place, where she is nourished for a time, and times, and half a time, from the face of the serpent. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And the serpent cast out of his mouth after the woman water as a river, that he might cause her to be carried away by the stream. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the earth helped the woman, and the earth opened her mouth and swallowed up the river which the dragon cast out of his mouth. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And the dragon waxed wroth with the woman, and went away to make war with the rest of her seed, that keep the commandments of God, and hold the testimony of Jesus:</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c"/>
	<para style="nb"><verse number="1" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">I stood etc.</char> connecting the clause with what follows.</char></note>he stood upon the sand of the sea.</para>
	<para style="p">And I saw a beast coming up out of the sea, having ten horns and seven heads, and on his horns ten diadems, and upon his heads names of blasphemy. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And the beast which I saw was like unto a leopard, and his feet were as <char style="add">the feet</char> of a bear, and his mouth as the mouth of a lion: and the dragon gave him his power, and his throne, and great authority. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And <char style="add">I saw</char> one of his heads as though it had been <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">slain</char>.</char></note>smitten unto death; and his death-stroke was healed: and the whole earth wondered after the beast; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and they <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worshipped the dragon, because he gave his authority unto the beast; and they <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worshipped the beast, saying, Who is like unto the beast? and who is able to war with him? <verse number="5" style="v"/>and there was given to him a mouth speaking great things and blasphemies; and there was given to him authority <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">to do</char> his works <char style="it">during</char>. See <ref loc="DAN 11:28">Dan. 11:28</ref>.</char></note>to continue forty and two months. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he opened his mouth for blasphemies against God, to blaspheme his name, and his tabernacle, <char style="add">even</char> them that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">tabernacle</char>.</char></note>dwell in the heaven. <verse number="7" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">And it was given&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. overcome them</char>.</char></note>And it was given unto him to make war with the saints, and to overcome them: and there was given to him authority over every tribe and people and tongue and nation. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And all that dwell on the earth shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship him, <char style="add">every one</char> whose name hath not been <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">written in the book&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. slain from the foundation of the world</char></char></note>written from the foundation of the world in the book of life of the Lamb that hath been slain. <verse number="9" style="v"/>If any man hath an ear, let him hear. <verse number="10" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">The Greek text in this verse is somewhat uncertain.</char></note>If any man <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, leadeth <char style="it">into captivity</char></char></note><char style="add">is</char> for captivity, into captivity he goeth: if any man shall kill with the sword, with the sword must he be killed. Here is the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience and the faith of the saints.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And I saw another beast coming up out of the earth; and he had two horns like unto a lamb, and he spake as a dragon. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And he exerciseth all the authority of the first beast in his sight. And he maketh the earth and them that dwell therein to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship the first beast, whose death-stroke was healed. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And he doeth great signs, that he should even make fire to come down out of heaven upon the earth in the sight of men. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And he deceiveth them that dwell on the earth by reason of the signs which it was given him to do in the sight of the beast; saying to them that dwell on the earth, that they should make an image to the beast who hath the stroke of the sword and lived. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And it was given <char style="add">unto him</char> to give breath to it, <char style="add">even</char> to the image of the beast, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">that even the image of the beast should speak; and he shall cause etc.</char></char></note>that the image of the beast should both speak, and cause that as many as should not <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship the image of the beast should be killed. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he causeth all, the small and the great, and the rich and the poor, and the free and the bond, that there be given them a mark on their right hand, or upon their forehead; <verse number="17" style="v"/>and that no man should be able to buy or to sell, save he that hath the mark, <char style="add">even</char> the name of the beast or the number of his name. <verse number="18" style="v"/>Here is wisdom. He that hath understanding, let him count the number of the beast; for it is the number of a man: and his number is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">Six hundred and sixteen</char>.</char></note>Six hundred and sixty and six.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And I saw, and behold, the Lamb standing on the mount Zion, and with him a hundred and forty and four thousand, having his name, and the name of his Father, written on their foreheads. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And I heard a voice from heaven, as the voice of many waters, and as the voice of a great thunder: and the voice which I heard <char style="add">was</char> as <char style="add">the voice</char> of harpers harping with their harps: <verse number="3" style="v"/>and they sing as it were a new song before the throne, and before the four living creatures and the elders: and no man could learn the song save the hundred and forty and four thousand, <char style="add">even</char> they that had been purchased out of the earth. <verse number="4" style="v"/>These are they that were not defiled with women; for they are virgins. These <char style="add">are</char> they that follow the Lamb whithersoever he goeth. These were purchased from among men, <char style="add">to be</char> the firstfruits unto God and unto the Lamb. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And in their mouth was found no lie: they are without blemish.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And I saw another angel flying in mid heaven, having <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">an eternal gospel</char></char></note>eternal good tidings to proclaim unto them that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">sit</char>.</char></note>dwell on the earth, and unto every nation and tribe and tongue and people; <verse number="7" style="v"/>and he saith with a great voice, Fear God, and give him glory; for the hour of his judgment is come: and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship him that made the heaven and the earth and sea and fountains of waters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And another, a second angel, followed, saying, Fallen, fallen is Babylon the great, that hath made all the nations to drink of the wine of the wrath of her fornication.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And another angel, a third, followed them, saying with a great voice, If any man <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worshippeth the beast and his image, and receiveth a mark on his forehead, or upon his hand, <verse number="10" style="v"/>he also shall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">mingled</char>.</char></note>prepared unmixed in the cup of his anger; and he shall be tormented with fire and brimstone in the presence of the holy angels, and in the presence of the Lamb: <verse number="11" style="v"/>and the smoke of their torment goeth up <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto ages of ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever; and they have no rest day and night, they that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship the beast and his image, and whoso receiveth the mark of his name. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Here is the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">stedfastness</char></char></note>patience of the saints, they that keep the commandments of God, and the faith of Jesus.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v"/>And I heard a voice from heaven saying, Write, Blessed are the dead who die <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">in the Lord. From henceforth, yea, saith the Spirit</char></char></note>in the Lord from henceforth: yea, saith the Spirit, that they may rest from their labors; for their works follow with them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v"/>And I saw, and behold, a white cloud; and on the cloud <char style="add">I saw</char> one sitting like unto a son of man, having on his head a golden crown, and in his hand a sharp sickle. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And another angel came out from the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple, crying with a great voice to him that sat on the cloud, Send forth thy sickle, and reap: for the hour to reap is come; for the harvest of the earth is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">become dry</char>.</char></note>ripe. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he that sat on the cloud cast his sickle upon the earth; and the earth was reaped.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And another angel came out from the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple which is in heaven, he also having a sharp sickle. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And another angel came out from the altar, he that hath power over fire; and he called with a great voice to him that had the sharp sickle, saying, Send forth thy sharp sickle, and gather the clusters of the vine of the earth; for her grapes are fully ripe. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the angel cast his sickle into the earth, and gathered the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">vine</char>.</char></note>vintage of the earth, and cast it into the winepress, the great <char style="add">winepress</char>, of the wrath of God. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the winepress was trodden without the city, and there came out blood from the winepress, even unto the bridles of the horses, as far as a thousand and six hundred furlongs.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And I saw another sign in heaven, great and marvellous, seven angels having seven plagues, <char style="add">which are</char> the last, for in them is finished the wrath of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>And I saw as it were a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">glassy sea</char></char></note>sea of glass mingled with fire; and them that come off victorious from the beast, and from his image, and from the number of his name, standing <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">upon</char></char></note>by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">glassy sea</char></char></note>sea of glass, having harps of God. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And they sing the song of Moses the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservant</char>.</char></note>servant of God, and the song of the Lamb, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Great and marvellous are thy works, O Lord God, the Almighty; righteous and true are thy ways, thou King of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">nations</char>. <ref loc="JER 10:7">Jer. 10:7</ref></char></note>ages. <verse number="4" style="v"/>Who shall not fear, O Lord, and glorify thy name? for thou only art holy; for all the nations shall come and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship before thee; for thy righteous acts have been made manifest.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v"/>And after these things I saw, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple of the tabernacle of the testimony in heaven was opened: <verse number="6" style="v"/>and there came out from the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple the seven angels that had the seven plagues, arrayed <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Many ancient authorities read <char style="it">in linen</char>. <ref loc="REV 19:8">19:8</ref></char></note>with <char style="add">precious</char> stone, pure <char style="add">and</char> bright, and girt about their breasts with golden girdles. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And one of the four living creatures gave unto the seven angels seven golden bowls full of the wrath of God, who liveth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple was filled with smoke from the glory of God, and from his power; and none was able to enter into the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple, till the seven plagues of the seven angels should be finished.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And I heard a great voice out of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple, saying to the seven angels, Go ye, and pour out the seven bowls of the wrath of God into the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v"/>And the first went, and poured out his bowl into the earth; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">there came</char></char></note>it became a noisome and grievous sore upon the men that had the mark of the beast, and that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worshipped his image.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v"/>And the second poured out his bowl into the sea; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">there came</char></char></note>it became blood as of a dead man; and every <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">soul of life</char>.</char></note>living soul died, <char style="add">even</char> the things that were in the sea.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>And the third poured out his bowl into the rivers and the fountains of the waters; <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">and they became</char>.</char></note>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">there came</char></char></note>it became blood. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And I heard the angel of the waters saying, Righteous art thou, who art and who wast, thou Holy One, because thou didst thus <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">judge. Because they&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. prophets, thou hast given them blood also to drink</char></char></note>judge: <verse number="6" style="v"/>for they poured out the blood of saints and prophets, and blood hast thou given them to drink: they are worthy. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And I heard the altar saying, Yea, O Lord God, the Almighty, true and righteous are thy judgments.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And the fourth poured out his bowl upon the sun; and it was given unto <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">him</char></char></note>it to scorch men with fire. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And men were scorched with great heat: and they blasphemed the name of God who hath the power over these plagues; and they repented not to give him glory.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And the fifth poured out his bowl upon the throne of the beast; and his kingdom was darkened; and they gnawed their tongues for pain, <verse number="11" style="v"/>and they blasphemed the God of heaven because of their pains and their sores; and they repented not of their works.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v"/>And the sixth poured out his bowl upon the great river, the <char style="add">river</char> Euphrates; and the water thereof was dried up, that the way might be made ready for the kings that <char style="add">come</char> from the sunrising. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And I saw <char style="add">coming</char> out of the mouth of the dragon, and out of the mouth of the beast, and out of the mouth of the false prophet, three unclean spirits, as it were frogs: <verse number="14" style="v"/>for they are spirits of demons, working signs; which go forth <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">upon</char></char></note>unto the kings of the whole <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">inhabited earth</char>.</char></note>world, to gather them together unto the war of the great day of God, the Almighty. <verse number="15" style="v"/>(Behold, I come as a thief. Blessed is he that watcheth, and keepeth his garments, lest he walk naked, and they see his shame.) <verse number="16" style="v"/>And they gathered them together into the place which is called in Hebrew <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Ar-Magedon</char></char></note>Har-Magedon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And the seventh poured out his bowl upon the air; and there came forth a great voice out of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple, from the throne, saying, It is done: <verse number="18" style="v"/>and there were lightnings, and voices, and thunders; and there was a great earthquake, such as was not since <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">there was a man</char>.</char></note>there were men upon the earth, so great an earthquake, so mighty. <verse number="19" style="v"/>And the great city was divided into three parts, and the cities of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Gentiles</char></char></note>nations fell: and Babylon the great was remembered in the sight of God, to give unto her the cup of the wine of the fierceness of his wrath. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And every island fled away, and the mountains were not found. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And great hail, <char style="add">every stone</char> about the weight of a talent, cometh down out of heaven upon men: and men blasphemed God because of the plague of the hail; for the plague thereof is exceeding great.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And there came one of the seven angels that had the seven bowls, and spake with me, saying, Come hither, I will show thee the judgment of the great harlot that sitteth upon many waters; <verse number="2" style="v"/>with whom the kings of the earth committed fornication, and they that dwell in the earth were made drunken with the wine of her fornication. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And he carried me away in the Spirit into a wilderness: and I saw a woman sitting upon a scarlet-colored beast, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">names full of blasphemy</char></char></note>full of names of blasphemy, having seven heads and ten horns. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the woman was arrayed in purple and scarlet, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">gilded</char>.</char></note>decked with gold and precious stone and pearls, having in her hand a golden cup full of abominations, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and of the unclean things</char></char></note>even the unclean things of her fornication, <verse number="5" style="v"/>and upon her forehead a name written, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a mystery, Babylon the Great</char></char></note><char style="sc">Mystery, Babylon the Great, the Mother of the Harlots and of the Abominations of the Earth</char>. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And I saw the woman drunken with the blood of the saints, and with the blood of the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">witnesses</char>. See <ref loc="REV 2:13">2:13</ref>.</char></note>martyrs of Jesus. And when I saw her, I wondered with a great wonder. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And the angel said unto me, Wherefore didst thou wonder? I will tell thee the mystery of the woman, and of the beast that carrieth her, which hath the seven heads and the ten horns. <verse number="8" style="v"/>The beast that thou sawest was, and is not; and is about to come up out of the abyss, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">and he goeth</char>.</char></note>and to go into perdition. And they that dwell on the earth shall wonder, <char style="add">they</char> whose name hath not been written <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">on</char>.</char></note>in the book of life from the foundation of the world, when they behold the beast, how that he was, and is not, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">shall be present</char>.</char></note>shall come. <verse number="9" style="v"/>Here is the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">meaning</char></char></note>mind that hath wisdom. The seven heads are seven mountains, on which the woman sitteth: <verse number="10" style="v"/>and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">there are</char></char></note>they are seven kings; the five are fallen, the one is, the other is not yet come; and when he cometh, he must continue a little while. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the beast that was, and is not, is himself also an eighth, and is of the seven; and he goeth into perdition. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And the ten horns that thou sawest are ten kings, who have received no kingdom as yet; but they receive authority as kings, with the beast, for one hour. <verse number="13" style="v"/>These have one mind, and they give their power and authority unto the beast. <verse number="14" style="v"/>These shall war against the Lamb, and the Lamb shall overcome them, for he is Lord of lords, and King of kings; and they <char style="add">also shall overcome</char> that are with him, called and chosen and faithful. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And he saith unto me, The waters which thou sawest, where the harlot sitteth, are peoples, and multitudes, and nations, and tongues. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the ten horns which thou sawest, and the beast, these shall hate the harlot, and shall make her desolate and naked, and shall eat her flesh, and shall burn her utterly with fire. <verse number="17" style="v"/>For God did put in their hearts to do his mind, and to come to one mind, and to give their kingdom unto the beast, until the words of God should be accomplished. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the woman whom thou sawest is the great city, which <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">hath a kingdom</char>.</char></note>reigneth over the kings of the earth.</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After these things I saw another angel coming down out of heaven, having great authority; and the earth was lightened with his glory. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he cried with a mighty voice, saying, Fallen, fallen is Babylon the great, and is become a habitation of demons, and a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">prison</char></char></note>hold of every unclean spirit, and a <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">prison</char></char></note>hold of every unclean and hateful bird. <verse number="3" style="v"/>For <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some authorities read <char style="it">of the wine&#160;.&#160;.&#160;. have drunk</char>.</char></note>by <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">the wine of</char>.</char></note>the wine of the wrath of her fornication all the nations are fallen; and the kings of the earth committed fornication with her, and the merchants of the earth waxed rich by the power of her <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">luxury</char></char></note>wantonness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>And I heard another voice from heaven, saying, Come forth, my people, out of her, that ye have no fellowship with her sins, and that ye receive not of her plagues: <verse number="5" style="v"/>for her sins <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">clave together</char></char></note>have reached even unto heaven, and God hath remembered her iniquities. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Render unto her even as she rendered, and double <char style="add">unto her</char> the double according to her works: in the cup which she mingled, mingle unto her double. <verse number="7" style="v"/>How much soever she glorified herself, and waxed <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">luxurious</char></char></note>wanton, so much give her of torment and mourning: for she saith in her heart, I sit a queen, and am no widow, and shall in no wise see mourning. <verse number="8" style="v"/>Therefore in one day shall her plagues come, death, and mourning, and famine; and she shall be utterly burned with fire; for strong is <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">the Lord</char>.</char></note>the Lord God who judged her. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And the kings of the earth, who committed fornication and lived <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">luxuriously</char></char></note>wantonly with her, shall weep and wail over her, when they look upon the smoke of her burning, <verse number="10" style="v"/>standing afar off for the fear of her torment, saying, Woe, woe, the great city, Babylon, the strong city! for in one hour is thy judgment come. <verse number="11" style="v"/>And the merchants of the earth weep and mourn over her, for no man buyeth their <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">cargo</char>.</char></note>merchandise any more; <verse number="12" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">cargo</char>.</char></note>merchandise of gold, and silver, and precious stone, and pearls, and fine linen, and purple, and silk, and scarlet; and all thyine wood, and every vessel of ivory, and every vessel made of most precious wood, and of brass, and iron, and marble; <verse number="13" style="v"/>and cinnamon, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">amomum</char>.</char></note>spice, and incense, and ointment, and frankincense, and wine, and oil, and fine flour, and wheat, and cattle, and sheep; and <char style="add">merchandise</char> of horses and chariots and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bodies</char>. <ref loc="GEN 36:6">Gen. 36:6</ref> (Septuagint).</char></note>slaves; and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lives</char></char></note>souls of men. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the fruits which thy soul lusted after are gone from thee, and all things that were dainty and sumptuous are perished from thee, and <char style="add">men</char> shall find them no more at all. <verse number="15" style="v"/>The merchants of these things, who were made rich by her, shall stand afar off for the fear of her torment, weeping and mourning; <verse number="16" style="v"/>saying, Woe, woe, the great city, she that was arrayed in fine linen and purple and scarlet, and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">gilded</char>.</char></note>decked with gold and precious stone and pearl! <verse number="17" style="v"/>for in one hour so great riches is made desolate. And every shipmaster, and every one that saileth any whither, and mariners, and as many as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">work the sea</char>.</char></note>gain their living by sea, stood afar off, <verse number="18" style="v"/>and cried out as they looked upon the smoke of her burning, saying, What <char style="add">city</char> is like the great city? <verse number="19" style="v"/>And they cast dust on their heads, and cried, weeping and mourning, saying, Woe, woe, the great city, wherein all that had their ships in the sea were made rich by reason of her costliness! for in one hour is she made desolate. <verse number="20" style="v"/>Rejoice over her, thou heaven, and ye saints, and ye apostles, and ye prophets; for God hath judged your judgment on her.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>And <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">one</char>.</char></note>a strong angel took up a stone as it were a great millstone and cast it into the sea, saying, Thus with a mighty fall shall Babylon, the great city, be cast down, and shall be found no more at all. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And the voice of harpers and minstrels and flute-players and trumpeters shall be heard no more at all in thee; and no craftsman, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">of whatsoever craft</char>.</char></note>of whatsoever craft, shall be found any more at all in thee; and the voice of a mill shall be heard no more at all in thee; <verse number="23" style="v"/>and the light of a lamp shall shine no more at all in thee; and the voice of the bridegroom and of the bride shall be heard no more at all in thee: for thy merchants were the princes of the earth; for with thy sorcery were all the nations deceived. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And in her was found the blood of prophets and of saints, and of all that have been slain upon the earth.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>After these things I heard as it were a great voice of a great multitude in heaven, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Hallelujah; Salvation, and glory, and power, belong to our God: <verse number="2" style="v"/>for true and righteous are his judgments; for he hath judged the great harlot, her that corrupted the earth with her fornication, and he hath avenged the blood of his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants at her hand.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="3" style="v"/>And a second time they <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">have said</char>.</char></note>say, Hallelujah. And her smoke goeth up <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever. <verse number="4" style="v"/>And the four and twenty elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshipped God that sitteth on the throne, saying, Amen; Hallelujah. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And a voice came forth from the throne, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Give praise to our God, all ye his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants, ye that fear him, the small and the great.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And I heard as it were the voice of a great multitude, and as the voice of many waters, and as the voice of mighty thunders, saying,</para>
	<para style="mi">Hallelujah: for the Lord our God, the Almighty, reigneth. <verse number="7" style="v"/>Let us rejoice and be exceeding glad, and let us give the glory unto him: for the marriage of the Lamb is come, and his wife hath made herself ready. <verse number="8" style="v"/>And it was given unto her that she should array herself in fine linen, bright <char style="add">and</char> pure: for the fine linen is the righteous acts of the saints.</para>
	<para style="m"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And he saith unto me, Write, Blessed are they that are bidden to the marriage supper of the Lamb. And he saith unto me, These are true words of God. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And I fell down before his feet to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship him. And he saith unto me, See thou do it not: I am a fellow-servant with thee and with thy brethren that hold the testimony of Jesus: <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship God: for the testimony of Jesus is the spirit of prophecy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And I saw the heaven opened; and behold, a white horse, and he that sat thereon <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit <char style="it">called</char>.</char></note>called Faithful and True; and in righteousness he doth judge and make war. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And his eyes <char style="add">are</char> a flame of fire, and upon his head <char style="add">are</char> many diadems; and he hath a name written which no one knoweth but he himself. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And he <char style="add">is</char> arrayed in a garment <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">dipped in</char>.</char></note>sprinkled with blood: and his name is called The Word of God. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the armies which are in heaven followed him upon white horses, clothed in fine linen, white <char style="add">and</char> pure. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And out of his mouth proceedeth a sharp sword, that with it he should smite the nations: and he shall rule them with a rod of iron: and he treadeth the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">winepress of the wine of the fierceness</char>.</char></note>winepress of the fierceness of the wrath of God, the Almighty. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And he hath on his garment and on his thigh a name written, <char style="nd">King of Kings, and Lord of Lords</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/>And I saw <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">one</char>.</char></note>an angel standing in the sun; and he cried with a loud voice, saying to all the birds that fly in mid heaven, Come <char style="add">and</char> be gathered together unto the great supper of God; <verse number="18" style="v"/>that ye may eat the flesh of kings, and the flesh of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">military tribunes</char>. Greek <char style="it">chiliarchs</char>.</char></note>captains, and the flesh of mighty men, and the flesh of horses and of them that sit thereon, and the flesh of all men, both free and bond, and small and great.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v"/>And I saw the beast, and the kings of the earth, and their armies, gathered together to make war against him that sat upon the horse, and against his army. <verse number="20" style="v"/>And the beast was taken, and with him the false prophet that wrought the signs in his sight, wherewith he deceived them that had received the mark of the beast and them that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worshipped his image: they two were cast alive into the lake of fire that burneth with brimstone: <verse number="21" style="v"/>and the rest were killed with the sword of him that sat upon the horse, <char style="add">even the sword</char> which came forth out of his mouth: and all the birds were filled with their flesh.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And I saw an angel coming down out of heaven, having the key of the abyss and a great chain <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">upon</char>.</char></note>in his hand. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And he laid hold on the dragon, the old serpent, which is the Devil and Satan, and bound him for a thousand years, <verse number="3" style="v"/>and cast him into the abyss, and shut <char style="add">it</char>, and sealed <char style="add">it</char> over him, that he should deceive the nations no more, until the thousand years should be finished: after this he must be loosed for a little time.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v"/>And I saw thrones, and they sat upon them, and judgment was given unto them: and <char style="add">I saw</char> the souls of them that had been beheaded for the testimony of Jesus, and for the word of God, and such as <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worshipped not the beast, neither his image, and received not the mark upon their forehead and upon their hand; and they lived, and reigned with Christ a thousand years. <verse number="5" style="v"/>The rest of the dead lived not until the thousand years should be finished. This is the first resurrection. <verse number="6" style="v"/>Blessed and holy is he that hath part in the first resurrection: over these the second death hath no <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">authority</char></char></note>power; but they shall be priests of God and of Christ, and shall reign with him <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities read <char style="it">the</char>.</char></note>a thousand years.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v"/>And when the thousand years are finished, Satan shall be loosed out of his prison, <verse number="8" style="v"/>and shall come forth to deceive the nations which are in the four corners of the earth, Gog and Magog, to gather them together to the war: the number of whom is as the sand of the sea. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And they went up over the breadth of the earth, and compassed the camp of the saints about, and the beloved city: and fire came down <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities insert <char style="it">from God</char>.</char></note>out of heaven, and devoured them. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And the devil that deceived them was cast into the lake of fire and brimstone, where are also the beast and the false prophet; and they shall be tormented day and night <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v"/>And I saw a great white throne, and him that sat upon it, from whose face the earth and the heaven fled away; and there was found no place for them. <verse number="12" style="v"/>And I saw the dead, the great and the small, standing before the throne; and books were opened: and another book was opened, which is <char style="add">the book</char> of life: and the dead were judged out of the things which were written in the books, according to their works. <verse number="13" style="v"/>And the sea gave up the dead that were in it; and death and Hades gave up the dead that were in them: and they were judged every man according to their works. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And death and Hades were cast into the lake of fire. This is the second death, <char style="add">even</char> the lake of fire. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And if any was not found written in the book of life, he was cast into the lake of fire.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And I saw a new heaven and a new earth: for the first heaven and the first earth are passed away; and the sea is no more. <verse number="2" style="v"/>And I saw <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the holy city Jerusalem coming down new out of heaven</char></char></note>the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, made ready as a bride adorned for her husband. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And I heard a great voice out of the throne saying, Behold, the tabernacle of God is with men, and he shall <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">tabernacle</char>.</char></note>dwell with them, and they shall be his peoples, and God himself shall be with them, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities omit, and be <char style="it">their God</char>.</char></note><char style="add">and be</char> their God: <verse number="4" style="v"/>and he shall wipe away every tear from their eyes; and death shall be no more; neither shall there be mourning, nor crying, nor pain, any more: the first things are passed away. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And he that sitteth on the throne said, Behold, I make all things new. And he saith, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Write, These words are faithful and true</char>.</char></note>Write: for these words are faithful and true. <verse number="6" style="v"/>And he said unto me, They are come to pass. I am the Alpha and the Omega, the beginning and the end. I will give unto him that is athirst of the fountain of the water of life freely. <verse number="7" style="v"/>He that overcometh shall inherit these things; and I will be his God, and he shall be my son. <verse number="8" style="v"/>But for the fearful, and unbelieving, and abominable, and murderers, and fornicators, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars, their part <char style="add">shall be</char> in the lake that burneth with fire and brimstone; which is the second death.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v"/>And there came one of the seven angels who had the seven bowls, who were laden with the seven last plagues; and he spake with me, saying, Come hither, I will show thee the bride, the wife of the Lamb. <verse number="10" style="v"/>And he carried me away in the Spirit to a mountain great and high, and showed me the holy city Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, <verse number="11" style="v"/>having the glory of God: her <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">luminary</char>.</char></note>light was like unto a stone most precious, as it were a jasper stone, clear as crystal: <verse number="12" style="v"/>having a wall great and high; having twelve <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates, and at the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates twelve angels; and names written thereon, which are <char style="add">the names</char> of the twelve tribes of the children of Israel: <verse number="13" style="v"/>on the east were three <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates; and on the north three <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates; and on the south three <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates; and on the west <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>three gates. <verse number="14" style="v"/>And the wall of the city had twelve foundations, and on them twelve names of the twelve apostles of the Lamb. <verse number="15" style="v"/>And he that spake with me had for a measure a golden reed to measure the city, and the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates thereof, and the wall thereof. <verse number="16" style="v"/>And the city lieth foursquare, and the length thereof is as great as the breadth: and he measured the city with the reed, twelve thousand furlongs: the length and the breadth and the height thereof are equal. <verse number="17" style="v"/>And he measured the wall thereof, a hundred and forty and four cubits, <char style="add">according to</char> the measure of a man, that is, of an angel. <verse number="18" style="v"/>And the building of the wall thereof was jasper: and the city was pure gold, like unto pure glass. <verse number="19" style="v"/>The foundations of the wall of the city were adorned with all manner of precious stones. The first foundation was jasper; the second, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">lapis lazuli</char></char></note>sapphire; the third, chalcedony; the fourth, emerald; <verse number="20" style="v"/>the fifth, sardonyx; the sixth, sardius; the seventh, chrysolite; the eighth, beryl; the ninth, topaz; the tenth, chrysoprase; the eleventh, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sapphire</char></char></note>jacinth; the twelfth, amethyst. <verse number="21" style="v"/>And the twelve <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates were twelve pearls; each one of the several <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates was of one pearl: and the street of the city was pure gold, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">transparent as glass</char></char></note>as it were transparent glass. <verse number="22" style="v"/>And I saw no <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple therein: for the Lord God the Almighty, and the Lamb, are the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">sanctuary</char></char></note>temple thereof. <verse number="23" style="v"/>And the city hath no need of the sun, neither of the moon, to shine upon it: for the glory of God did lighten it, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">and the Lamb, the lamp thereof</char></char></note>and the lamp thereof <char style="add">is</char> the Lamb. <verse number="24" style="v"/>And the nations shall walk <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">by</char></char></note>amidst the light thereof: and the kings of the earth bring their glory into it. <verse number="25" style="v"/>And the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates thereof shall in no wise be shut by day (for there shall be no night there): <verse number="26" style="v"/>and they shall bring the glory and the honor of the nations into it: <verse number="27" style="v"/>and there shall in no wise enter into it anything <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">common</char>.</char></note>unclean, or he that <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">doeth</char></char></note>maketh an abomination and a lie: but only they that are written in the Lamb&#8217;s book of life.</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c"/>
	<para style="nb"><verse number="1" style="v"/>And he showed me a river of water of life, bright as crystal, proceeding out of the throne of God and of <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the Lamb. In the midst of the street thereof, and on either side of the river, was the tree of life etc.</char></char></note>the Lamb, <verse number="2" style="v"/>in the midst of the street thereof. And on this side of the river and on that was <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">a tree</char></char></note>the tree of life, bearing twelve <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">crops of fruit</char></char></note><char style="add">manner of</char> fruits, yielding its fruit every month: and the leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations. <verse number="3" style="v"/>And there shall be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">no more anything accursed</char></char></note>no curse any more: and the throne of God and of the Lamb shall be therein: and his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants shall serve him; <verse number="4" style="v"/>and they shall see his face; and his name <char style="add">shall be</char> on their foreheads. <verse number="5" style="v"/>And there shall be night no more; and they need no light of lamp, neither light of sun; for the Lord God shall give them light: and they shall reign <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">unto the ages of the ages</char>.</char></note>for ever and ever.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v"/>And he said unto me, These words are faithful and true: and the Lord, the God of the spirits of the prophets, sent his angel to show unto his <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">bondservants</char>.</char></note>servants the things which must shortly come to pass. <verse number="7" style="v"/>And behold, I come quickly. Blessed is he that keepeth the words of the prophecy of this book.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v"/>And I John am he that heard and saw these things. And when I heard and saw, I fell down to <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">See marginal note on <ref loc="REV 3:9">3:9</ref>.</char></note>worship before the feet of the angel that showed me these things. <verse number="9" style="v"/>And he saith unto me, See thou do it not: I am a fellow-servant with thee and with thy brethren the prophets, and with them that keep the words of this book: worship God.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v"/>And he saith unto me, Seal not up the words of the prophecy of this book; for the time is at hand. <verse number="11" style="v"/>He that is unrighteous, let him do unrighteousness <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">yet more</char></char></note>still: and he that is filthy, let him be made filthy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">yet more</char></char></note>still: and he that is righteous, let him do righteousness <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">yet more</char></char></note>still: and he that is holy, let him be made holy <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">yet more</char></char></note>still. <verse number="12" style="v"/>Behold, I come quickly; and my <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">wages</char></char></note>reward is with me, to render to each man according as his work is. <verse number="13" style="v"/>I am the Alpha and the Omega, the first and the last, the beginning and the end. <verse number="14" style="v"/>Blessed are they that wash their robes, that they may have <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">the authority over</char>. Compare <ref loc="REV 6:8">6:8</ref>.</char></note>the right <char style="add">to come</char> to the tree of life, and may enter in by the <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">portals</char>.</char></note>gates into the city. <verse number="15" style="v"/>Without are the dogs, and the sorcerers, and the fornicators, and the murderers, and the idolaters, and every one that loveth and <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">doeth</char>. Compare <ref loc="REV 21:27">21:27</ref>.</char></note>maketh a lie.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v"/>I Jesus have sent mine angel to testify unto you these things <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">over</char>.</char></note>for the churches. I am the root and the offspring of David, the bright, the morning star.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v"/><note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, <char style="it">Both</char></char></note>And the Spirit and the bride say, Come. And he that heareth, let him say, Come. And he that is athirst, let him come: he that will, let him take the water of life freely.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v"/>I testify unto every man that heareth the words of the prophecy of this book, If any man shall add <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">upon</char>.</char></note>unto them, God shall add <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Greek <char style="it">upon</char>.</char></note>unto him the plagues which are written in this book: <verse number="19" style="v"/>and if any man shall take away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God shall take away his part from the tree of life, and out of the holy city, <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Or, even from <char style="it">the things which are written</char></char></note>which are written in this book.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v"/>He who testifieth these things saith, Yea: I come quickly. Amen: come, Lord Jesus.</para>
	<para style="b"/>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v"/>The grace of the Lord Jesus <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Some ancient authorities add <char style="it">Christ</char>.</char></note>be <note caller="-" style="f"><char style="ft">Two ancient authorities read <char style="it">with all</char>.</char></note>with the saints. Amen.</para>
</usx>